<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three tracts of the great medicine of philosophers for humane and metalline bodies ... all written in Latine by Eirenæus Philalethes ... ; translated into English for the benefit of the studious, by a lover of art and them.</title>
            <title>Tres tractatus de metallorum transmutatione. English</title>
            <author>Philalethes, Eirenaeus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12001211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12001211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 77:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three tracts of the great medicine of philosophers for humane and metalline bodies ... all written in Latine by Eirenæus Philalethes ... ; translated into English for the benefit of the studious, by a lover of art and them.</title>
                  <title>Tres tractatus de metallorum transmutatione. English</title>
                  <author>Philalethes, Eirenaeus.</author>
                  <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 186 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Tres tractatus de metallorum transmutatione.</note>
                  <note>"A short mauuduction [sic] to the caelestial ruby" and "The fountain of chymical philosophy" each has special t.p., the former not included in the paging.</note>
                  <note>Authorship attributed to George Starkey. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>First English ed. Cf. Wing; first published in Latin, Amsterdam, 1668.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. Ars metallorum metamorphoseths -- II. Brevis manuductio ad rubinum coelestem -- III. Fons chymicae philosophiae.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alchemy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Three Tracts</hi> Of the Great Medicine OF PHILOSOPHERS FOR Humane and Metalline BODIES.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. Intituled, Ars Metallorum Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſeos.</item>
                     <item>II. Brevis Manuductio ad Rubinum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtem.</item>
                     <item>III. Fons Chymicae Philoſophiae.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All Written in Latine</hi> By <hi>EIRENAE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S PHILALETHES</hi> Coſmopolita.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh <hi>for the Benefit of the</hi> Studious <hi>By a Lover of</hi> Art <hi>and</hi> Them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and ſold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet</hi> in <hi>Holy-well-Lane Shoreditch,</hi> Anno 1694.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:2"/>
                  <head>THE Publiſhers Preface To the READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEing Converſant for many <hi>Years</hi> with <hi>Writings of this kind,</hi> and alſo with <hi>not a few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> in purſuit of the <hi>Maſtery,</hi> who together with <hi>me</hi> have not only <hi>read</hi> the <hi>true and falſe Books</hi> with equal <hi>Credit,</hi> (by which thou may judge of the <hi>Event</hi> in <hi>practice</hi>) but alſo have <hi>imbraced</hi> the Notions or Practice of <hi>confident Affirmers</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52222:3"/>with <hi>ſuitable Credit</hi> to the hopes of <hi>Attaining.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Labyrinth</hi> having no more poſſeſſion of me, and the <hi>Theory</hi> of <hi>Principles</hi> ſo far prevailing as to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> me to make <hi>choice</hi> of <hi>Authors</hi> and Perſons to <hi>converſe</hi> with, can do no leſs then <hi>contribute</hi> as much as in me lyes to the <hi>help</hi> of thoſe <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Searchers</hi> under the ſame <hi>Difficulty.</hi> In order to effect this I have already <hi>communicated</hi> a ſhort but candid <hi>Tract</hi> not long ſince, which was <hi>communicated</hi> to me by my very <hi>good Friend,</hi> as may be ſeen in his <hi>Kind Letter,</hi> in which it was <hi>incloſed &amp; Printed</hi> with it, called <hi>PHILADELPHIA;</hi> which I think in no ways falls ſhort of the <hi>Title.</hi> This I thought might have <hi>terminated</hi> my Care of that kind,
<pb facs="tcp:52222:3"/>contenting my ſelf that every one, tho perhaps more <hi>capable,</hi> had not born a <hi>Proportion;</hi> but receiving this <hi>ſecond Kindneſs</hi> from <hi>my Friend,</hi> wherein he <hi>freely communicates</hi> his <hi>Thoughts</hi> according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and my <hi>Requeſt;</hi> which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded my ſelf could not but <hi>prove</hi> of <hi>advantage</hi> to the <hi>Searchers of Art,</hi> eſpecially in their <hi>Beginnings.</hi> And let it not be an <hi>Objection,</hi> that he does not <hi>aſſume</hi> the <hi>Title</hi> of a <hi>Poſſeſſor,</hi> but rather an <hi>Argument</hi> of his <hi>Sincerity,</hi> ſince I believe it poſſible that ſomething may be gained from ſuch early <hi>thoughts,</hi> which more ripe <hi>Experience</hi> denies. I meet with <hi>confirmation</hi> in this from a great <hi>Maſter,</hi> Viz. <hi>Eirenaeus Philalethes,</hi> in his Preface to his Expoſitions on <hi>Ripleys Compound</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52222:4"/>of <hi>Alchymy.</hi> Where Speaking of the Benefit he had Received from Authors, has this expreſſion; <q>
                        <hi>ſome in good ſooth, who are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of this Secret, Write more Edifyingly to the inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a</hi> Tiro, <hi>then thoſe whom Skill hath made Crafty.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>However leaſt this ſhould not be ſufficient to recompence thy <hi>Expence</hi> I have added three <hi>excellent Tracts</hi> which I received from the Hands of a <hi>Friend</hi> that had taken ſome pains and care in their <hi>Tranſlation</hi> from the Latine Copies Printed in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and I take this Oportunity the rather, becauſe the firſt of them is ſo highly <hi>Commended</hi> by my <hi>Friend.</hi> This is <hi>Intituled Ars Metallorum, &amp;c.</hi> Which indeed well Anſwers the <hi>End.</hi> Here the
<pb facs="tcp:52222:4"/>Studious may meet with help, the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant with <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Information</hi> and Reproachers and <hi>Myſo-Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micks</hi> with Demonstration beyond Diſpute.</p>
                  <p>The Second <hi>Brevis Manudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, &amp;c.</hi> In which not only the field in which it lyes, and the Reaſon of its <hi>Epithet,</hi> but the means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is alſo ſhaddowed forth. And indeed there are ſome peculiar <hi>Hints</hi> that are not <hi>common.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third <hi>Fons Chymicae, &amp;c.</hi> As this Anſwers the Title ſo no doubt it will the deſire of Searchers. For as nothing is more needful, ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more earnestly ſought then the true <hi>Fountain, Bath</hi> or <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum</hi> in which <hi>Sol</hi> is Diſsolved and amended.</p>
                  <p>Thus Reader having performed
<pb facs="tcp:52222:5"/>this in good will to the Studious give me leave to withdraw, and ſpend my time more privately: And do thou endeavour to bear a Proportion with me in <hi>communicating,</hi> rather then Carp; at what perhaps thou cannot Imitate; However ſince I ſeek no Honour from thee I ſhall be ſafe from the Contrary.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By Remaining, PHILOMATHES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:5"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Eſteemed Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>LYing under the Promiſe in my laſt (in which I ſent <hi>Philadelphia</hi>) according to thy earneſt Requeſt, that I would communicate my thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Secret Art of <hi>Hermes,</hi> and finding that little Tract ſo Generouſly communicated to the World, haſtens the fulfilling it.</p>
                  <p>But in the firſt Place let me premiſe, that as theſe are my Thoughts and Conceptions, let them merit no otherways then ſuch, always preferring the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of known <hi>Maſters</hi> to all, and no farther then theſe agree with them, and by them are
<pb facs="tcp:52222:6"/>Confirmed truſt or imbrace them.</p>
                  <p>Having obſerved in my <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> with thoſe Studious in this Art, that not one amongſt many were poſſeſſed with ſo much as the <hi>Theory</hi> of the Poſſibility of it, tho of many Years Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was a Motive to me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider things Radically, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembring the ſaying of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, 'that it was never found of any by Chance.</hi> And in the firſt place the poſſibility of the thing, whence I might be aſſured that it was, nor that only, but that it was ſufficient to recompence the Time, Coſt and Labour ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to it.</p>
                  <p>I therefore (after many Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) betook my ſelf to the moſt valued and candid <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> treating of the Theory and
<pb facs="tcp:52222:6"/>Poſſibility of the thing, ſuch as were recommended by thoſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knowing; as <hi>Treviſans</hi> four <hi>Books, &amp;c. Sendivogius</hi> and many more, but one ſmall Piece fell into my hands of greateſt value which I think fit to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was Intituled, <hi>Ars Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallorum, &amp;c.</hi> Written by <hi>Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus Philalethes,</hi> this fully ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting the poſſibility &amp; worth of the <hi>Art;</hi> in a Stile not ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous but full of Learning and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration; which was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by all but by none more then <hi>Philadelphia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus proſecuting this effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, I found it not very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to conceive the poſſibility of ſuch an Exaltation of <hi>imperfect Bodies</hi> to perfection; ſeing that
<pb facs="tcp:52222:7"/>no Eſſential Difference was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them but only accidental, and that all had one and the ſame Matter, which is eaſily known to be <hi>Mercurial,</hi> and that <hi>Natures</hi> Deſign or End was, if ſhe could have worked free from Accidents, to have brought all to perfection.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it will eaſily be granted &amp; gathered from hence, that if a <hi>pluſquam perfection</hi> of <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> endued with <hi>fixity</hi> and <hi>pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trability</hi> could be attained of the ſame Nature theſe <hi>imperfect Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> (ſo much of them as is <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial</hi> ſayes <hi>Philadelphia</hi>) might be influenced and Enobled to the Perfection of <hi>Gold;</hi> whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is the <hi>Standard.</hi> So that as much as any Body ſhall exceed in
<pb facs="tcp:52222:7"/>
                     <hi>Tincture</hi> this <hi>Standard,</hi> ſo much it is capable of communicating to thoſe ſhort of it. <hi>Vide Philadelphia, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that we are not to think this <hi>Tranſmutation of Metals</hi> is a changing of one Species into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as thoſe who conceive <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> differ after that Manner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) neither any thing contrary to Nature; but only changing of the ſame <hi>Aureous Matter</hi> from the ſtate of <hi>Crudity</hi> to the ſtate of <hi>Maturity,</hi> in natures own way. I could give Examples in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this, but ſeing it is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully ſhown by Maſters of the <hi>Art</hi> themſelves it ought to ſuffice.</p>
                  <p>And for the poſſibility of Multiplying this <hi>Tincture</hi> it is plentifully ſhown by many (at
<pb facs="tcp:52222:8"/>which ſome Carp) neither is it hard to conceive ſince our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhows in common Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there is no end, as it were, of the power of Ferment, as it comes to have reiterated Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on ſuitable matters.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Conſiderations Leads immediatly, through an neceſſity, to abandon all thoughts of <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Patients</hi> out of kind, or that are not <hi>Homogeneal</hi> to the bodys to be mended, and one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this no ſmall ſecurity to a young Searcher againſt the many Pretences and Practices of thoſe who proſecute thoſe things blindly and Corruptly.</p>
                  <p>How this may be effected is indeed worth enquiry. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us conſider that next.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52222:8"/>
Nature being arrived at her End in the perfection of <hi>Gold</hi> the <hi>Standard,</hi> and fallen ſhort of it in imperfect Metals through Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, we to perfect them, muſt go as near to Perfection as we can to begin, and as <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſay where Nature left. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we hope to move this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to a <hi>pluſquam perfection,</hi> the Perfection muſt dye. Our great Care then muſt be to ſeek and find ſuch an <hi>Agent</hi> that is capable to effect it. Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be, from all candid <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> and reaſon it ſelf an <hi>homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneous Humid:</hi> Which doth not only Kill the Body but dyes with it, and are both raiſed farr more Noble and Perfect, endued with a Multiplicative Power. Like as
<pb facs="tcp:52222:9"/>a Grain of <hi>Corn,</hi> when by its own Humidity, in a proper Matrix, is thus Killed and Raiſed, it put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth many Grains, each en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the ſame Multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Virtue with the firſt Seed, which may be Multiplyed, as it were, Infinitely.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Humidity,</hi> I very well know, is the deſire of all true Searchers of Art; who know by ſad Experience how Difficultly it is obtained: But how difficult ſoever it may be thought or found to be, it muſt be attained or we Labour without Reward.</p>
                  <p>To reincrudate, neceſſarily requires a <hi>Crudity;</hi> and as this is to Dye, Riſe and Dwell with the Body reduced, muſt alſo through neceſsity be the ſame in
<pb facs="tcp:52222:9"/>kind and only differ with reſpect to Crudity: Which then will naturally follow to be that <hi>Crude</hi> out of which Perfect <hi>Gold</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; according to all candid Writers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philadelphia</hi> has Illuſtrated and <hi>Bernard Treviſan</hi> with others, has affirmed that <hi>Mercury</hi> to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> is like common Water to <hi>Vegetables,</hi> Viz. their Matter. Therefore the Crudeſt <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> muſt be the only <hi>Agent</hi> to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crudate ripe <hi>Mercurial</hi> Bodies.</p>
                  <p>I have obſerved a pretty Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs between <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Metallick</hi> Works, and Water in <hi>Vegetables.</hi> For if I would produce a <hi>Vegetable</hi> it muſt be by Seed and Water, if a <hi>Metal</hi> it muſt be by <hi>Mercury</hi> and its Ferment. If I would purifie a <hi>Vegetable Body</hi>) which is Water
<pb facs="tcp:52222:10"/>congealed) as <hi>Sugar, Salt,</hi> &amp;c. which are Capable of being mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with extraneous Earth or <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> I muſt diſſolve it in Water, which Water being of the Unity of its Matter poſſeſſes it and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the <hi>Feces,</hi> which being eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated leave the Body free from thoſe impurities. Juſt ſo in Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Metals</hi> (which are <hi>Mercury</hi> Coagulated) we Diſſolve them in a ſufficient quantity of <hi>Mercurial</hi> matter, (by Fuſion) then evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Crude <hi>Mercurial</hi> Matter on a Teſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the pure <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> remains behind. In this Work of Refining Running <hi>Mercury</hi> is not choſe or uſed but Corporeal; as in <hi>Luna Saturn</hi> is Choſe, and in <hi>Sol Antimony. Silver</hi> being leſs perfect, is purified by <hi>Lead,</hi> leſs <hi>Crude; Gold</hi> moſt perfect is puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:52222:10"/>by <hi>Antimony</hi> moſt <hi>Crude.</hi> And as <hi>Antimony</hi> is too Crude for <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> ſo is <hi>Lead</hi> not Crude enough for <hi>Gold.</hi> From hence may be Learned the Reaſon and Ground of the Refiners <hi>Art.</hi> And further to manifeſt the difference in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity between <hi>Lead</hi> and <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> I have obſerved in the union of them with other <hi>Metals</hi> this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent effect. When in the Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Lead Oar,</hi> we add <hi>Iron,</hi> and what elſe may be requiſite and a fuſion of both is made, the metal that reſides is malleable. But if the like be done with <hi>Antimony,</hi> we find, inſtead of that, a brittle <hi>Metalline</hi> Maſs. The Reaſon of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Iron</hi> in ſuch Works is from hence, the <hi>Mercuriality</hi> or <hi>Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> part in the <hi>Oar</hi> is held in Chains by the abundance of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure
<pb facs="tcp:52222:11"/>
                     <hi>Sulphur,</hi> which violently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts to its ſelf the <hi>Metallick Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> in the <hi>Iron,</hi> through which Union, the Accidents in great meaſure are thrown off, and the <hi>Metal</hi> reſides in the Bottom. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we ſee that when ſome ripe <hi>Metal</hi> is mixed with a greater Quantity of Crudity or imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the immature is blown off and the ripe remains: But if the Crude too much exceed the ripe it will carry that alſo: whence it is eaſy to err in Quantities, and degrees of Fire. For if a ſmall Quantity of <hi>Silver</hi> be mixed with a great Quantity of <hi>Antimony,</hi> and that haſtily blown off, how eaſily do this <hi>Crudity</hi> Conquer and carry off the Ripe Body. This by the By.</p>
                  <p>But to return to that which is
<pb facs="tcp:52222:11"/>ſooner ſpoke then done, <hi>viz.</hi> The Reduction of a perfect Body by a Crude Agent; and as this is no doubt the End of our Labour, ſo we ſhall find it attended with many Difficulties. Firſt in fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Extreams; then in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them which muſt be through Mediums; and perhaps in purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for Crudity is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally attended with Impurity, and every perfect Generation and Union requires purity in the Principles.</p>
                  <p>The Mediums of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> ought to be Adapted to the Nature of the Extreams, leaſt they ſhould alinate rather then unite. Alſo Mediums imply middle Natures, that are not ſo Crude as the one, nor ſo ripe as the other.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſay that <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                        <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52222:12"/>begin to move, leaſt we Return without Recompence.</p>
                  <p>I am not ignorant that the Practice is diverſly conceived by Searchers as well as Principles; for the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> having ſpoken Alluſively of both, we may eaſily miſtake. But I am obliged by the neceſſity of it to believe the Principles were the ſame to all true Philoſophers; Neither can I admit, for the ſame Reaſon, of any other thoughts of their Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. I remember a ſaying in <hi>Ars Metallorum</hi> very confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where he ſpeaks of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Art from Argument, and amongſt others brings this as none of the leaſt. <q>
                        <hi>This at leaſt is clear, that it is ſo far from being a new Device, that there have been
<pb facs="tcp:52222:12"/>men skilful in it through many Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries's of Ages, who being Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent both in Tongue and Nation, and very many of them Contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary have written ſo Agreeingly of the Art, that they cannot be proved by ſuch as underſtand them either to Corrupt or diverſly to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſo much as one Operation.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This perhaps may ſeem ſtrange at firſt, as it did to me being prepoſſeſſed with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That their ſeeming Contradictions were owing to their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Working on divers Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. But conſidering the thing I found that he ſaid not this alone, but that all admoniſh that we ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:52222:13"/>wherein they all agree and there was the truth. This admits that they do all agree, and conſequently the ſame Principles and Practice or it could not be ſo. There fore reſolving to make an Eſſay, I deeply weighed their ſayings: Proſecuted them one by one, Obſerved their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication one of another, and at length perceived a Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beyond compare, moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly couched in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, yea in thoſe I before thought moſt differing: Tho not indeed without <hi>Tropes, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> are theſe things expreſſed; to conceal them from the Vulgar.</p>
                  <p>In ſhort therefore let us
<pb facs="tcp:52222:13"/>not, like the <hi>Alchymiſts</hi> of <hi>Sendivogius,</hi> propoſe to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the thing by <hi>Mercury</hi> alone or <hi>Sulphur</hi> alone, but let both be the <hi>Subjects</hi> of our <hi>Contemplation</hi> and Practice. For if I conceive aright the matter of this moſt ſecret Maſtery is a <hi>Sulphureous Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> and the <hi>Stone</hi> it ſelf nothing elſe but that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulated; which then is a <hi>Mercurial Sulphureity</hi> penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, tinging and fixing.</p>
                  <p>Admit of my ſhort <hi>Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but believe, this is not obtained without the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious <hi>Smiles</hi> of <hi>Diana</hi> (who parting from the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> appears Horned, the <hi>Earth interpoſing</hi>) and <hi>Venus
<pb facs="tcp:52222:14"/>Orient</hi> who foreruns the <hi>Sun</hi> and proclaims the joyful day approaching.</p>
                  <p>Excuſe me with Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that I thus preſume to mention things ſo Secret, ſince we have little elſe but ſuch Shadows to Satiate our Longing Minds, till the <hi>Sun</hi> ariſe &amp; overcome the night of <hi>Moon-ſhine</hi> as well as Darkneſs and all the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> wholly become <hi>Sol</hi>'s then is the time to write <hi>Adeptus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus with hearty Wiſhes of Succeſs accept this <hi>Cordial Communication</hi> of my thoughts, and continue the Bond of Friendſhip inviolable as doth thy Well-Wiſhing and Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Friend,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>PHILETAEROS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52222:14"/>
                  <head>TRACT The FIRST</head>
                  <head type="sub">The ART of the <hi>Tranſmutation</hi> OF METALLS.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Concerning the Authority of the Art, its Profeſſors, and the way of ſearching out the Secret.</head>
                     <p>SEeing that all <hi>Men,</hi> of whatſoever <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>Fortune,</hi> do propoſe ſome Bounds to themſelves of their hours ſpent in ſearching out of things; to wit that they may obtain the Skilfulneſs of that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52222:15"/>
                        <hi>Art</hi> in which they are Converſant, and uſe all Induſtry that they may come to the <hi>Perfection.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Notwithſtanding this <hi>Fortune</hi> bleſſeth very few, for altho many Labour after <hi>Architecture</hi> but few <hi>Archimedes</hi>'s are found. Many however they adict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Phyſick,</hi> yet there are not many <hi>Paratelſas</hi>'s, few endued with the Wit of <hi>Helmont;</hi> nay if they can arrive to an Indifferency in <hi>their</hi> Art, they will not think they have loſt their Coſt and Pains. Hence it comes to paſs, that no one can think he has ſtudied in vain, tho' every <hi>Geometrician</hi> cannot be equal to <hi>Archimedes,</hi> or <hi>Poet</hi> to <hi>Homer,</hi> or <hi>Rhetorician</hi> to <hi>Cicero.</hi> For that alſo Rhetoricians of an inferiour ſtamp, may (according to the Talent beſtowed upon them) profit the Common-Wealth. Any men may I ſay, altho' ſomething un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful in that Art in which they have been converſant, be thought uſeful in that Common-Wealth where they live.</p>
                     <p>But as many as do adict themſelves to the <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> do ſeem to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52222:15"/>preſs after a very uſeful thing, at leaſt not unwiſely nor unprofitably. For the top of this <hi>Art.</hi> is <hi>Artifice</hi> it ſelf, which who hath attained, hath acquired the <hi>Heighth,</hi> but he that hath not proceeded hither, will carry back no <hi>profit.</hi> For no thing but the Loſs both of <hi>Mony</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> comes from the <hi>Science</hi> of <hi>Alchimy</hi> half Learned. Moreover he will expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf both to be <hi>Laughed</hi> at, and Diſgraced by <hi>Myſo-Chymicks.</hi> But the object of the <hi>Art</hi> is ſo <hi>Noble,</hi> that it promiſes <hi>Infinite Riches</hi> to the Poſſeſſor, and moreover <hi>moſt perfect Health.</hi> Hence it comes to paſs, that there is hardly any Idiot, who after he has heard never ſo little of the <hi>Art,</hi> doth not preſently Apply himſelf to the Diſquiſition thereof, and preſently puts on the Name of <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> and as ſoon as he hath Conceived any hopes, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome Receipts, he forthwith claims the title of <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> But leaſt that he ſhould ſeem to adore a fooliſh <hi>Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> every one according to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own <hi>Genius,</hi> Excogitates <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties,</hi> and according to what ability he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52222:16"/>is of, builds <hi>Furnaces,</hi> gets him <hi>Glaſſes,</hi> and ſets upon the <hi>Work</hi> with a wonderful Solemnity. So he Laviſheth away his <hi>Money,</hi> till it is too late, and very little, if any ſubſiſtance is left. Leaſt in the mean time he ſhould be reproved of <hi>mad Raſhneſs,</hi> he can talk ye of the <hi>first Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallick-matter;</hi> the <hi>Rotation</hi> of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the <hi>Marriage</hi> of <hi>Gabritius</hi> with <hi>Bega,</hi> and that in an <hi>Idiom</hi> commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, he ſhall cite ye the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Expound</hi> them at his pleaſure, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly comfort himſelf with the hopes of his future <hi>Fortune.</hi> But in the mean while he endures Labours in this <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> even to a Conſumption both of his <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Money,</hi> untill he hath miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably practiced upon <hi>himſelf</hi> that <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis</hi> which he ſought on the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which thing, when ſome captious <hi>Myſo-Chymicks</hi> obſerve, and have ſeen the ſame Event to happen to moſt, they laugh at the <hi>Art</hi> forthwith, as <hi>fabulous</hi> and deride it. But they who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived themſelves by their own raſhneſs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52222:16"/>do go about to Intice others into the ſame way of Loſs, and by their <hi>Devices</hi> and <hi>feigned Receipts,</hi> do blurr Paper, that they may ſeem at leaſt to have gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome skill by the Loſs of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. With which Sophiſtications, the world is ſo full, that almoſt no ſtudious <hi>Tiro</hi> of the <hi>Art,</hi> but is ſeduced by them. No Deſpiſer of <hi>Science,</hi> who may not take an occaſion of Barking againſt it from hence. So that as well the <hi>Art</hi> it ſelf, as its Ingenious <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> ſuffer unworthily for the baſeneſs of ſome <hi>Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals,</hi> who altho' they are more ſtupid then a <hi>Block</hi> in the <hi>Art.</hi> yet Write ſo as tho' they were truly <hi>Adepts,</hi> and do freely devulge their Impoſtures ſo far, that the firſt Inextricable Labyrinth to a young <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> is to diſtinguiſh between the true and falſe Books, from which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtical Deceivers, do build up no leſs ſpecious an <hi>Edifice,</hi> then the true <hi>Artiſts,</hi> nay for the moſt part they promiſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things. Concerning theſe, <hi>Bernard Treveſan,</hi> (a man not unexperienced in the Cheat of this kind) writes thus, <hi>"<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52222:17"/>(ſaith he) <hi>thou avoid theſe as the Plague, thou milt never taſte any good in this Art.</hi> Therefore I have writ this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> to Inform the blind more fully in this <hi>Science,</hi> leaſt wandring through <hi>Deſart Places,</hi> they miſerably Rove. And firſt I have decreed to Vindicate the <hi>Art</hi> from Calumnies: Nextly, I thought good to ſubjoyn the Qualifications of them who ſtudy this <hi>Art:</hi> and laſtly, I will deſcribe the true manner of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: Which things being premiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a <hi>Preface,</hi> I will preſently betake my ſelf to Dilucidate the <hi>Art</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>For that there are found many decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Sophiſters</hi> Treating of <hi>Althimy,</hi> ſhould it be reproved either of <hi>falſity</hi> or <hi>folly.</hi> For that the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of <hi>things</hi> is to be weighed, by which, if the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Art</hi> can be diſproved, <hi>let</hi> it fall, If not, it is not only fooliſh, but unworthy a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> to ſlander it. For the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men who handle this <hi>Art</hi> raſhly, makes nothing to the deſtroying it, for the Light of <hi>Nature</hi> is clearer, then to be obſcured by thoſe <hi>Dark Fellows.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52222:17"/>I will Inſtruct the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> leſt they ſhould be ſeduced by <hi>Errours,</hi> and it ſhall appear to theſe more evident then the <hi>Sun</hi> that the <hi>Tranſmutation</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> is real, poſſible and true from the ſtate of <hi>Imperfection</hi> to <hi>Perfection,</hi> and that by the Co-operation of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art.</hi> Seing that no material or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Difference is ſeen betwixt <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>Imperfect</hi> Metals, but only an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental one, which conſiſts in the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Maturity. This alone being greater or leſſer, does diverſify <hi>Metals</hi> in their <hi>Species</hi>'s, unleſs that ſome <hi>ſuperadventitious ſuperfluities</hi> do appear diſtinct among <hi>Metals,</hi> which being only dreggs, have no Correſpondence with the <hi>Matter,</hi> but being altogether <hi>Irreptitiouſly ſurro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated,</hi> not purified, becauſe of the <hi>Defect</hi> of <hi>Digeſtion,</hi> have remained mingled with the <hi>Indigeſted pure.</hi> Hence the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of <hi>metallick</hi> Formes. But if at any time theſe <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> ſhall be caſt off, by the compleat perfection of Digeſtion, then the <hi>Metals</hi> is ſeen no longer <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> but rather <hi>perfect;</hi> Hence out of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52222:18"/>Mineral of <hi>Lead,</hi> in a convenient ſpace of time, without much trouble, <hi>Miners</hi> do witneſs that a great deal of <hi>Silver</hi> is found. And in like manner, if this ſame thing could be performed by <hi>Triumphant Art,</hi> without the means of the <hi>Earth,</hi> there is nothing in <hi>Nature</hi> to hinder but the ſame <hi>Effect</hi> ſhould ſollow. But the certainty of this thing is plain from hence, (to wit, that all Metals ariſe from the ſame matter) becauſe <hi>Mercury</hi> which is generated in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Earth.</hi> is the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal material Mother,</hi> of all thoſe things which are Indued with a <hi>Metallick</hi> Species, which will not be hard to be proved from hence, becauſe <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> is accommodated to all thoſe things and may be joined by <hi>Art;</hi> but it were altogether impoſſible to perform that, unleſs all participated of <hi>one matter.</hi> For that <hi>Mercury</hi> is a <hi>Water,</hi> yet ſuch a one, as is mingled with nothing which is not of the <hi>Identity</hi> of its own <hi>Nature.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince it Drinks up all <hi>Metals,</hi> by moiſtening them, that all thoſe do retain a Correſpondency of <hi>matter</hi> with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52222:18"/>this I add, that by <hi>Art,</hi> the Handmaid of <hi>Nature, Mercury</hi> may be ſo Succeſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concocted with all <hi>Metals,</hi> that one and the ſame, under the ſame <hi>Colour,</hi> and form of <hi>Flux,</hi> may ſubalternatly ſhow and Expreſs, the true <hi>Temperature</hi> and the true <hi>Proprieties</hi> of all of them. Which would be impoſſible in <hi>Art,</hi> unleſs <hi>Nature</hi> did ſupply the poſſibility of this, by the Correſpondency of <hi>matter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For thermore, There are not wanting other Arguments to prove the ſame.</p>
                     <p>And firſt of all truly this is not light, The all <hi>Metals</hi> may be reduced into run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Mercury,</hi> as alſo <hi>Minerdls</hi> that do conſiſt of <hi>metallick</hi> principles. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, theſe <hi>metallick Mercuries</hi> may be ſo changed, that a <hi>Saturnine</hi> may become a <hi>Martial</hi> neglecting its own force the mean while) only by the Decoction of a <hi>Martial</hi> Eſſence in the ſame, by ſaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Artifice;</hi> moreover the ſame <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> may become <hi>Venereal,</hi> by the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Venus;</hi> The ſame alſo <hi>Lunar, Jovial,</hi> or <hi>Solar,</hi> by a Ferment of them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52222:19"/>in the mean while no alteration being made either in <hi>Colour</hi> or <hi>Fluxs</hi> excepting that one <hi>Mercury</hi> is more pure &amp; deffica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then the other. An admirable <hi>Mercury</hi> is ſeparated alſo from <hi>Antimony</hi> which will alſo put on the Nature of <hi>metallick Mercuries,</hi> by the ſubtile Adminiſtration of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi> Nor this alone but alſo thoſe above ſaid <hi>Mercuries,</hi> will ſo change the <hi>Common Mercury,</hi> as well of <hi>Metallick</hi> as <hi>Mineral,</hi> ſo that by its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion it being digeſted with them, takes to it ſelf the ſame Natural Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with them, that it makes one and the ſame <hi>Mercury</hi> with them, according to the Species of the Corporal <hi>Mercury,</hi> being joyned with it in a Spiritual Bond, and one and the ſame individual by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Operations, can put on the <hi>Farms</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> and chuſe one new one, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former, until it has run through the Kingdoms of all the <hi>Planets.</hi> And what doth this argue, but that all claim to themſelves one matter, from which all come, and to which all return, and that all things being reduced to this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52222:19"/>
                        <hi>mercurial matter,</hi> according to the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Digeſtion, may go from one into anothers <hi>Species,</hi> and alone ſucceſſfully travel through <hi>all.</hi> Which Argument, as being true in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> ſo alſo it will remain a firm <hi>Foundation</hi> to this <hi>Art,</hi> and <hi>inviolable.</hi> Againſt theſe moſt <hi>evident</hi> thing I know not what can be Objected, unleſs ſome, the dulneſs of whoſe wit does not reach to receive theſe things do Complain that they have often tryed theſe things, and that according to the preſcript of moſt famous <hi>Authors,</hi> yet the Event has no way anſwered their <hi>Hope.</hi> Whom we may Anſwer, that their <hi>Ignorance</hi> makes nothing to Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſo <hi>Noble</hi> an <hi>Art.</hi> Let not this be imputed a fault to the <hi>Art,</hi> if any thing in <hi>Nature</hi> poſſible by <hi>Art,</hi> eſcape their Intellect; for this Objection will be no leſs a mark of affected <hi>Arrogance,</hi> then groſs <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as tho' thoſe things alone were to be performed by the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>Nature,</hi> Art Co-operating, which without an exact Scrutiny, fall under the Capacity of their <hi>Wit.</hi> The
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52222:20"/>reſt being, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> Excluded, as the there were the ſame meaſure of their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect,</hi> and the poſſibility of <hi>Nature.</hi> Moreover, I would meet by an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental affirmative <hi>Knowledge,</hi> their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative <hi>Experience.</hi> I my ſelf that write theſe things can be a faithful Witneſs of <hi>Nature,</hi> that all theſe aforeſaid things are true, without any <hi>Falſity,</hi> and certain without <hi>Pretence,</hi> and I have ſeen all theſe things in and about <hi>Metals,</hi> have tryed them, and by Experience have found them <hi>true.</hi> Therefore they muſt not contend with bare <hi>Negations</hi> (whoſe Baſis is Ignorance) againſt eye <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> of whom I profeſs my <hi>ſelf</hi> one, who alſo, am backt with one mouth, by all the true <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> ſuch are <hi>Albertas, Raimundus, Ripley, Flammel, Moren,</hi> and many others, whoſe names it would be tedious to reckon. I confeſs at leaſt, that it is no light <hi>Work</hi> to perform this which I have ſaid, but on the contrary very much hidden from <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and I might affirm it the moſt hidden thing in <hi>Nature.</hi> Furthermore I make it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52222:20"/>known, that the <hi>Key</hi> of the <hi>Art</hi> is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us by <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> which whee ſoever hath, the <hi>Key</hi> of unlocking all the <hi>doors</hi> is committed to him, ſo that he Learn to handle every thing in its Order and true Method. For it is not all one what <hi>Metal</hi> or <hi>Mineral</hi> is firſt took in hand, or which <hi>way,</hi> or by what <hi>Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> it goes on, but in knowing of theſe an Ingenious Sagacity is required, and beſides the <hi>Theory,</hi> a Practical <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> or elſe he will <hi>err</hi> let him do what he can. I could here reckon up divers <hi>Mutations</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> as for Inſtance, <hi>Mars</hi> into <hi>Venus,</hi> by the <hi>acid Stalagma</hi> of <hi>Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol, Mercury</hi> into <hi>Saturn, Saturn</hi> into <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, Jupiter</hi> into <hi>Luna,</hi> which Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons indeed, many vulgar <hi>Chymiſts</hi> (far enough from the top of <hi>Art</hi>) know to perform. I add that it is known to few, (and thoſe only true <hi>Philoſophers</hi>) that there is a middle ſubſtance, <hi>hidden, noble,</hi> betwixt a <hi>Metal</hi> and a <hi>Mineral,</hi> of which the one end is a <hi>Metal,</hi> and the other a <hi>Mineral,</hi> whoſe Commixt Heavenly <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> make one certain <hi>anonymous Metal,</hi>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52222:21"/>when yet it is not a <hi>Metal,</hi> but a <hi>Chaos,</hi> that is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> becauſe wholly <hi>volatile,</hi> from whence (altho in it ſelf it be wholly <hi>Volatile</hi>) all <hi>Metals</hi> may be drawn, without the <hi>Tranſmuting Elixir,</hi> even <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna,</hi> alſo <hi>Mercury,</hi> whoſe <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> I ſhall not willingly deſcribe, I have <hi>ſeen, done, known,</hi> the <hi>Tranſmutation</hi> of this into all <hi>Metals,</hi> and this the <hi>Adepts</hi> will witneſs with me to be <hi>true.</hi> I will tell thee, (if thou wilt conceive) it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chalibs</hi> by the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New Light,</hi> and it is the true principle of the Work, the true <hi>Key</hi> (as it may be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled) of unlocking the moſt hidden <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> What in the mean while if <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have hidden theſe things, and have Painted out <hi>parabolical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> to the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>Art,</hi> under a mask of Falſhood; ſhall therefore this ſo <hi>Divine</hi> a Science be contemned; farr be it. For it is plain, that in the Nature of an <hi>imperfect</hi> thing there is no Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but it may be changed into a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> ſince of its <hi>own nature</hi> it retains a propenſity of putting on <hi>Perfection,</hi> if ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52222:21"/>be it be tryed by an <hi>Homogeneous Agent,</hi> prevailing with a <hi>Digeſtive</hi> power. Now then we will inquire into its <hi>Virtue,</hi> and firſt indeed, we will determine, that by which this ought to be done. And then we will adjoyn <hi>Philoſophical</hi> reaſons. As for the <hi>firſt,</hi> we do, and will profeſs it to be nothing elſe but <hi>Gold</hi> digeſted to the ſupream Degree to which it can be brought by <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>Art;</hi> which then will be ſeen not ſimply <hi>Gold,</hi> but a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more perfect then <hi>Common Gold.</hi> Which being ſo exalted it <hi>radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> penetrates <hi>Metals,</hi> tinging and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. Neither let this ſeem won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful to any one, ſince whilſt it remains in its <hi>Corporeal Exiſtence,</hi> it can diffuſe its <hi>Tincture</hi> far and near, above what is credible to any one who doth not ſee it: Inſomuch that it ſeems to colour into its <hi>Tincture,</hi> as tho by littles, almoſt ſix Pound of <hi>Silver</hi> with one ſingle Ounce of <hi>Gold.</hi> For Example, let a maſs of <hi>Silver</hi> be guilded (tho it be very great) let it afterward be drawn into a Thread (as ſmall as a Hair) that whole Thread
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52222:22"/>will appear as tho' of the pureſt <hi>Gold,</hi> and the <hi>Artiſt</hi> will ſooner be wanting to attenuate the Thread, then the <hi>Gold</hi> to the Power of <hi>Colouring.</hi> Moreover, if this Corporeal <hi>Metal,</hi> Earthly and dead is able to perform this ſo unſpeakable a thing, from whence I pray, is this Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>Tincture,</hi> except becauſe a Body cannot alteratively enter into a <hi>Body,</hi> for there is not wanting a Tincture to Change it, but the <hi>Corporality</hi> of the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Matter hinders the <hi>Tranſmutation.</hi> But if this <hi>Corporeal Earthly,</hi> would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>ſpiritual Fiery,</hi> its kind being altered, then truly it would ſundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally enter, and what it did outwardly to the <hi>ſight,</hi> it would perform the ſame <hi>alteratively Internally,</hi> yea, and much more; by how much <hi>fire</hi> is of a more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile property and Eſſence then <hi>Earth.</hi> Therefore this being ſuppoſed, to wit, that terrene vulgar <hi>Gold,</hi> may be ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated, untill it be placed in the Seat of a <hi>Fiery Eſſence,</hi> it will eaſily be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that this <hi>fifth Eſſence,</hi> is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more <hi>perfect</hi> then its former
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52222:22"/>ſubſtance, and that from the <hi>Law</hi> of the diſproportion of <hi>ſubtilty</hi> amongſt the four <hi>Elements,</hi> and therefore it is of <hi>power</hi> to defuſe its <hi>Tincture</hi> further; it hath this moreover, that whilſt it is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> it may <hi>Intrinſically</hi> be mingled with the leaſt things, which a <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſhould be extended far, cannot attain to, becauſe of its <hi>Corporality,</hi> and if it ſhall ſo enter, without doubt it would <hi>Tranſmute</hi> it, ſince every <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Ingreſſion by Littles, is the <hi>Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of the paſſive <hi>Nature,</hi> unleſs the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentity</hi> of Nature be between the thing entring and entred, as <hi>Water</hi> mixed with <hi>Water.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Suppoſition inſtead of a <hi>Preface,</hi> we do aſſert to be true, and in its Place will deſcribe the manner of it.</p>
                     <p>Here at leaſt we will bring ſome <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Confirming the poſſibility. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, this is of no light moment that <hi>Seed</hi> is the <hi>Perfection</hi> of every thing having <hi>Seed,</hi> and that which has not <hi>Seed</hi> is wholly Imperfect, as Sung the Poet.</p>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52222:23"/>
                        <l>In auro—</l>
                        <l>Semina ſunt auri licet haec abſtruſa re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt,</l>
                        <l>Longius —</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>This is not only <hi>perfect,</hi> but the moſt <hi>perfect,</hi> in its <hi>Metallick Species.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there be the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> it will follow, that this does reſide in <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> which is the Habitation of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> for <hi>Seed</hi> is a certain ſpiritual Means of Conſerving the <hi>Species,</hi> hence the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Diſſolution of <hi>Gold.</hi> Altho it is the Work of a very <hi>quick ſighted Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> Bleſſed by <hi>God</hi> with no mean <hi>Talent,</hi> to find out a powerful <hi>Agent</hi> to perform this. Moreover, if <hi>Gold</hi> could be diſſolved to bring out its <hi>Seed,</hi> reaſon perſwades, that this is to be done no other <hi>Way</hi> then into <hi>Water Homogeneous</hi> of its own Kind. Which Diſſolution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once made, the <hi>Body</hi> hath put off its <hi>form,</hi> to wit, a terrine form of <hi>Gold,</hi> and hath put on another <hi>Watry-Golden</hi> form. Moreover all <hi>Motion</hi> is from <hi>ſomething,</hi> to <hi>ſomething,</hi> and every perfect <hi>Motion,</hi> is the bound of a <hi>generative</hi> in the ſame
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52222:23"/>kind, whence motion is a Progreſſion, which will be done by Various Homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous <hi>Mutations</hi> to the thing moved, wherefore when <hi>Aureity</hi> is the <hi>terminus a quo,</hi> the ſame will be <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> and there will be Intermedial Progreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a <hi>Metallick Homogeneity,</hi> by the Neceſſity of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which being obſerved, the Effect is forced to its <hi>End,</hi> through the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of an <hi>End,</hi> if ſo be the <hi>Operations</hi> ſhall not be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Contrary. Wherefore from <hi>diſſolved Gold</hi> we put a <hi>regreſs</hi> of the ſame <hi>diſſolved,</hi> to <hi>aureity;</hi> and we conclude it to be <hi>proved.</hi> But this <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> form which it ſhall re-aſſume, in no wiſe ſhall be the ſame which it hath put off, ſince a <hi>regreſs</hi> from a <hi>privation,</hi> to a <hi>habit</hi> is impoſſible. Therefore there is neceſſarily another <hi>Golden</hi> form to this, which will be ſo much more <hi>Noble,</hi> then the former, by how much more <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> as far as <hi>Fire</hi> is more ſubtile and pure then <hi>Earth.</hi> I have Writ enough, and too much, to Direct the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> now let the Chief <hi>Myſo-Chymicks</hi>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52222:24"/>bark at ſafely thoſe things which they are Ignorant of, they can in no wiſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate</hi> the force of thoſe things which I have ſaid, or <hi>diſprove</hi> the truth, and they ſhall certainly bear away this <hi>Reward</hi> of their ſlanders, <hi>deep Ignorance.</hi> For I write nothing to the <hi>Haters</hi> of <hi>Art,</hi> to the reſt what I have ſaid is abundantly ſufficient.</p>
                     <p>Now this <hi>Science</hi> being Eſtabliſhed, and Vindicated, ſomething is to be ſaid of its <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> for that (as is above ſaid) it comes to paſs from the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome ſorry <hi>Fellows,</hi> that this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Art</hi> as well as its Friends, hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much by Calumniators. For when ſome ſtupid <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> ſeduced by blind Preſumption go about the handling of theſe things, being vexed they preſently curſe <hi>Chymical Philoſophy,</hi> ſpeak evil of its <hi>Practitioners,</hi> and tear with railing the <hi>Authors</hi> that write thereof. Others, altho little Learned prepoſterous <hi>Men,</hi> blinded with the thirſt after <hi>Gold,</hi> do gape after the <hi>Art,</hi> and ſet upon the thing without Mature Deliberation, and err, yet nevertheleſs they conceive a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52222:24"/>of the <hi>Art,</hi> and ſpeak well of it, and being aſhamed to conſeſs their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance therein, pretend a <hi>ſkilfulneſs,</hi> to the Ignorant, and perhaps go on to Write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Art,</hi> and being allured with a ſilent <hi>hope</hi> of recovering at laſt what they have loſt, will yet try again, untill they do multiply their <hi>Loſſes;</hi> they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort their <hi>Friends</hi> with the hope of future Good, but in the mean while they are <hi>poor,</hi> and every day made <hi>poorer,</hi> ſo giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an occaſion to the fooliſh Mockers of <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> to deride them. Indeed ſo great is their <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> ſince they are ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced themſelves they go about to intice others with their falſe Receits, Lyes and Sophiſtical Writings, into the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament of <hi>Error;</hi> at length ſome, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever skil'd in the <hi>Art,</hi> yet being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up thereto by <hi>envy,</hi> do handle the thing very <hi>Scabiouſly</hi> and <hi>deceitfully,</hi> and under the promiſes of true <hi>Doctrine,</hi> do ſeduce <hi>Tiro's</hi> with moſt miſerable <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures,</hi> ſo <hi>Geber, Arnold, Lully</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all others, amongſt whom there is not found one Candid Writer, and if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52222:25"/>any, yet he will be found to handle the Matter very obſcurely. Hence an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable <hi>Labyrinth</hi> to one that is to begin <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> that there ſeems to be need, even of the Immediate finger of <hi>God,</hi> if any one ſhall deſire to go the right <hi>Path.</hi> Hence alſo the Name of the <hi>Art</hi> is ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious that a body cannot ſet to it eaſily without the greateſt <hi>deriſion.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is very neceſſary to be known what is to be done in the firſt place by one that will be a <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Science,</hi> to obtain this <hi>Golden Art,</hi> to obtain this <hi>Fleece,</hi> ſince there will be many hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to drive him back, unleſs he has a firm Reſolution of <hi>mind,</hi> many things to delude his <hi>hope</hi> and expectation, unleſs he hath a quick ſighted <hi>Wit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt</hi> Indeed, that he may be made ſafe from them who <hi>Deride</hi> his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, his <hi>Courſe</hi> ought to be <hi>Secret</hi> that his <hi>Labour</hi> may be known to none, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ancient wiſe <hi>Philoſophers</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to hide this <hi>Science,</hi> like a word in the Mouth. Neither truly may it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52222:25"/>ſeem unprofitable ſo to Exhort, ſince that the diſgraces and Calumnies of <hi>Men,</hi> make not little towards the Caſting of a diſpondency in the <hi>mind</hi> of a <hi>Tiro,</hi> who abhorring the <hi>Art</hi> themſelves have its Practitioners in the higheſt Contempt. Moreover if any one conſider the Event, there will appear to be need of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Concealing of the <hi>Art.</hi> For if any one ſhall be fruſtrated of his <hi>hope,</hi> can <hi>Silence</hi> hurt him any thing, when other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, he ſhall be propounded, who is ſo diſappointed, for an <hi>Example</hi> of a <hi>fooliſh</hi> throwing away of Money and time (as it is commonly reputed.) But if on the other hand he ſhall obtain this <hi>Treaſure,</hi> it ſhall not only be found profitable, but alſo extreamly neceſſary to have conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. For he is propounded a Prey to <hi>Tyrants</hi> and wicked perſons if any one ſhall enjoy and uſe openly ſo great a <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> and ſome alſo being too <hi>improvident</hi> in this thing having endangered the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Life,</hi> have repented too late. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he ought to be of a Conſtant <hi>mind,</hi> which would Deſcend into this <hi>Paleſtra,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52222:26"/>Diligent, Induſtrious, I earned,</hi> a devourer of Books, <hi>Private, Solitary,</hi> unleſs that he hath one faithful <hi>Companion,</hi> not more, not <hi>Poor;</hi> for altho a little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity may ſuffice when the Art is once try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet it will happen that he will <hi>err</hi> ſometimes, to repair which errors, he has need of money; moreover to ſupply Charges neceſſary for <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Raiment,</hi> whilſt he is incumbent in this <hi>Art,</hi> leaſt by chance he ſhould be obliged to do ſomething elſe, when he rather ought to be of an undiſturbed <hi>Mind.</hi> And that which is the greateſt thing, let him be <hi>honeſt</hi> and fearing <hi>God,</hi> abhorring <hi>Sin</hi> and ſoliciting <hi>Heaven</hi> with his <hi>Prayers</hi> to proſper his Undertakings, thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified let him go on, but without the clear <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> he will err. Moreover, let him get the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Learned Men,</hi> and not <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> let him diligently mind thoſe let him <hi>read</hi> and read and <hi>read</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and Conſider things deeply with <hi>himſelf,</hi> and have a care leaſt when he hath once Concluded the thing, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently try it <hi>Practically,</hi> but let him often
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52222:26"/>
                        <hi>ponder, examine</hi> and <hi>weigh</hi> his Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Compare</hi> it with the Opinion of the moſt Learned <hi>Authors,</hi> and <hi>alter</hi> in ſo long, untill he ſhall have <hi>choſe</hi> ſome one, which ſhall endure all <hi>probations,</hi> then at length let him begin a <hi>Praxis,</hi> Praying for Gods Aſſiſtance, let him conſider his Experiments, which as <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſhall perſwade, let him <hi>alter</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new,</hi> until he ſhall ſee the <hi>Signs</hi> Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> And omitting <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Operations,</hi> let him inſiſt only upon one <hi>true Complement,</hi> neither let him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, altho he err often, and yet let him have a Care of <hi>great Charges,</hi> ſo by the bleſſing of God, he ſhall at length obtain his <hi>deſire.</hi> I moreover to inſtruct ſuch a one have writ the following <hi>Treatiſe true, plain, perfect,</hi> without <hi>Deceit.</hi> And yet I would admoniſh all <hi>Covetous, Fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> Perſons and the reſt of that <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> that they let alone the <hi>Art,</hi> and this <hi>Treatiſe.</hi> For</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Certum eſt procul hinc arcere profanum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52222:27"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the beginning of the <hi>Art,</hi> its <hi>Writers,</hi> and its <hi>Foundation,</hi> in which it is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the <hi>Metallick</hi> Principles and the gradual Production of <hi>Metalls</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HErmes</hi> by Sirname <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> the Father of this <hi>Art,</hi> is introduced into the Scene of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> of whom various Opinions of <hi>Authors</hi> are report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who he ſhould be; there are not wanting who affirm him to have been <hi>Moſes,</hi> at leaſt they agree in this, that he was an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> alſo a moſt quick ſighted <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> He is called the Father of this <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> to wit, who firſt of all (whoſe Books are extant) handled this <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> Yet ſome will have this <hi>Science</hi> derived from <hi>Enoch,</hi> who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the <hi>Flood,</hi> Writ the ſeven <hi>Liberal Sciences,</hi> (amongſt which is <hi>Chymiſtry</hi>) upon Tables, and left them to <hi>Poſterity.</hi>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52222:27"/>But <hi>Hermes</hi> entring into the Valley of <hi>Hebron</hi> found them, which are yet called the <hi>Emrald Pillars</hi> and thence Learned his <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> Others ſharply contend that <hi>Noah</hi> knew this <hi>Art,</hi> and carryed it into his <hi>Ark.</hi> Not a few do indeavour to eſtabliſh this <hi>Art</hi> from ſome places of <hi>Scripture</hi> and write that <hi>Solomon</hi> had it. Some bring it down from <hi>Adam</hi> himſelf, to <hi>Abel</hi> and ſo to <hi>Seth;</hi> but ſuch like ſubtilties do not pleaſe me, being about to write the Simplicity of <hi>Nature,</hi> they do not Illuſtrate, nay rather obſcure <hi>Art,</hi> that it ſeems <hi>Enthyſiaſtical,</hi> and they that ſo <hi>Write,</hi> do nothing elſe but yield an Occaſion of deriding to <hi>Myſo Chymicks.</hi> For that if the <hi>Art</hi> has a real Foundation in <hi>Nature,</hi> why ſhould I be Solicitous whether this or that man underſtood it or no, ſince we know that its Lovers and the <hi>Adepts</hi> have always concealed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all their endeavour, even as alſo it is declared to others in their <hi>Books.</hi> Neither have all, or at leaſt very many been known but after their <hi>Death,</hi> but whilſt they were <hi>alive</hi> they lay concealed with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52222:28"/>the greateſt Diligence. This at leaſt is clear, that it is ſo farr from being a new <hi>Device,</hi> that there have been <hi>men</hi> skilful of it through many <hi>Series</hi>'s of <hi>Ages,</hi> who being Different both in <hi>Tongue</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and very many of them <hi>Contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> have writ ſo agreeingly of the <hi>Art,</hi> that they cannot be proved, by ſuch as rightly underſtand them, either to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt,</hi> or <hi>diverſly</hi> to handle ſo much as one <hi>Operation.</hi> I confeſs at leaſt, there may appear a great difficulty in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Books,</hi> to a man unskilful of the thing, they write ſo <hi>obſcurely, tropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, allegorically</hi> and <hi>figuratively;</hi> ſome alſo do intermingle many <hi>falſe</hi> things to enſnare the <hi>unworthy</hi> and <hi>unwary,</hi> that by this means they may diſtinguiſh <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> from <hi>Fools;</hi> but in ſum, all of them do ſtrike at one mark and lead to the lame Inn. But thoſe things which they deliver more <hi>Obſcurely,</hi> they do this to no other end, but that they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>unworthy,</hi> as they often wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their <hi>Books. Bernard Treviſan</hi> (much adored by me) is found moſt <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did;</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52222:28"/>alſo <hi>Ripley</hi> an Engliſh-man, <hi>Fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>el</hi> a French-man, <hi>Sendivogius</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>The new Light,</hi> alſo the <hi>anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Author</hi> of the <hi>Hermetick Secrets,</hi> yet whoſe name hath delivered a double <hi>Anagram,</hi> as to wit <hi>(ſpes nea eſt in agno)</hi> in a Book whoſe Title is <hi>Enchiridion hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicae Reſtitutae,</hi> and <hi>(penes nos unda tagi)</hi> in his <hi>Hermetick arcanum.</hi> I would not paſs by here the <hi>Ladder</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> the <hi>great Roſary,</hi> the Works of <hi>Arnoldus,</hi> the <hi>Boys play,</hi> the Works of <hi>Dionyſius Zacharius, Aejidius de vadis,</hi> the Works of <hi>Moren, Augurellus his Poems of making Gold,</hi> alſo <hi>Five Treatiſes</hi> of the <hi>Roſary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviated,</hi> the Works of <hi>Peter Bonus of Ferrara,</hi> In a word I would have all the <hi>Books</hi> included which are agreeable to theſe aſoreſaid, and thoſe which are otherwayes excluded. Which being compared, as is fit, before the Work be begun, in the firſt place the ſtudious <hi>Schollar</hi> of Art may learn the <hi>Lives, Kingdoms, Manners</hi> and <hi>Habits</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Minerals,</hi> nor delight himſelf in the bare <hi>Notion,</hi> but know them <hi>Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entifically,</hi>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52222:29"/>that is <hi>Practically.</hi> But to this end, there is need of a Profound medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Contemplation,</hi> that he may Learn and Underſtand the Original of <hi>Natural</hi> things in the <hi>genus</hi> and of <hi>Mineral Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> in the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> As for me, being only intentive to the Doctrine of <hi>Metals,</hi> to wit, as far forth as it ſeems to Explain the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Tranſmutation,</hi> I willingly paſs by the Original of Natural things in the <hi>genus;</hi> Content to have ſpoken thoſe things which may ſatisfie the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid purpoſe, <hi>yet</hi> I will briefly touch the reſt in <hi>Order.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All the <hi>Common Philoſophers</hi> have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered that there are <hi>four Elements</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding all things <hi>Originally,</hi> from whence are all things, to which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, from whoſe divers <hi>Coalition,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things <hi>proceed.</hi> Almoſt all <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Philoſophers</hi> have ſubſcribed to this unhappy Opinion. No other Cauſe of which I am able to conjecture then that without <hi>mature Deliberation</hi> (they being prepared to their own Intereſt) they have haſtily deſcribed theſe firſt <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52222:29"/>of things. Which <hi>Opinion</hi> of theirs, I not daring to <hi>diſallow,</hi> upon the account of the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> I have for them, will handle it <hi>Philoſophically</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways according to the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> For I only acknowledge <hi>three Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which they Contend to be <hi>four,</hi> all which Experience teacheth to be <hi>cold</hi> of their <hi>own nature,</hi> to wit, <hi>Air, Water</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> for that the only defect being cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the remote diſtance of the <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factive Sun,</hi> which doth bring a <hi>coldneſs</hi> upon all theſe things and that is more <hi>remiſs,</hi> or <hi>Intenſe,</hi> by how much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer diſtance it is removed. For I altogether reject an <hi>Elementary Fire,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I deny that there is any beſides our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fire</hi> which burns in the Kitchins, whoſe heat is always <hi>diſtructive</hi> in it ſelf. Neither do I deny, notwithſtanding, that there is <hi>heat</hi> in things, flowing, either from <hi>Light</hi> or <hi>motion,</hi> or <hi>Life,</hi> or alterative <hi>Blas,</hi> no other. The Pyrate <hi>Vulcan</hi> doth <hi>burn</hi> and <hi>waſte</hi> Concrete things, by <hi>feeding</hi> upon them &amp; it is the moſt Corrupt Violent <hi>motion,</hi> cauſed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52222:30"/>from the <hi>Repugnancy</hi> which ariſes from two contrary active things, but yet it is not an <hi>Element,</hi> as being neither <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> nor <hi>Accident</hi> as farr as appeartains to the <hi>actual</hi> burning, but the expreſſion of the Activity of two <hi>Agents,</hi> mutually in themſelves, in a Capacious <hi>Subject.</hi> I would not ſhow now what things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in order to Fire <hi>actually burning,</hi> beſides the accident of <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> in which this <hi>Action</hi> is made, at leaſt we aſſert this hear, altho its <hi>heat</hi> be an <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> yet that it its ſelf is neither an <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> nor a <hi>ſubstance,</hi> but the expreſs Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>activity</hi> of two <hi>active</hi> things and acting mutually upon one another, which <hi>activity</hi> I could eaſily demonſtrate in every Combuſtable thing <hi>burning,</hi> but that it would be <hi>foreign</hi> to this place. And as I do altogether reject <hi>Elemental Fire,</hi> in the mean while being content with a <hi>Ternary</hi> number of the <hi>Elements</hi> and do aſſert, the firſt native quality <hi>cold,</hi> neither do I attribute to them <hi>heat,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept accidental as is ſaid; ſo neither do I admit theſe <hi>three</hi> by their <hi>Commixtion</hi>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52222:30"/>to go into the Compoſition of Natural things. For that the <hi>Diſproportion</hi> of things to be mingled, takes away the mixture fit for <hi>Generation,</hi> and the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility thereof. For a <hi>Natural</hi> Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made by the Union of Generative Ingredients. Moreover <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of things to be <hi>united per minima,</hi> but if the <hi>leaſt</hi> of one thing be <hi>tenfold</hi> or a <hi>Hundreafold</hi> more ſubtile then the <hi>little</hi> of another, the adequate <hi>littles</hi> cannot come together, for that it behoves very little things to come together, which we ſeek to unite <hi>per minima.</hi> From hence <hi>water</hi> mixed with <hi>Earth</hi> is not united with it, even as neither <hi>Water</hi> with <hi>Wine,</hi> or <hi>Flegme</hi> with <hi>Spirit,</hi> yea they may be ſeparated, becauſe of this diſproportion amongſt the <hi>littles.</hi> If any one ſhall ſay in order to make this <hi>mixture,</hi> one thing undergoes the <hi>ſubtilty</hi> of another, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence are <hi>united,</hi> I urge that if it be equally <hi>ſubtile</hi> (<hi>which</hi> was firſt thick) that it may enter <hi>liquid</hi> by uniting it ſelf, it behoves that it be altogether brought to the ſame <hi>Nature,</hi> and what then I pray is <hi>Earth</hi> but <hi>Water,</hi> (for that, <hi>Water</hi>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52222:31"/>will not go into <hi>Earth</hi> that it may have an umon with <hi>Earth,</hi> that is to ſay a <hi>Body</hi> will not enter a <hi>Body</hi> ſo unitively and if it be ſo, how fooliſh is it to imagine this, that <hi>Earth</hi> is convertible to Water, that it ſhould promote the <hi>Generation</hi> of a <hi>Conerete</hi> with <hi>Water,</hi> and if this ſhould be granted, the thing would be ſaid to be produeed of <hi>Water;</hi> if ſo be <hi>before</hi> it was poſsible to be produced, the <hi>Earth</hi> had gone into real <hi>Water,</hi> but this is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or otherwiſe the <hi>little</hi> of this will not be able to agree with the <hi>little</hi> of the other. And as yet <hi>Air</hi> is wanting, whoſe <hi>little</hi> is much more <hi>ſubtile</hi> then the <hi>little</hi> of <hi>water,</hi> unleſs all things be held to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh into <hi>Air,</hi> that alſo the aforeſaid <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> may have it a Companion to it ſelf in generating, which if it ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it would follow that all things did conſiſt of <hi>Air</hi> alone, which <hi>Air,</hi> altho it be <hi>Originally</hi> in its own Nature from it <hi>ſelf,</hi> or gathered together of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> Changed between themſelves, yet it will be the ſame thing, nor diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified becauſe of the difference of its <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal;</hi>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52222:31"/>for unleſs it be the ſame it cannot be united, to wit, that <hi>Water</hi> may have the ſame ſubtilty with <hi>Air,</hi> it is obliged to have the ſame firſt <hi>Qualities</hi> with it, the ſame alſo is to be Judged of the <hi>Earth,</hi> that it may be adequated to the rarity of the <hi>Water,</hi> and if it be ſo <hi>Water</hi> ſo ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized will be real <hi>Air,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilized will be real <hi>Water,</hi> and now where is the compoſition of things gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by <hi>Elements,</hi> when according to this Doctrine all things are neceſſary to proceed from <hi>Air,</hi> and of <hi>Fire</hi> how much more ſubtilly, a quaternity of <hi>Elements</hi> being admitted, with this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Mixture. But if any one ſhould ſay, that it is true that the <hi>Elements</hi> are ſo Converted, I would ask him by what <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> they were changed: Moreover if <hi>Earth</hi> goes into <hi>Water,</hi> water into <hi>Air,</hi> that ſo there may be an union of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding <hi>Elements,</hi> to make an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary thing, I would ask again what need there is to unite another <hi>new</hi> to <hi>Earth</hi> reduced into real <hi>Water,</hi> ſo alſo to mingle new <hi>Air</hi> to <hi>Water</hi> ſubtilized to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52222:32"/>the rarity of <hi>Air,</hi> as tho one and the ſame <hi>Flement,</hi> ſo convertable into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being converted could not procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate an effect of its ſelf, without the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the other. If it be ſaid that <hi>Earth</hi> as aforeſaid, being Subtilized, is equal to <hi>Water</hi> in Rarity, and yet is not <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> even as neither is <hi>Water</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> would ask then whether or no the on can put on the firſt Qualities of the <hi>other</hi> if not, neither will they have Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in their <hi>littles,</hi> for this is impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; if ſo, I deſire to know whether if one <hi>firſt</hi> ſhould put on the <hi>firſts</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>firſt,</hi> that would not be really the <hi>firſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>firſts</hi> it <hi>firſt</hi> puts on. To aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the Contrary is not <hi>Philoſophical,</hi> therefore it is concluded that all things Materially take their Original from one <hi>Element,</hi> which cannot be neither <hi>Earth</hi> nor <hi>Air,</hi> which unleſs I ſtudied Brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I could eaſily <hi>Demonſtrate.</hi> The <hi>Earth</hi> is a Soil or Bed in which all Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Increaſe and are preſerved, the <hi>Air,</hi> into which they grow, it is the means and bringer of <hi>heavenly</hi> Virtues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52222:32"/>it is filled, and by which they are Communicated to all theſe <hi>Inferior</hi> things, the <hi>Seed</hi> of all things is put into the <hi>Water</hi> by the <hi>Creator</hi> in the firſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, which ſome do produce into the <hi>Air,</hi> as <hi>Vegitables,</hi> ſome keep within their own Reins, as <hi>Animals,</hi> in ſome it is hid very <hi>abſtruſe</hi> as in <hi>Metals,</hi> and there is, even to the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> ſeed ſufficient to produce all things of <hi>Seed,</hi> whoſe Habitation (as is ſaid) the <hi>Water</hi> is found to be. This <hi>Seed</hi> (other ways Idle) being ſtirred up by its <hi>form</hi> (which form is a certain particle of <hi>Ineffable Light, Heavenly Virtue,</hi> which is preſent to Endue (in reference to <hi>place</hi> and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>Agent</hi>) with its <hi>force,</hi> Inferior things aptly diſpoſed, and to ſtirr them up to <hi>Motion</hi>) ſo I ſay the <hi>Seed</hi> being ſtirred up with an <hi>active</hi> Virtue, does Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulate the Material <hi>Water</hi> with its <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatious Odour,</hi> which it ſo Changes by <hi>various</hi> Fermentations, the <hi>Author</hi> of all Changes, until it has produced that, to produce which the <hi>Seed</hi> was propenſe. If therefore there be a <hi>Metallick Seed,</hi> there
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52222:33"/>grows from thence <hi>firſt</hi> a dry humour ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery not wetting the hands, to wit <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> the Mother of all <hi>Metals.</hi> I could here teach the Procreation of <hi>ſtones</hi> of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fort, alſo note very many things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of obſervation, about the <hi>Firſt Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi> of <hi>Mercury:</hi> But I purpoſely paſs by thoſe things making little to the purpoſe. For <hi>Mercury</hi> has deſerved to be called the <hi>true Matter</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> becauſe before it was <hi>Mercury</hi> that it might be deſtined to <hi>Metal,</hi> yet it might happen by ſome <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> that ſome thing different from <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> did reſult from thence, but when once it is <hi>Mercury</hi> then indeed no longer can any thing be born from thence but <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> or <hi>Metaline,</hi> from this the different kind of <hi>Metals</hi> which are ſeen, as for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Jupiter, Saturn, Luna, Venus, Mars, Sol,</hi> which all have one and the ſame Mother, <hi>Mercury;</hi> alſo ſome <hi>middle Minerals</hi> ariſe from hence, ſome alſo are made of the <hi>Metals</hi> themſelves eroded with <hi>acid Mineral Salts,</hi> ſo <hi>Vitriol</hi> from a Vein of <hi>Copper,</hi> eroded by ſuch an <hi>acid, Stalagma,</hi> whoſe Generation to teach
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52222:33"/>would be from the <hi>Matter,</hi> therefore I purpoſely <hi>omit</hi> it. But not any <hi>Interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sulphureous Fatneſs,</hi> (as ſome think fakly) is joyned to the <hi>Mercury</hi> which it Coagulates, boyling it with its heat, whoſe Expurgation afterwards is the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Metal.</hi> For we know that <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,</hi> as it is called, in <hi>Jupiter,</hi> is much more impure then <hi>Sulphur</hi> in <hi>Saturn,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Saturn</hi> be more Crude and unclean then <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and yet even <hi>Common People</hi> will witneſs that <hi>Jupiter</hi> is a more pure <hi>Metal</hi> than <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> therefore we muſt not think with them of a Metallick Digeſtion by ſuch a fatt <hi>Coloſtrum,</hi> when in <hi>Mercury</hi> there is a proper Internal digeſting <hi>Agent,</hi> to wit, <hi>Heat,</hi> which being cauſed by a <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestial influence,</hi> infuſeth Life and Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this our Matter, which <hi>life</hi> and <hi>motion</hi> depend from an Adaptation of a Convenient <hi>Matrix,</hi> or Place fit for <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> For altho all of theſe aboveſaid things are full of this moſt plentiful <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> and this is preſent to all, to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of them; yet it does not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52222:34"/>act by <hi>Informing,</hi> that is by exciting to <hi>Motion,</hi> except as far forth as it is hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by <hi>Extrinſicks</hi> rightly accommod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſo then this <hi>Heavenly Virtue</hi> acts inceſſantly, which altho it be <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> in the whole <hi>World,</hi> yet it is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by reaſon of the <hi>Seed,</hi> according to which, the <hi>Ferments</hi> of things are diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified to produce diverſe <hi>Tranſmutations,</hi> wherefore if <hi>Mercury</hi> born here all find a place in its ſelf fit for <hi>Generation,</hi> altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its ſelf without ſuch a Place it appear <hi>Cold,</hi> for that it is <hi>dead,</hi> yet within the <hi>Center</hi> of its own <hi>Nativity,</hi> (the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive action not being yet Intermitted) this <hi>force</hi> or <hi>Heavenly virtue,</hi> being Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as well from the <hi>Light,</hi> as a Rotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Superior things,</hi> and by means of the <hi>Air</hi> moſt plentifully diffuſed <hi>to</hi> all things, and <hi>through</hi> all things, I ſay this <hi>Virtue</hi> (as it has reference to Light) will cauſe ſome <hi>Heat,</hi> (and as it has refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Rotation of the <hi>Superiors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> will cauſe <hi>Motion</hi> in this Inferior Subject, this <hi>Heat,</hi> and <hi>Celeſtial Motion,</hi> cannot be without its <hi>Life,</hi> in which they are, (I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52222:34"/>mean not an <hi>Animal Life,</hi> nor yet <hi>Vegin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table;</hi> but a <hi>formal</hi>) from theſe, ferments are produced by an <hi>altering Blaſs;</hi> which dayly doth change the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute</hi> it, until the Heavenly Predominate Inducing a <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>leſſer</hi> fixation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Accommodation of the <hi>Place,</hi> helping or retarding <hi>Digeſtion,</hi> from one and the ſame <hi>Mother,</hi> the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid different <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> do proceed, only <hi>diverſified</hi> by the inequality of the <hi>Matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> By reaſon of which <hi>Inequality,</hi> ſome <hi>Crude Super fluities</hi> which are not of <hi>Metallick Impoſition,</hi> but being in the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> are <hi>ſeparable</hi> from it, theſe I ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not <hi>purged</hi> receiving a Coagulation with the <hi>pure,</hi> does ſeem to <hi>ſpecificate</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Metals,</hi> and thoſe <hi>feculent Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities,</hi> being <hi>different</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation</hi> of the <hi>Generative Matrix Mercury,</hi> and it is Coagulated <hi>Different,</hi> and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes this <hi>difference,</hi> according to the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio</hi> of the Place. Moreover the <hi>Matter</hi> of all Metals is <hi>one,</hi> to wit, <hi>Mercury</hi> which properly tends to procreate <hi>Sol</hi> or <hi>Luna,</hi> for the different reſpect in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52222:35"/>of perfectien, if any <hi>Feces</hi> of Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be Commixed in its Generation, theſe are <hi>Accidents,</hi> neither do enter into a <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial</hi> ubſtance of which <hi>partly</hi> the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and partly the Difference of the <hi>place</hi> in which the <hi>Digeſtion</hi> is made, from a different <hi>Coagulation</hi> with this one <hi>pure,</hi> the ſame <hi>one</hi> thing puts on different <hi>Meeks,</hi> and ſo produceth <hi>Imperfect Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> in their Species. I avoid a particular Deſcription of the <hi>Genealogy</hi> of all <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> becauſe I make <hi>haſte</hi> to the <hi>Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Multiplitation</hi> only of <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna.</hi> Therefore I betake my ſelf to the <hi>Tack.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:52222:35"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> how they come of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial-Matter,</hi> and of the poſſibility of Changing <hi>Imperfect Metals,</hi> to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of theſe.</head>
                     <p>OUt of the forſaid <hi>Fountain.</hi> as is ſaid, ſprings <hi>Sol</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> to wit, this Matter is brought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by <hi>Digeſtion.</hi> Now Perfection is <hi>twofold,</hi> either <hi>begun</hi> or <hi>Compleat,</hi> that is, <hi>partly</hi> or <hi>wholly. Compleat</hi> Perfection is the outmoſt bound to which <hi>Nature</hi> aims of her <hi>own</hi> accord, to wit, that all <hi>Crudity</hi> being decocted, and all <hi>Dregs</hi> Cleanſed out, the Metallick Nature may <hi>Triumph</hi> without any Coagulated <hi>Droſs.</hi> This <hi>Sun</hi> of ours has its <hi>Riſing,</hi> and does <hi>Illuminate</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> with its Beams and Splendor. But <hi>begun</hi> perfection, (as I may ſo ſay) is not called Perfection <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly,</hi> and yet in reſpect of that which is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52222:36"/>
                        <hi>formally Imperfect</hi> it deſerves not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly, to be called <hi>Perfection.</hi> For it is to be judged <hi>formal</hi> in perfection, when the <hi>Crudity</hi> is not ſo decocted, which did ſtick to the <hi>pure</hi> in Generation (by accident) nor yet the <hi>Heterogeneous ſuperfluity</hi> is ſo purged out, but it is left mingled with the <hi>pure</hi> in Coagulation; in ſo great quantity that it predominates over it, and at laſt overcomes it; ſo it happens to all <hi>Metals,</hi> (<hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) which are Corrupted eaſily by all Corrupting <hi>Elements,</hi> alſo are Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Fire.</hi> But when the <hi>Crudity</hi> is ſo bound, and the <hi>feculent ſuper fluity</hi> ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out before Coagulation, that the <hi>pare</hi> has ſuch Do ninion over the <hi>Impure,</hi> to be delivered from the <hi>Corruptive</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny thereof, this is to be accounted the <hi>firſt Degree</hi> of Perfection. But a <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Expurgation of the <hi>Feces,</hi> and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the <hi>Impure</hi> is the <hi>top</hi> or <hi>higheſt</hi> perfection of <hi>Metallick</hi> Operations. And yet theſe <hi>Crudities</hi> and <hi>Feces</hi> were not O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally of the ſame Impoſition of <hi>nature</hi> with <hi>Metallick Mercury,</hi> nay they were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52222:36"/>
                        <hi>ſeparable,</hi> whoſe Separation before Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation is the <hi>Perfection</hi> of <hi>Metals.</hi> But if they be not purged out before <hi>Coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet this has in no wiſe united them to the <hi>pure,</hi> nay they are ſeparable <hi>yet,</hi> altho not by <hi>Nature</hi> without the <hi>Help</hi> of another, but by <hi>Art</hi> the <hi>Hand. Maid</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi> Hence the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Baſis</hi> of the <hi>Tranſmutatory Art,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> the true <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Alchimy,</hi> to wit, that a more <hi>Impure metal</hi> may poſſeſs in it ſelf the ſame <hi>pure</hi> of which <hi>Gold</hi> is, with which altho ſome <hi>Impure</hi> be Concoagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>yet</hi> this <hi>impure</hi> is no wiſe of <hi>Metallick Impoſition,</hi> altho one Imperfect <hi>Metal</hi> differs from another, alſo from the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> therefore ſince it is <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> it may be ſeparated by a <hi>Triumphant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> which if it could be found above the <hi>Earth,</hi> moſt ſurely an <hi>Impure</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Metal</hi> would go into <hi>pure perfect Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> with reſpect to dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive Separation. For that every <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Agent,</hi> will be by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a <hi>digeſtive Agent,</hi> ſince <hi>this Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is impoſſible to be effected without
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52222:37"/>an Effectual <hi>Digeſtive Power.</hi> Such an <hi>Agent</hi> our <hi>Divine Arcanum,</hi> forit is a <hi>Heavenly Spirit</hi> and of a fiery <hi>Virtue,</hi> therefore has the <hi>Power</hi> of penetrating, and yet doth ſhew the Native <hi>Propriety</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> for it is <hi>Gold digeſted</hi> to the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream degree,</hi> [wherefore it tranſcends and excells common <hi>Gold</hi> by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, in an Homogeneity of the ſame kind and nature. Altho furthermore it be a <hi>ſpiritual body,</hi> yet] it doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come any other Body in the World by its <hi>fixity,</hi> to the end it may retain the <hi>Homogeneous Pure</hi> when it is caſt upon Impenfect <hi>Metals,</hi> leaſt they ſhould fly away from the <hi>Fire,</hi> becauſe of their <hi>Crudity:</hi> whilſt the <hi>Feces</hi> are expoled to be burned by its <hi>Heterogeneous Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> in which thing <hi>alone</hi> all Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative Digeſtion <hi>Conſiſts.</hi> For <hi>Fire</hi> is the Tryal of <hi>Gold,</hi> I ſay <hi>our Vulcan,</hi> which by <hi>burning</hi> will take away all <hi>Combuſtible</hi> Impurity from the <hi>Pure,</hi> if ſo be that that which is pure don't fly away from the tryal of the <hi>fire</hi> becauſe of its tender <hi>Crudity.</hi> But all <hi>Imperfect
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52222:37"/>Metals</hi> (altho they contain a Pure in themſelves) yet this <hi>Pure</hi> is ſo <hi>Crude,</hi> that is mixed with the <hi>Impure,</hi> that <hi>that</hi> not bearing the <hi>Fire,</hi> and yet predomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over <hi>this,</hi> flying away from the <hi>fire</hi> ſnatches it along with it, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would rejoice at the <hi>fire</hi> as its like. Moreover our <hi>Arcanum,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Hamogeneous ſubſtance,</hi> does enter ſuch like <hi>Imperfect Metals per minima,</hi> and what it finds like to it ſelt, and by its <hi>Prevailing Power,</hi> defends it from the Violence of the <hi>Burning fire,</hi> and retains its <hi>more then Perfect fixity,</hi> in the mean while <hi>Burning Vulcan</hi> does feed upon the Combuſtible by his Flame, which being Conſumed by the <hi>Fire,</hi> pure <hi>Gold</hi> remains, or <hi>Silver,</hi> (according to the quality of the Medicine) ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining all the Violence of the Fire, and remaining in <hi>all Probations,</hi> not at all inferior the Mineral, but rather Excelling it. Wherefore we do not (as ſome Detractors Object) profeſs to Create <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver,</hi> but to <hi>find</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52222:38"/>
                        <hi>effect</hi> an <hi>Agent</hi> which being caſt upon Imperfect Metals, can <hi>enter</hi> them <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minima,</hi> becauſe of its <hi>Homogeneity</hi> and <hi>Spirituality.</hi> Moreover that it may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Pure</hi> by its prevailing <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> from the Combuſtion of the Fire, which finding <hi>a Like</hi> to it Self, <hi>Retins</hi> it, until the Superſtions <hi>Feces</hi> be deſtroyed by the <hi>Burning Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> of <hi>Vulean;</hi> which Operation is <hi>Chryſopoetick Tranſmutation.</hi> All this our <hi>Secret Elixir</hi> performs. Moreover it has this, that it as well Commeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates its <hi>Tincture,</hi> as it is to: Finits actually to the Imperfect, ſince that it is both of the higheſt Exuberant <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> and <hi>Fixity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:52222:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold:</hi> alſo the Queſtion anſwered whether other <hi>Metals</hi> have <hi>Seed.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FOr the <hi>preſerving, propagating,</hi> and <hi>producing</hi> every <hi>Species Seed</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the great <hi>Creator</hi> to things: And Seed is the perfection of every thing; and that which has no <hi>Seed,</hi> is deſervedly to be Judged <hi>Imperfect:</hi> Therefore it is not to be doubted that there is <hi>Metallick Seed.</hi> Either all theſe things were <hi>Created</hi> in the firſt <hi>ſix dayes,</hi> which <hi>are</hi> or <hi>have been</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> or at <hi>leaſt</hi> they have <hi>Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> being Augmented daily. The <hi>firſt</hi> both <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> denys, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the <hi>latter,</hi> then no body can deny that there is <hi>Metallick Seed;</hi> which if there be, ſurely the <hi>Metal</hi> does not looſe it in Coagulation, for <hi>Coagulation</hi> is the effect of <hi>perfection,</hi> (or rather of <hi>Matura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:52222:39"/>which leads ſtreight to <hi>perfection,</hi> if the <hi>Exteriors</hi> be rightly Diſpoſed) more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over its <hi>Seed</hi> is a ſigne of <hi>perfection,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo <hi>Matured,</hi> therefore it is not probable that the <hi>Seed</hi> is loſt by Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but is rather rendred <hi>more noble.</hi> It is plain by this, that <hi>Metallick Seed</hi> is in <hi>Metals:</hi> Therefore it may be asked, whether all <hi>Metals</hi> have <hi>Seed</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves! I would anſwer by ſaying <hi>all</hi> have <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Seed,</hi> but in ſome it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>nearer,</hi> in others more <hi>remote:</hi> But <hi>this Seed</hi> is the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold.</hi> For it is in no wife lawful to think, that <hi>Jone</hi> has the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Jove, Saturn</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and ſo of the reſt, that is in a <hi>Jovial</hi> form, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnine,</hi> or <hi>Martial,</hi> for it is purely <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental,</hi> but the <hi>pure matter</hi> is <hi>Aureous,</hi> to which nothing is wanting beſides a bare <hi>digeſtion, ſeparative</hi> of the <hi>Dreggs. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive</hi> of the <hi>Crudities</hi> and <hi>Inductive</hi> of <hi>Fixity.</hi> But the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> is ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, that is, founded upon the fubſtance of matter it ſelf <hi>ſo purified:</hi> Therefore there is an <hi>Aureous ſeed</hi> in all imperfect <hi>Metals</hi> tending to perfection, but <hi>acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:52222:39"/>hindred in its <hi>pregreſs</hi> In digeſted <hi>Gold</hi> there is the <hi>ſame Seed,</hi> cloſly ſhut up, <hi>Triumphing</hi> in <hi>Perfection;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it ſhould be ſought to bring <hi>Seed</hi> out of imperſect <hi>Metals,</hi> it being farr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moto, <hi>altho truly exiſting</hi>) the Labour will be in wain, for it is neceſſary that all be eualted to <hi>Sol,</hi> other wiſe the <hi>Seed</hi> is not ſeparated from them, (being the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the thing.) I <hi>Mean Seed,</hi> not <hi>Mercury,</hi> which is in <hi>all,</hi> and is to be <hi>ardwn out</hi> of <hi>all;</hi> to that force <hi>in which</hi> and <hi>by which,</hi> they are all multiplyed: But <hi>Saturn</hi> is not multiplicable <hi>in Saturn,</hi> but <hi>in Gold only,</hi> to wit, where he ſhall come to <hi>Gold,</hi> that he may <hi>afterwards</hi> emitt his <hi>Seed,</hi> that is, <hi>his moſt digeſted Virtue</hi> from himſelf, that <hi>multiplication</hi> may have its <hi>Original</hi> from <hi>this.</hi> Concerning <hi>Lune</hi> it may not be unprofitable <hi>here</hi> to add ſomething, whom <hi>any one</hi> would eaſily believe to have <hi>Seed,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſhe</hi> is <hi>perfect.</hi> It ſeems to make for <hi>this Opinion,</hi> there being an <hi>Elixir</hi> ſerving to the <hi>projection</hi> of the <hi>white.</hi> Truly <hi>I grant</hi> that there is a <hi>multiplicative Seed,</hi> both of the <hi>white</hi>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:52222:40"/>and <hi>red,</hi> but <hi>this white</hi> is only <hi>contained</hi> in the Reins' of <hi>Sol.</hi> And altho there be a Multiplication of <hi>Luna,</hi> yet the Seed will not be found immediatly in <hi>Luna,</hi> but has a neceſſity to proceed from <hi>Sol:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we have ſaid this <hi>Lunar whiteneſs</hi> is the <hi>firſt</hi> degree of perfection, whoſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar yellowneſs</hi> is the <hi>Complement.</hi> For the <hi>Mother</hi> of our <hi>Stone</hi> which is called <hi>Land,</hi> (not <hi>Common</hi> but <hi>Philoſophical</hi>) is <hi>whith,</hi> becauſe it <hi>dealbates</hi> our <hi>Sol,</hi> which is the <hi>father</hi> of our <hi>Stone</hi>) with its <hi>whiteneſs,</hi> from whence the <hi>Offipring,</hi> which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from theſe two <hi>Parents,</hi> is <hi>white, firſt</hi> in Imitation of the <hi>Mothers form,</hi> and then it is <hi>Perfect Seed, multiplicative white,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wards it grows <hi>red</hi> with a <hi>Royal San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guineous redneſs,</hi> indued with a <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poetick Power.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:52222:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Virtue</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> and <hi>in what</hi> it is immediatly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BUt that we may obtain this <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> with which we might bring <hi>Imperifects</hi> to <hi>perfection,</hi> by a <hi>projection</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <hi>firſt of all</hi> it is to be Noted, what we have ſaid of our <hi>Arcanum,</hi> to wit, that it is <hi>Gold exalted to the ſupream degree of Perfection to which it can be brought by Art and Nature;</hi> alſo it will be obſerved that in <hi>Gold, Nature</hi> hath obtained a <hi>bound</hi> of <hi>her</hi> Operation, neither can it move it ſelf of its own accord any <hi>further.</hi> And yet its <hi>Seed</hi> is further to be <hi>matured</hi> with <hi>ſagacious wit.</hi> But <hi>this</hi> lyes further abſtruſe, neither eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to the <hi>ſight,</hi> as otherwayes the <hi>ſeed</hi> of <hi>Vegetables</hi> or <hi>Animals</hi> may be exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Eyes,</hi> not withſtanding by <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacious
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52222:41"/>Art</hi> it may be <hi>Extracted,</hi> and ſo far <hi>enalted</hi> above its own <hi>Virtus,</hi> in which <hi>Nature has reſted,</hi> that <hi>it</hi> may <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel</hi> it a <hi>thouſand</hi> times. I could relate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things of this <hi>Seed,</hi> which are rather to be kept <hi>Secret;</hi> but the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this <hi>Metallick</hi> and <hi>Vegetable,</hi> or <hi>Animal ſeed</hi> is diligently to be obſerved: For <hi>this,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Diſſimilarity</hi> of <hi>the part bringing forth ſeed</hi> is diſcerned when parted from the <hi>whole Body,</hi> but that <hi>Metallick</hi> is not ſo. But ſince the <hi>leaſt of Gold,</hi> is <hi>real Gold,</hi> therefore its <hi>Seed</hi> lyes by <hi>littles,</hi> neither can be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from its <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> in the mean while remaining a <hi>gueſt;</hi> but when the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nileſtation of the <hi>Seed</hi> it is done with the plenary Deſtruction of the <hi>Metal;</hi> and ſo <hi>Metal Reduced</hi> goes <hi>wholly</hi> into <hi>Seed</hi> therefore there is made a multiplication of the <hi>Seed,</hi> rather by <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> than <hi>Quantity</hi> and <hi>Number,</hi> that is, it is <hi>Nobiliteted</hi> rather than <hi>Increaſed</hi> (the <hi>Golden matter</hi> being reduced into <hi>Seed</hi>) becauſe of the ſimiliarity of <hi>Parts:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in reſpect of a <hi>Stone, Gold</hi> is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52222:41"/>
                        <hi>matter,</hi> when the ſecret profundity is manifeſted is <hi>wholly Sperm,</hi> which by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culating receives the <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>Superiours</hi> and <hi>Inferiours,</hi> and then it becomes whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>form</hi> or <hi>heavenly Virtue</hi> capable of Communicating <hi>this</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> which are related to it by the <hi>Homogeneity</hi> of <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> The <hi>place</hi> in which the <hi>Seed</hi> refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth is immediatly Water, for in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king properly and exactly, the <hi>leaſt part</hi> of <hi>Metal</hi> is <hi>Seed,</hi> but inviſible; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Inviſible is univerſally pour'd out, through all the <hi>Water</hi> of its <hi>Kind</hi> and inhabits it, and exert its <hi>Virtues</hi> in it, nor is any thing elſe manifeſted but <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> altho the internal <hi>Agent,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is <hi>Seed, reaſon</hi> perſwades us to be there; wherefore we promiſcuouſly call the whole, <hi>Seed,</hi> as we call a whole Grain <hi>Seed,</hi> when yet the Germinating <hi>Life</hi> is only the <hi>leaſt</hi> particle of the <hi>Grain.</hi> But <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>ſeminal Virtue</hi> is not ſo diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in <hi>Metals,</hi> but is inſeparatly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt, through the <hi>least</hi> of the Body con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining. I have added theſe things of the <hi>Seed,</hi> becauſe it is ſaid above that a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:52222:42"/>whoſe <hi>profundity</hi> has been ſo mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt under a <hi>Mercurial form,</hi> doth all go into <hi>Seed;</hi> for we name all that <hi>water</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>Exquiſitely</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed through it, in as much as it cannot be <hi>ſeparated</hi> but by Reaſon alone. This is called <hi>occult Ferment, Poyſon</hi> by the <hi>Ancient wiſe Philoſophers;</hi> alſo <hi>inviſible fire,</hi> the <hi>ſecret Agent.</hi> Neither alſo have I alone named the whole promiſcuouſly <hi>Seed</hi> after a manner, but theſe alſo have often called their <hi>Water, Fire,</hi> ſometimes they Taught that <hi>fire</hi> reſides in their <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Wherefore they diſtinguiſhed this into <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> of which the <hi>former</hi> is the <hi>means,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> the <hi>active Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> by that means. Therefore we name <hi>Water Seed</hi> Metonimically, when yet in ſpeaking <hi>properly,</hi> the ſeminal <hi>Virtue</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally inhabits, and is diffuſed through the <hi>whole Water,</hi> which indeed is <hi>Seed,</hi> but is not ſeparable from the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of its <hi>water.</hi> If it ſeem a <hi>wonder</hi> to any one, that I aſſigne <hi>water</hi> the <hi>Seat</hi> of the <hi>ſeminal Spirit,</hi> let not this ſeem a wonder, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52222:42"/>firſt <hi>Creation</hi> was carried upon the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> that is, the <hi>Heavenly Spirit</hi> infuſed through the <hi>Waters,</hi> it enriched them with its <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>prolifick Virtue.</hi> For in this alone all <hi>Seeds</hi> which are in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> were founded from the <hi>firſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, neither ever go out of it, and yet, in <hi>Vegetables</hi> they are produced into the <hi>Crude Air,</hi> in <hi>Animals</hi> preſerved within their <hi>Reins,</hi> in <hi>Minerals</hi> they are firmly ſhut up in their <hi>profundity.</hi> For it is impoſſible that <hi>Seed</hi> ſhould go out of its Original <hi>Seat.</hi> Therefore if all things are from <hi>Water</hi> (as we have ſaid) <hi>Reaſon</hi> will teach us, that the <hi>Seed</hi> even as yet, doth reſide in <hi>Water.</hi> Things are not <hi>preſerved</hi> any other way then from whence they <hi>ſpring,</hi> for the Cauſe of the <hi>Original</hi> being taken away, the <hi>Effect</hi> is taken away, hence it comes to paſs that the <hi>multiplication</hi> of all things is <hi>in humido &amp; per humido</hi> even as the <hi>Nutriment. Vegetables</hi> by a <hi>watry Leffas</hi> of <hi>Earth, Animals</hi> by a <hi>liquid Chile, Metals</hi> by a <hi>Mercurial Liquor.</hi> Hence <hi>Vegetables</hi> being <hi>Increaſed</hi> and <hi>produced,</hi> of their own
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52222:43"/>accord does ſeparate a <hi>Seed</hi> different from their whole <hi>Body,</hi> into the crude <hi>Air,</hi> which will be a Coagulated <hi>Body,</hi> but that it may be known that it has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from <hi>Water</hi> and does retain its <hi>ſeminal Spirit</hi> in the <hi>water,</hi> it is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Earth</hi> to increaſe its <hi>ſpecies,</hi> in which <hi>Matrix,</hi> by a <hi>watry Leffas</hi> of <hi>Earth,</hi> it is reſolved into its next <hi>watry</hi> matter, and then begins the <hi>Vegetation.</hi> Moreover the <hi>Watry ſeminal,</hi> receives this <hi>Watry Leffas</hi> (by which it is manifeſt in the Diſſolution) and that Germinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is for the <hi>Radical Nutritive Humor</hi> by which it receives Increaſe, to a <hi>plant,</hi> or <hi>Tree,</hi> according to the <hi>ſpecifick</hi> Ferment of the <hi>Seed. Animals</hi> do keep within their <hi>Reins</hi> a <hi>Seed</hi> ſprung from Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Generation,</hi> being Diffuſed into a due <hi>Matrix,</hi> forms a <hi>Faetus,</hi> tender and abounding with much <hi>Humidity,</hi> which afterwards is increaſed by the <hi>Liquid Female Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruums,</hi> and increaſes into a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Infant,</hi> and coming into the <hi>world,</hi>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:52222:43"/>in the hour of its <hi>Nativity,</hi> is Nouriſhed by <hi>milk,</hi> until he can bear ſtronger <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which then unleſs they are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a <hi>Liquid Chyle</hi> (as <hi>Bones</hi> in the ſtomach of a <hi>Dogg,</hi>) don't nouriſh. In like manner to all theſe things <hi>Metals</hi> Coagulated doth ſhut up their <hi>Seed,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly elaborated under thick <hi>Coverts,</hi> yet being placed in <hi>Water,</hi> this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being Extracted by <hi>ſagacious Art,</hi> Increaſes, and is Cheriſhed in a due <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,</hi> until by a <hi>previous Corruption,</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives its <hi>glorification.</hi> But this <hi>Work</hi> is very difficult, becauſe of the ſecret foulds of <hi>Metals</hi> in which this <hi>Seed</hi> is ſhut, giving place to no <hi>force,</hi> unleſs there be a ſubtile wit. Moreover I make it known, that there is a <hi>Matrix,</hi> in which <hi>Gold</hi> being put (from whence <hi>Seed</hi> alone is to be <hi>Sought</hi>) will emitt its Sperm <hi>freely</hi> and <hi>ſweetly,</hi> until it be weakened and <hi>dye,</hi> and by its <hi>Death,</hi> ſhall be renewed into a moſt <hi>glorious King,</hi> having afterwards got the <hi>power</hi> of delivering all his <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> from the fear of <hi>Death.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:52222:44"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the</hi> Manner <hi>and</hi> Means <hi>of Extracting its</hi> Seed.</head>
                     <p>THoſe things are always <hi>moſt difficult</hi> which are <hi>most excellent,</hi> as the Experience of all <hi>Ages</hi> will bear ample <hi>Teſtimony.</hi> It is not to be wondered therefore, if ſo great a difficulty be found in a <hi>ſubject</hi> ſo <hi>noble</hi> before others. For I do not well know any <hi>work,</hi> in <hi>Rerum Natura,</hi> encompaſſed with more <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties</hi> then this is. Wherefore if any one ſhall enter upon this <hi>Work,</hi> and yet would <hi>ſpare</hi> his <hi>mind</hi> from <hi>ſtudy</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> he muſt return back again, for he has miſſed his <hi>way</hi> in the <hi>very Entrance.</hi> For that the <hi>Evils</hi> which are in the <hi>Work</hi> appear Terrible, Chiefly upon the account of <hi>Diſpondency.</hi> But if the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>Lights,</hi> ſhall grant the <hi>Key</hi> of the <hi>Art</hi> to any one, there remains to him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52222:44"/>more, then the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>Women,</hi> and the <hi>Play</hi> of <hi>Children:</hi> As to delight his <hi>Eyes</hi> as he Labours, with moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful appearing <hi>Signes,</hi> untill he ſhall reap his <hi>Harveſt,</hi> that he may poſſeſs the moſt precious <hi>Treaſure</hi> of all the <hi>World.</hi> But without this, <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Loſs, Care</hi> and <hi>Vexation,</hi> will be the Fruits of his vain <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> Therefore every <hi>wiſe man,</hi> before he enters upon his <hi>Work,</hi> ſhall be firſt and <hi>chiefly</hi> ſolicitous of knowing it with its <hi>marks,</hi> that if by chance any Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties may appear in it, he being <hi>Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> againſt them, may not after his <hi>Work</hi> is begun, be compelled to return with <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>ſorrow.</hi> Therefore let all <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>Art</hi> know, that in order to attain our <hi>Arcanum,</hi> there is need to manifeſt the moſt <hi>hidden Seed</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> which is not done but by a <hi>plenary,</hi> and every way <hi>volatilization</hi> of the fixed, and then the Corruption of its <hi>form.</hi> Moreover ſo to deſtroy <hi>Gold</hi> is the moſt ſecret Work of the whole <hi>World.</hi> For this <hi>Divine Science</hi> is not compleated in a <hi>Corroſiſe</hi> Deturpation of the <hi>Mtal,</hi> nay all ſuch
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52222:45"/>
                        <hi>Corroſions</hi> are falſe and Erroneous; ſinee that there is required to our <hi>Work</hi> not any Diſſolution but <hi>Philoſophical,</hi> that is, into <hi>Mercur al water,</hi> made by a previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Calcination,</hi> by a <hi>Mercurial Agem,</hi> which is produced by a ſubt ile <hi>Rotation</hi> and Converſion of <hi>Elements,</hi> which <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination</hi> is a <hi>mortification</hi> of a <hi>Homogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Humid,</hi> with a <hi>dry</hi> of its own Nature, that afterwards the dry may be viviſied by the ſaid <hi>Humid</hi> ſo farr, that the muſt digeſted <hi>Virtue</hi> by diſſolving, being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by the <hi>Diſſolvent,</hi> may be the Cauſe of this <hi>Calcination</hi> and <hi>Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Is there any thing here <hi>Common</hi> with a Corroſive Contrition of <hi>Bodies</hi> by <hi>Mire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral waters?</hi> Nay rather the foreſaid O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations are <hi>Diametrically</hi> oppoſite. If any one ſhall conſider theſe things right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he will eaſily perceive the trouble of the <hi>Work.</hi> For <hi>Gold</hi> being the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, moſt <hi>fixed</hi> of all <hi>Bodies</hi> and of the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> Compoſition, moſt <hi>Patient</hi> of the <hi>fire</hi> and not at all obnoxious to <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> does not eaſily paſs over into <hi>a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſo Contrary to this of its own,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52222:45"/>Therefore if any one ſhall attempt this by <hi>force</hi> he will <hi>profit Nothing:</hi> Seeing there is required an <hi>Agent</hi> of an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Virtue to do this, which ought to be <hi>Homogeneal, Amicable</hi> and <hi>Spiritual,</hi> namely that it may be related to the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and yet be able to overcome it and <hi>fundamentally</hi> penetrate it whoſe <hi>ſecret</hi> Parts, ſince they are diſtended ſo fart, and ſo little <hi>Gold,</hi> is true <hi>Gold</hi> will not ſo eaſily puting off its <hi>form;</hi> nay it will fight until it be wholly overcome, it lyes down and <hi>Dyes,</hi> alſo it follows that our <hi>Agent</hi> ought to have an <hi>enlivening virtue,</hi> that it may Raiſe up a new pure <hi>Body,</hi> from the dead <hi>Carkaſſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:52222:46"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the firſt</hi> Philoſophical Agent, <hi>or</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, <hi>into which our</hi> Seed <hi>is to be</hi> Emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>and into which it is</hi> Ripened.</head>
                     <p>MOreover ſuch an <hi>Agent</hi> remains to be ſought out by us, where with we may do <hi>all</hi> the aforeſaid things. In which it is required, <hi>firſt</hi> of all, that the Water be <hi>Homogeneal,</hi> that is, by a <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> For that I have Taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, That the <hi>Golden ſeed</hi> doth lye hid in the <hi>Water</hi> alone, and doth obtain its <hi>Power.</hi> But it is ſhut up in the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Gold</hi> under moſt thick <hi>Foulds,</hi> of which is manifeſt a plain <hi>Contrary</hi> one to that hidden one which we ſeek. Therefore this <hi>Water</hi> remains to be drawn out by a ſubtile <hi>Artifice,</hi> but it doth not enter in of its own accord; therefore this is to be effected by <hi>another</hi> thing, which other thing indeed ought
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52222:46"/>to be of the ſame <hi>Nature,</hi> with that which we ſeek to draw forth. For eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>like</hi> begets its like, that is every <hi>Agent</hi> Exerciſing its Generative <hi>Action</hi> upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, changes that upon which it <hi>acts,</hi> into its own <hi>Nature</hi> as near as it can. And nextly it behoves this <hi>water</hi> to be related to the <hi>Body</hi> to be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> and therefore <hi>pure, Clean</hi> and exquiſitely cleanſed and purged from all <hi>filth.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this enough, but <hi>Gold</hi> is held to be Contraried in all its qualities, in which it differs from the <hi>Water</hi> we ſeek, wherein the <hi>Seed</hi> lyes hid. The former is highly <hi>fixed,</hi> the other highly <hi>Volatile,</hi> the former a moſt <hi>ſolid Body,</hi> this a moſt <hi>penetrating Spirit,</hi> the one <hi>thick,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſubtile,</hi> the one <hi>dead,</hi> the other <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> and <hi>enlivening,</hi> and all the other <hi>Conditions,</hi> are required which we ſeek in it after <hi>diſſolution,</hi> but they are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a <hi>dead Coagulated Body.</hi> Therefore it is Concluded, that <hi>Mercury</hi> alone is the true <hi>Key</hi> of the <hi>Chymical Art,</hi> which is indeed that <hi>dry Water,</hi> ſo often deſcribed by <hi>Philoſophers, ſluent, ſtipery,</hi> and yet
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52222:47"/>not <hi>wetting</hi> the <hi>hands</hi> of the Toucher, or any other thing, which is not of the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of its <hi>Matter,</hi> and moreover it is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Virtues</hi> above deſcribed: this is the <hi>Keeper</hi> of <hi>our Gates,</hi> our <hi>Balſam, Oyle, Honey;</hi> our <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, May-dew, our fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, Mother, Egg, Secret Furnace, Stove, Sieve, Marble, true Fire, venomous Dragon, Treacle, burning Wine, Green Lyon, Bird</hi> of <hi>Hermes, Gooſe</hi> of <hi>Hermogenes, Double Sword</hi> in the hand of the <hi>Cherub,</hi> that defends the way of the Tree of <hi>Life,</hi> and is famous for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> other <hi>Names;</hi> and it is our <hi>Veſſel, true, hidden,</hi> alſo it is our <hi>Philoſophical Garden</hi> in which our <hi>Sun</hi> riſes and ſets, it is our <hi>Royal Mineral,</hi> and <hi>Triumphant Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable Saturnia,</hi> alſo the Caduce of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> becauſe it Operates <hi>wonderful</hi> things, and <hi>transforms</hi> it ſelf according to its own <hi>pleaſure,</hi> that it may put on Different <hi>Masks.</hi> Concerning this <hi>water</hi> the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> ſaith, <q>Let <hi>Chymiſts</hi> boaſt as they will, but the <hi>Tranſmutation</hi> of <hi>Metals</hi> is impoſſible without this.</q> What ſhall I <hi>ſay,</hi> what ſhall I <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port its <hi>Praiſes.</hi> It is not ſo in its own <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:52222:47"/>as we render it by our <hi>Artifice:</hi> it is a thing very <hi>Vile,</hi> and yet the moſt <hi>precious Treaſure</hi> of all the <hi>World.</hi> O the perfection of <hi>Nature!</hi> and the <hi>head</hi> of <hi>Metallick Works!</hi> therefore thou <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> and ſtudious of <hi>Art,</hi> attend that thou mayeſt <hi>attain</hi> thy deſire. Take that which is moſt <hi>unclean</hi> of its ſelf, that is our <hi>Harlot,</hi> purge throughly all the <hi>Filth</hi> and draw from thence what is the <hi>pureſt,</hi> that is our <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> or <hi>Regal Diadem.</hi> Behold I have finiſhed in <hi>few</hi> Words that which <hi>Enobles</hi> a <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> delivers from <hi>Errors</hi> and leads forthwith into a moſt fair field of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</hi> Therefore that I may conclude this <hi>Chapter,</hi> I will repeat ſuccinctly all things which hath been ſaid before. There is a Certain and true <hi>Science</hi> called <hi>Alchmy,</hi> whereby every imperfect <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> is perfected into <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver,</hi> by the projection of the Triumphant <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> upon them, <hi>penetrating</hi> and <hi>tinging,</hi> which Secret is no other then <hi>Gold</hi> Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to its ſupream degree of <hi>perfection,</hi> and this by Sagacious <hi>Art,</hi> the Handmaid of <hi>Nature.</hi> For that all Imperfect <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:52222:48"/>are of the ſame <hi>Material</hi> Impoſition with <hi>Gold,</hi> nor do differ but in the <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> alone, as alſo by the <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of incompleated Decoction. And that which being Imperfect, is mixed with them, is plainly <hi>heterogeneous,</hi> and altho it ſtick <hi>Externally</hi> to the <hi>pure</hi> yet it is not United <hi>Inwardly,</hi> and therefore may be rejected, by a prevalent <hi>Agent,</hi> ſuch is our <hi>compleat Elixir</hi> to obtain which <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> the <hi>Sperm</hi> (which lyes ſecret in the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Gold</hi>) is to be drawn out, which is ſhut up in moſt thick <hi>Coverts,</hi> and gives place to no <hi>power,</hi> but only is manifeſt by Sagacious <hi>Art.</hi> Which when it appears (being hid <hi>firſt</hi>) it comes out under a <hi>Mercurial form,</hi> from whence it is Exalted into the <hi>fifth Eſſence,</hi> firſt <hi>white,</hi> then <hi>Red,</hi> by a Continual decocting <hi>fire.</hi> And all this is done by a <hi>Homogeneous Mercurial Pontique Agent, Pure, Clean, Chriſtaline</hi> without Tranſparency, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid</hi> without humectation, which is <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> truly <hi>Divine,</hi> neither it is found up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Earth,</hi> know the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> is made by <hi>this, Nature</hi> Cooperating.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52222:48"/>Which we <hi>know, have ſeen, have done, have</hi> and <hi>poſſeſs,</hi> and ſtudy to make it plain to the <hi>Ingenious,</hi> yet ſo that driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the <hi>unworthy,</hi> we may Exclude them altogether from the <hi>Art,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Caſt off, we will accompany the <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> into this moſt beautiful <hi>Garden.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the</hi> Genealogy <hi>of the</hi> Philoſophical Mercury, <hi>its</hi> Riſe, Birth <hi>and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing</hi> Signes <hi>that go before and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SOme Boaſting and Arrogant <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> after having Learned from the Reading of <hi>Books,</hi> that <hi>Common Mercury</hi> is very Forraine, to this <hi>Art,</hi> alſo reading that <hi>Philoſophers</hi> do call this by <hi>diverſe Names,</hi> being led preſently with a blind Opinion, they think themſelves ſecure of the <hi>Art,</hi> and do not bluſh to Affirm
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52222:49"/>themſelves <hi>Maſters</hi> of this <hi>Science,</hi> when in the mean time they are more <hi>blockiſh</hi> then the Wood it ſelf. Some will have this to be a <hi>Diaphanous menſtruum</hi> and <hi>Limped,</hi> others a certain <hi>Metallick Gum,</hi> when they Dream it to be permiſſible with <hi>Metals,</hi> and to no purpoſe; Others who ſeek the <hi>true Mercury,</hi> do indeavour to draw it either out of <hi>Common Mercury,</hi> by infinite previous Purgations, or of <hi>Metals,</hi> by refuſcitative <hi>Salts</hi> (as they call them) neither <hi>Water</hi> nor <hi>Gum,</hi> nor <hi>Calx</hi> nor <hi>Powder,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>fatt</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuous.</hi> But thoſe that Indeavour to draw <hi>Mercury</hi> out of <hi>Herbs</hi> and ſuch like, are <hi>thick Skull'd,</hi> and of wretched Wit. But this Opinion happens to them through a <hi>deep</hi> Ignorance of <hi>Metallick matters.</hi> They ſeek things <hi>pure,</hi> but what are they Ignorant of, they do not apprehend the Operations of <hi>Philoſophical Mercury</hi> in its <hi>Cauſes,</hi> being uncertain, they therefore ſeek ſomething Inſtead of <hi>Common Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury:</hi> For they do not know in what, the <hi>Mercury</hi> of the <hi>vulgar,</hi> is wanting to be the the true <hi>Mercury</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi>
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:52222:49"/>and yet they reject it, becauſe <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> do not Chuſe it; or laſtly do ſeek, by <hi>waſhing, ſubliming</hi> and <hi>decocting,</hi> to alter it from its Nature, not doubting but it will put on its true <hi>Philoſophical form,</hi> if it has once put off its own. It would be a trouble to reckon up ſuch like Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Wherefore I paſs over to the thing it ſelf, whence there may be a true <hi>Index</hi> of its <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſity,</hi> of its <hi>ſtreightneſs</hi> or <hi>Obliquity.</hi> I have taught before, that all <hi>Metals</hi> are of the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial <hi>Principle,</hi> to wit, of <hi>Mercury,</hi> it follows therefore that <hi>Mercury</hi> is indeed a <hi>Metallick</hi> thing, and therefore altho <hi>Common,</hi> yet Originally doth obtain a <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous matter</hi> with all <hi>Metals.</hi> If therefore <hi>Philoſophical Mercury</hi> will be an <hi>Homogeneous Metallick Water,</hi> it follows that materially and Fundamentally it is not Diſtinguiſhed from other <hi>Mercury,</hi> unleſs ſo far forth as one is <hi>purer</hi> then the other and more <hi>hot,</hi> and yet both a dry <hi>Mineral</hi> Water. Therefore let the <hi>Sons</hi> of Learning know that the matter of <hi>Common Mercury,</hi> ought and can paſs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52222:50"/>into the matter of <hi>Philoſophick Mercury,</hi> altho not into the whole <hi>Subſtance</hi> which is beheld in it. For certainly all Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Chymiſts</hi> know, that there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mercury,</hi> from whence come all <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> then <hi>Common</hi> (namely in reſpect of its Original) which is generated in the Bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> as long as it hath remained ſafe from the <hi>Crude Air,</hi> in a place fit and accomodated to Generation, it is altogether deſtined to Procreate <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> and did retain its Motion and Excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its ſelf, that it might be ſtirred up to a <hi>perfect</hi> Generation, for the fitneſs of the <hi>Place</hi> being <hi>violated,</hi> or <hi>viciated</hi> by Chance, this <hi>Matter,</hi> as tho it were ſtruck with the Hammer of <hi>Death,</hi> altogether looſeth all <hi>Motion,</hi> neither be moved fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any more, like an <hi>Egg,</hi> (upon which a <hi>Hen</hi> hath ſet for ſome time) being <hi>Cooled</hi> is thence forth rendred unfit to produce a <hi>Foetus,</hi> the pure <hi>Life</hi> or Internal <hi>Heat</hi> altering, vaniſhes away, the <hi>outward</hi> fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſo that which before <hi>every day</hi> tended to perfection, now being hindred by chance, becomes <hi>abortive,</hi> no hope
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52222:50"/>being left of a future ſpontaneous <hi>Motion.</hi> This is the cauſe when ſome have tryed with <hi>Heat</hi> Artificially Invented, to heap <hi>Earth</hi> upon <hi>Mercury,</hi> they have obtained but a mock Reward of their <hi>Labours.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Form</hi> in its acceſs is taken away, or rather hindred, which (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid) is a <hi>particle of ineffable Light,</hi> which is preſent enlightening its <hi>dwelling</hi> ſo long as all things ſhall be rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed outwardly; and ſo it leaves an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of its ſelf in things, which being received by things, doth produce the <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which is the true <hi>Author</hi> of all <hi>Tranſmutation,</hi> altering things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in which it is, by its <hi>Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Odour,</hi> ſtirring up to a <hi>Corruptive</hi> as well as a Generative Motion, but the accidents required to theſe things, fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>without,</hi> all theſe things fall of their own accord, neither is the ruin eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repaired by any <hi>Art.</hi> Therefore there is left to us a <hi>Crude Metallick, Indigeſted, Cold Matter,</hi> neither <hi>purged</hi> by <hi>Decoction;</hi> which (in reſpect to <hi>Minerals</hi>) Immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates the Nature of <hi>Fountain Water</hi> (in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:52222:51"/>reſpect to <hi>Vegetables</hi> and <hi>Animals</hi>) this is the <hi>true Matter</hi> to which the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Philoſophical Mercury</hi> is wanting, for which it is held to change its own, that there may be made from thence what we ſeek for. But it is different from this <hi>form,</hi> in a <hi>double</hi> Reſpect, <hi>firſt</hi> of the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity</hi> it retains in it <hi>ſelf; Secondly</hi> of that <hi>Spiritual Virtue</hi> which is wanting in it. <hi>Superfluity</hi> is <hi>twofold,</hi> the <hi>Leprous Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> part, and the <hi>Hydropical watry</hi> part. But there is a defect of true <hi>Sulphureous heat,</hi> the Addition of which will <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> purge out all its <hi>ſuperfluities.</hi> For <hi>Philoſophical Water</hi> is the <hi>Womb,</hi> but there is no <hi>Womb</hi> fit for generation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Heat,</hi> add therefore and ſupply to <hi>Mercury,</hi> that which is wanting, to wit, a <hi>Fiery Force</hi> to <hi>Burn,</hi> and his <hi>Dreggs</hi> will fall from him of its own accord, which thou ſhalt <hi>Exquiſitely</hi> ſeparate, if thou ſhalt perform this, thou haſt perfected the <hi>Work</hi> of a very quick-ſighted and skilful <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> Then <hi>Jupiter</hi> has got his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the Louring Clouds of <hi>Saturn</hi> being Diſcuſſed, he hath made a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:52222:51"/>bright and Glittering <hi>Fountain</hi> to appear unto thee. Thou wilt wonder at the <hi>extraordinary</hi> brightneſs of this Water, whoſe <hi>extraordinary</hi> Virtues, which it doth not receive from the <hi>matter,</hi> but the <hi>form,</hi> are to be found in no other thing in the whole <hi>World.</hi> For Inſtance it Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves <hi>Gold</hi> Naturally, by a true <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick</hi> Solution, not as indeavouring <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters</hi> Diſſolve, by Corroſive filthy <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and endeavouring to eſtrange it from a <hi>Metallick matter</hi> as farr as they can. This <hi>Mercury</hi> doth produce natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> of it ſelf, alſo the <hi>Arcanum</hi> of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> which I write knowingly, alſo the <hi>Adepts</hi> do know and witneſs the <hi>ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore I will conclude this little <hi>Trertiſe,</hi> becauſe what other things do remain to be ſpoken, are delivered in a <hi>peculiar Treatiſe</hi> candidly written by me. In the mean time, injoy thou theſe things, expect the Bleſſing from God. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For thou ſhalt obtain this from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>Lights</hi> alone.</p>
                     <p>So I have <hi>ſaid,</hi> ſo <hi>done.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <hi>Praiſe to</hi> GOD.</closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:52"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:52"/>
                  <p>A Short <hi>Manuduction</hi> To the Caeleſtial Ruby.</p>
                  <p>Written in LATINE By <hi>Eyraeneus Philalethes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh <hi>by a Lover of Art and Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, by <hi>T. Sowle</hi> in <hi>Holy-well Lane</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1694.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:53"/>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:52222:53"/>
                  <head>TRACT The SECOND</head>
                  <head type="sub">A ſhort Manuduction to the Caeleſtial RUBY.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Philoſophical Stone, <hi>and the</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>thereof.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe <hi>Stone</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> is a certain <hi>Caeleſtial Subſtance,</hi> Spiritual, fixt, Perfecting all <hi>Metals</hi> into true <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> (according to the quality of the Medicine) expoſed to all Tryals and that according to the <hi>Imitation</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and its <hi>Operations,</hi> as near as it can be done.</p>
                     <p>About this <hi>Subſtance</hi> the <hi>Art of Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> is converſant, which handleth and teacheth the Means and way of doing it,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:52222:54"/>but not by diverſe things, but by one thing alone it is done, to which nothing is to be added, nothing taken away but only the <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> removed.</p>
                     <p>But that which appertains to the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of this <hi>Art,</hi> Experience in this thing would be of much value to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men: For if it could be proved, that <hi>true Gold</hi> was made thereby, then indeed it would not be doubted both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> thereof. But it is plain that <hi>imperfect Metals</hi> are <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable</hi> after this manner, becauſe alſo general have been <hi>Deſtinated</hi> to perfect on, but ſome have remained <hi>imperfect</hi> for want of <hi>Digeſtion.</hi> Therefore if they can be duly <hi>Cocted</hi> would alſo be <hi>perfect,</hi> and ſeing nothing hinders in the <hi>Matter,</hi> but <hi>this</hi> may be done, becauſe out of one <hi>Fountain</hi> all <hi>Metals</hi> have proceeded, to wit, <hi>Crude Mercury;</hi> Cold and Moiſt, in which there hath been no <hi>difference</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> but only what <hi>Nature</hi> works after wards in this <hi>Matter,</hi> to wit, <hi>Decocting</hi> it more or leſs, this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath made the <hi>Diverſity.</hi> Therefore all other <hi>Metals</hi> may be <hi>perfected</hi> into <hi>Sol</hi>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:52222:54"/>to wit, by the help of our <hi>Divine</hi> and moſt <hi>perfect Magiſtery,</hi> which being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected upon <hi>imperfect Metals,</hi> is able ſo far to <hi>perfect</hi> them, by <hi>Decocting,</hi> as it is of a more then due perfection required in <hi>Gold.</hi> Here therefore we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, of how great Virtue and ſpiritual a Nature this our <hi>Divine Stone</hi> is, which can perfect that in one hour above the Earth, by a bare <hi>Projection,</hi> which <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> could not have Perfected by <hi>Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> Operations. Therefore it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt here, what <hi>Nature</hi> helped by <hi>Art</hi> can do. For that our <hi>Stone</hi> as it was <hi>perfected</hi> by <hi>Nature</hi> without the help of <hi>Art,</hi> was only of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nary Virtue,</hi> but the Virtue which is acquired by <hi>Art, Nature Co-operating</hi> and <hi>aſſiſting</hi> is <hi>Denary,</hi> in every <hi>Regimen,</hi> that is, after a manner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, for it cannot be computed, for that firſt by diſſolving it, and again <hi>Coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>Decocting</hi> it, one part of the <hi>Medicine</hi> falls upon a Thouſand of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect <hi>Metals,</hi> penetrating and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Tinging</hi> it: But if the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:52222:55"/>
                        <hi>Coagulation,</hi> being <hi>Iterated,</hi> thou ſhalt try to promote this Medicine further, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it is Extended <hi>in infinitem:</hi> For you ſhall ſooner want wit to compute, then the <hi>Elixir Virtue</hi> to <hi>penetrate</hi> and <hi>tinge:</hi> Not that immediatly by its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Touch, it <hi>tinges</hi> the whole, but by its Virtue and Influence, paſſes through the whole, ſince the leaſt particle of the <hi>Imperfect Body</hi> is touched and <hi>tinged</hi> immediatly by the <hi>Medicine.</hi> But the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſo, every part is <hi>tinged</hi> by the <hi>conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> part, like <hi>Leaven,</hi> therefore the <hi>Elixir tinges</hi> that which it touches more immediatly, with a <hi>Tincture</hi> a little more feeble then it was it ſelf, this again <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> that which is neareſt it, by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the <hi>Tincture,</hi> and that ſo long until the whole <hi>Maſs</hi> be brought to the Perfection of true <hi>Gold.</hi> But this is done in a ſhort ſpace of time, becauſe of the Spirituality of our <hi>Agent,</hi> which being a true <hi>Metallick Fire,</hi> like that Eleme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary one, does <hi>Imperceptibly</hi> warm and <hi>penetrate</hi> the hardeſt <hi>Bodies,</hi> even thoſe parts which were not touched by the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:52222:55"/>
                        <hi>Coals;</hi> and ſo this doth penetrate with its virtue <hi>Metals,</hi> being reſolved by the <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>fuſed,</hi> in a moment: So it hath often times been obſerved, that <hi>Dow</hi> is <hi>fermented</hi> by the <hi>ferment,</hi> even that outward part, which the <hi>Corporeal</hi> part of the <hi>Ferment</hi> never touched: juſt ſo it is done in this Work; obſerve therefore how Natural this <hi>Progreſs</hi> is in this Work. For we do not Profeſs to Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> (as ſome <hi>Reproachers</hi> falſly Object) by our <hi>Art,</hi> but out of thoſe things we ſay only in which theſe are by Nature, to wit, out of <hi>Metals,</hi> which are of the ſame Matter with <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> but of an inequal <hi>Digeſtion,</hi> and therefore remain imperfect, which by the <hi>Projection</hi> of our <hi>Arcanum</hi> upon them, we <hi>Digeſt</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> after this manner, ſince nothing elſe is required to <hi>Perfect</hi> them, beſides this ſimple <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction</hi> of their <hi>Crudity,</hi> which our <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi> can abundantly perform.</p>
                     <p>Ho therefore you Sons of <hi>Learning!</hi> attend to me! becauſe I will make known to you the whole Secret of our <hi>Stone,</hi>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:52222:56"/>which is not a <hi>Stone,</hi> and it is in every Man, and may be found in its own Place at all times. If you have this you have the moſt precious thing in the whole World. But it is <hi>Divine,</hi> and therefore not to be Communicated to all. But to you Sons of <hi>Learning,</hi> I will manifeſt the whole thing, neither will I conceal any thing neceſſary to this Magiſtery. But be preſent with attentive Minds and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my words, and lay them up in your ſecret <hi>Breaſts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You have heard before, <hi>The poſſibility of Tranſmutation,</hi> to wit, that a thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined to Perfection, but being left Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, through defect of <hi>Decoction,</hi> may by the Application of an <hi>Agent,</hi> of the ſame <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but of greater Digeſtion, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected (to which theſe Imperfect were Deſtinated) and matured, in as much as the <hi>Agent</hi> is of a more <hi>Exuberant</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, and more then perfect virtue. But our <hi>Stone</hi> is ſuch to all other imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Metals,</hi> whence we conclude without
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:52222:56"/>Controverſie, that theſe are <hi>Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> thereby into <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Conſider therefore you <hi>Lovers of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> what and of what kind, that ought to be, which can perform this, which by the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> is called a <hi>Stone,</hi> but it is in every Man, and in every thing, and at every time of the Year to be found in its place.</p>
                     <p>Obſerve my words! Note the Myſtery! becauſe it will moſt certainly Conſiſt of the <hi>Elements,</hi> then which nothing is more Univerſal, and thoſe not ſimply, but <hi>Compounded</hi> and <hi>Anatized,</hi> that is, every <hi>Element</hi> being to be known by its Quality: Therefore in every thing is our <hi>Stone,</hi> or every thing, or rather out of every thing, that is, <hi>Element,</hi> for any one of them, being deſtroyed, the <hi>Aurei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> periſheth. Be not therefore Solicitous concerning any thing Combuſtible by the Fire, for certainly that which is made out of every thing, that is, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the virtue or Qualities of every <hi>Element Anatized,</hi> reſiſteth the <hi>Violence</hi> of the <hi>Fire</hi> without danger.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:52222:57"/>
Hearken therefore you Sons of <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning!</hi> Behold I make known to you, the greateſt <hi>Myſtery!</hi> and God help you to conceal this <hi>Arcanum</hi> from all unworthy Perſons. Our <hi>Stone</hi> does not draw its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal elſewhere then from <hi>Metals,</hi> &amp; thoſe the moſt perfect: But ye ſhall ſuffer <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Operators</hi> in this Art, to ſeek it in all things Extraneous; but as many of you as are Lovers of <hi>Truth,</hi> don't attempt to find it out elſe where then in <hi>Metals:</hi> For this is our one, nay only true <hi>Principle.</hi> But what that is, it will be your part to Obſerve; neither to induce any <hi>Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> thing into this <hi>Work,</hi> but to leave that to others, which ſeek our <hi>Stone</hi> in ſuch things, but they ſhall always La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as long as they ſhall be Ignorant, what our only true <hi>Principle</hi> is.</p>
                     <p>But I do make known this to you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therefore, that a <hi>Lyon</hi> is Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated of a <hi>Lyon,</hi> a <hi>Man</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> but to expect the Generation of theſe from other things, it would be abſurd and Ridiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: <hi>Combuſtibles</hi> are produced even as <hi>Combuſtibles, Incorruptibles</hi> as <hi>Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibles.</hi>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:52222:57"/>Do you expect to gather <hi>Grapes</hi> from <hi>Thiſtles,</hi> or <hi>Roſes</hi> from <hi>Thorne:</hi> It would be ſo abſurd, if any ſhould go about to make our <hi>Stone</hi> out of <hi>Animals, Herbs</hi> or ſuch like things, as though the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Gold making</hi> were elſewhere to be ſought then in <hi>Gold:</hi> Therefore our <hi>ſtone</hi> is not to be ſought in ſuch things, which ought to have the <hi>Natural Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of <hi>true Gold,</hi> which are not in ſuch like things, neither to be found in them, except we be able to Create <hi>Sperms,</hi> which is in the ower of no Man, but is proper to <hi>God alone;</hi> and if any one ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelf to enect this, he would be <hi>falſe</hi> and a <hi>Lyar.</hi> Therefore let it ſuffice us, to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> and <hi>adminiſter Sperms</hi> which are ready to our Hands, but it is not to the Mattet, that new ones ſhould be Created from <hi>Heterogeneous things,</hi> which is both impoſſible to be done, and if it ſhould be done, theſe <hi>Artificial Sperms</hi> would be of no more virtue then thoſe Natural Ones, which Nature has fitted to our <hi>Work;</hi> therefore we muſt in no wiſe believe him that <hi>profeſſes</hi> to produce the <hi>Seed of Metals,</hi> out of <hi>Vegetables,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:52222:58"/>For altho he take to himſelf the Title of a <hi>Wonderful Philoſopher</hi> and a <hi>skilful Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> with the ignorant ſort, yet whilſt he knows not to uſe Created things, it is much leſs probable that he can <hi>Create Sperms.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whoſoever therefore will be a <hi>Son of Art,</hi> let him learn and acknowledge that our <hi>Stone,</hi> the <hi>Tranſmutor of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> into a perfect <hi>ſpecies,</hi> is nearly inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and contained in moſt <hi>perfect Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals:</hi> Out of theſe therefore let him be admoniſhed to Learn its <hi>Production,</hi> and not elſewhere.</p>
                     <p>Now therefore, if I be not deceived, you have heard plainly enough, whence the <hi>Matter</hi> of this <hi>ſecret Stone</hi> is to be ſought: And if you have well obſerved, it will not happen that you ſhould act in this thing: Now let us ſay ſomething of its <hi>Name,</hi> for it is explained how it is in every Man and Place. Now I will teach how, and why it is called a <hi>Stone</hi> and not a <hi>Stone:</hi> Laſtly I will adumbrate how it is to be <hi>Found.</hi> For the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſay that it is a <hi>Stone,</hi> and not a <hi>Stone,</hi>
                        <pb n="103" facs="tcp:52222:58"/>which ſome underſtand ill; but the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> for the moſt part, but it is Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to the letter, to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what they are Ignorant, to be like a <hi>Stone, tinging</hi> every thing, even by the very touch, into <hi>pure Gold,</hi> whether it ſhall be <hi>Wood</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for falſe (and deſervedly) therefore they judge it impoſſible to every <hi>Art,</hi> (except Diabolical:) Therefore the name of a <hi>Chymiſt</hi> being heard, they preſently abhor and deteſt him, nor look upon him any other then a <hi>Fooliſh Waſter</hi> of his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> being incited to this, by the falſe and confuſed Underſtanding of our moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> Stone; therefore the more Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Men do ſuperſtitiouſly believe, that ſuch men are to be Puniſhed by the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law:</hi> But under the Name of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Men,</hi> I do not only mean thoſe that are <hi>Plebeians,</hi> or <hi>Illiterate,</hi> and <hi>unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but alſo I mean ſome, nay many men otherwiſe Learned, and perhaps Pious, whom I therefore name Ignorant and unskilful in this Art; and alſo that they indued with ſuch Rude Manners, to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:52222:59"/>bark at every thing unknown, like <hi>Dogs,</hi> and ſpeak Evil of thoſe things, which they neither, either have or could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in their minds, my reproof Extends to them moſt, becauſe they being both <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Pious,</hi> do what is contrary to <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> to wit, Judge ſuch things which they neither do nor can diſcern. For when <hi>Learning</hi> admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, Piety Perſwades that every one ſhould Conſider and Examine thoſe things which he judges; theſe on the other hand condemn it undoubtedly, which yet after they have Condemned, they know not, and are ignorant what it is, which is very unworthy every wiſe Man.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, others <hi>studious</hi> in the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> altho they underſtand the thing a little more <hi>Natural,</hi> yet in this they err, becauſe they would make ſome <hi>Stony Congealation,</hi> to wit, they would make ſomething to bear the form of a <hi>Stone,</hi> for this alledging the <hi>words of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> which affirm it to be a <hi>Stone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But I would have you to Underſtand,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:52222:59"/>that it is not called a <hi>Stone</hi> becauſe it is like a <hi>ſtone,</hi> but for this Cauſe alone; that it flyes not from the Fire, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſixed in it, like as it were a <hi>ſtone,</hi> and for this it is called a <hi>ſtone,</hi> for the ſake of hiding this <hi>ſecret,</hi> but it is like a <hi>ſtone</hi> no otherways, and therefore it is not a <hi>stone;</hi> but in <hi>ſpecies</hi> is <hi>Gold</hi> more pure then the pureſt, in <hi>fixity</hi> or <hi>incombuſtibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> a <hi>ſtone,</hi> in <hi>Figure</hi> of moſt <hi>ſubtile Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> to ſight a <hi>grave Body,</hi> to touch <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palpable,</hi> to taſte <hi>ſweet,</hi> of <hi>good ſmell,</hi> in virtue a moſt <hi>penetrating ſpirit,</hi> being dry and yet <hi>unctuous,</hi> eaſily flowing upon a Plate of <hi>Metal</hi> and <hi>tinging:</hi> Therefore it is deſervedly called <hi>the Father of all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful things,</hi> ſince it hath all the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in it, yet ſo anatized, that none Predominates, but all four make one fifth <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> which is none of the four, but partakes of all, and is a moſt temperate <hi>Complexion,</hi> tho it be <hi>pure Metallick Fire,</hi> and this is our <hi>ſtone,</hi> which is not a <hi>ſtone,</hi> nor has any Name proper to its ſelf, and yet there is nothing in all the World whoſe Name it may
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:52222:60"/>not have, under ſome Conſideration. For that it is of ſo wonderful a <hi>Nature,</hi> as if we call it <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> it is <hi>true,</hi> if <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal</hi> we ſpeak <hi>properly:</hi> For it is <hi>Gold,</hi> and that not <hi>Vulgar</hi> but <hi>Spiritual,</hi> that is, <hi>ſubtile, penetrative</hi> and <hi>Noble:</hi> wherefore it is a <hi>ſpirit</hi> or <hi>fifth Eſſence,</hi> the moſt <hi>Noble</hi> of all <hi>Creatures,</hi> after the <hi>Rational Soul,</hi> and bringing all <hi>Diſtempers,</hi> and all <hi>Imperfections</hi> both in <hi>Animals</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> (according to the Quality of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine</hi>) to a moſt exact and perfect <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature:</hi> And that is truly our <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme,</hi> which we eſteem ſo much. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Powder</hi> or <hi>fifth Eſſence,</hi> neither <hi>Riches</hi> nor <hi>Health</hi> will be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God giving, to whom be glory for Ever.</p>
                     <p>But that I may come to the laſt part of my <hi>undertaken Task,</hi> to wit, that I may ſhow by what Means this our <hi>Stone</hi> may be obtained, for it is not Fabricated by Nature, but it is to be ſought, and to be Compoſed by the <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> of the <hi>Work-man;</hi> yet nature helping and ſeconding his Endeavour, for as it is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:52222:60"/>abundantly enough Declared, that the <hi>Matter</hi> of this <hi>Stone</hi> is not to be fetched elſewhere then from <hi>Metals;</hi> Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs theſe <hi>Metals</hi> are not our <hi>ſtone,</hi> for they have Another form Different from our <hi>ſtone.</hi> Notwithſtanding, I do not deny that our Medicine, is to be drawn from them, but the former form of the <hi>Metal</hi> muſt neceſſarily be taken away, that it may be drawn out, and that under the Conſervation of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> tho under the Diſtruction of that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and <hi>Individual</hi> Metal. But the <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> of <hi>Metals</hi> dwells, and is Conſerved in the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> which <hi>ſpirit</hi> reſides not in any other thing, but in Water <hi>Homogeneous</hi> of its own kind: For water is the <hi>Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> which is Eſpecially to be retained in the <hi>Conſervation</hi> of its <hi>ſpecies.</hi> Therefore <hi>Gold</hi> is to be Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from its <hi>Form,</hi> and that into <hi>Water Homogenous</hi> of its own kind, in which <hi>Water</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Gold</hi> is preſerved, which afterwards, <hi>Re-inſpiſſates</hi> its <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and Induces a new Form, after <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction,</hi> a thouſand times more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:52222:61"/>then the form of <hi>Gold,</hi> which it loſt by being <hi>re incrudated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore <hi>Metallick Bodies</hi> are to be reduced into <hi>Homogeneal Water,</hi> not <hi>wetting the Hands,</hi> that out of this <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> a new <hi>Metaltick Species</hi> may reſult, far more <hi>Noble</hi> than any <hi>Metal.</hi> This is our moſt <hi>precious Medicine</hi> and <hi>Coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Ruby.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But all this Work, very well Anſwers to the <hi>ſubterraneal Operations</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> from whence the <hi>Work</hi> is deſervedly called <hi>Natural.</hi> For Nature doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Metals,</hi> according to their <hi>ſpecies</hi> out of <hi>Mercury</hi> alone, <hi>Cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt,</hi> by a daily <hi>Digeſtion</hi> &amp; <hi>Coction</hi> in the Veins of the <hi>Earth.</hi> But <hi>Art</hi> to ſhorten the <hi>Work,</hi> hath found out a far more ſubtile Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet like to this: For it <hi>Conjoyns</hi> with <hi>Crude Mercury, cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt,</hi> ripe <hi>Gold,</hi> and both of theſe by <hi>Commixtion,</hi> and <hi>ſecret Conjunction,</hi> makes one <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which they Name <hi>Aqua Vitae,</hi> which <hi>Mercury</hi> at laſt they Decoct into <hi>Gold</hi> not <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but far more <hi>Noble:</hi> which fulls upon all <hi>Imperfect Metals,</hi> and <hi>tings</hi>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:52222:61"/>them into <hi>tryed Gold,</hi> expoſed to all Tryals.</p>
                     <p>You underſtand, therefore, as I believe, that tho our <hi>Stone</hi> be of <hi>Gold</hi> alone, yet it is not <hi>Vulgar Gold.</hi> That therefore our <hi>Gold</hi> may be fetched from <hi>Vulgar Gold,</hi> it is to be <hi>Diſſolved</hi> into <hi>Water,</hi> not <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary,</hi> but not wetting the Hands, that is <hi>Mineral:</hi> which Water is <hi>Mercury,</hi> which from a Red <hi>ſervant,</hi> hath means in its ſelf; to perfect the whole <hi>Work,</hi> without any Impoſition of Hands, and this at laſt is that only, true and Natural <hi>Principle,</hi> to which nothing is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nothing taken away, unleſs ſome <hi>ſuperſtuities,</hi> which without any humane help, its ſelf will <hi>perfect,</hi> by its own <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> and <hi>Natural Inſtinct.</hi> Therefore thou having this <hi>Mercury</hi> mind nothing elſe. With good Reaſon therefore, the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> ſaid, <hi>Imploy thy whole ſtudy in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocting Mercury,</hi> but I ſay to thee, let thy whole Study be <hi>Imployed</hi> in getting this <hi>Mercury,</hi> that is in <hi>Dealbating</hi> our <hi>Red Laren,</hi> which being done, thou haſt done thy Part, what remains is the work
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:52222:62"/>of <hi>Women</hi> and the Play of <hi>Boys:</hi> For <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> will be preſent to diſpatch the reſt, but in the mean while, a deſired reſt is given to thee, which indeed, as the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> ſaid, <hi>Is more deſirable then any Labour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For know that our <hi>Albification</hi> is no Light <hi>Work,</hi> being Radical, for this will be the <hi>Indicium</hi> of an <hi>Altered</hi> and <hi>reduced Body.</hi> Neither will <hi>Gold</hi> ſo <hi>Albificated,</hi> ever return to its <hi>Priſtine form;</hi> for from a <hi>Body</hi> it is made a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and from a <hi>fixt, Volatile,</hi> by this Operation. Therefore be wholly intent in <hi>Dealbating Laton,</hi> for it is eaſier to make <hi>Gold,</hi> then ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, for he that <hi>diſſolves</hi> ſo, <hi>Congeals</hi> it rather, for the ſolution of the <hi>Body,</hi> and the <hi>Coagulation</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> are <hi>Coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> in it.</p>
                     <p>But Conſider you <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and Note theſe <hi>Myſteries:</hi> That which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves is a <hi>ſpirit,</hi> but that which <hi>Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> is a <hi>Body.</hi> Therefore if you would Diſſolve your <hi>Body,</hi> firſt of all, you have need of a <hi>ſpiritual ſubſtance,</hi> becauſe a Body cannot <hi>diſſolutively</hi> enter a <hi>body,</hi>
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:52222:62"/>But a <hi>Spirit</hi> entreth it, <hi>Attenuating</hi> and <hi>Rarifying;</hi> and becauſe you require <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> therefore you have need of <hi>Water</hi> to manifeſt this: for every <hi>Agent</hi> Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing any Act upon any thing, <hi>Aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> that on which it Acts to its ſelf (as far as it can be done) and every Natural Effect is conformed to the Nature of the <hi>Efficient,</hi> therefore to draw <hi>Water</hi> out of the <hi>Earth</hi> you have need of <hi>Water.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I don't mean (as ſome badly think) by <hi>Water, Aquafortis, Aqua Regis,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Corroſives,</hi> which Common <hi>Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, Artificially Compound</hi> to themſelves, and put them to diſſolve theſe <hi>Metallick Species's</hi> which yet they don't Diſſolve, but Corrode, foul and Corrupt: for who would believe that thoſe <hi>Waters,</hi> can De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the old form of the <hi>Metal,</hi> under <hi>Conſervation</hi> of a <hi>Metallick Species,</hi> which yet themſelves are <hi>Aliens</hi> from a <hi>Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Nature?</hi> for they are not ſufficient Enough to deſtroy throughly the <hi>Species!</hi> Elſe they would Convert them into their own Nature? But as far as they can, they do Transform them into ſome fordid
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52222:63"/>thing: for the more Bodies are Corrod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the more they are Eſtranged from a <hi>Metallick Nature.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But our <hi>VVater</hi> is <hi>VVater</hi> of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and diſſolves Bodies into <hi>Mercury,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably is joyned with them, being Diſſolved, <hi>Cohabitates</hi> &amp; is <hi>Concocted,</hi> that from them may be made that one <hi>All-Spiritual</hi> thing which is ſought. For every thing that any thing <hi>Naturally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves,</hi> (that ſo the <hi>Species</hi> of the thing Diſſolved may be preſerved) remains with the thing Diſſolved, Materially and formally, and does <hi>Coaleſce,</hi> and is <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſſated</hi> by it, and nouriſhes it, as a <hi>Body</hi> may ſee in a <hi>Grain of Wheat,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>olved by a <hi>terrene Hamid Vapour,</hi> this <hi>Vapour</hi> remains with this Grain af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>diſſolution</hi> for its <hi>Radical Humidity,</hi> and <hi>Coaleſces</hi> with it into a <hi>Plant.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing alſo will be to be Obſerved in every <hi>Natural diſſolution,</hi> which ſince ſuch like Diſſolution, is the <hi>enlivening</hi> of a Dead thing, can be done by nothing elſe then that <hi>Living thing</hi> which was of the Eſſence of the Dead thing before
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:52222:63"/>it was Dead: As in a Grain the Life is dead as (I may ſay) which we would have vivified; this can be done therefore by nothing elſe but the vapour of the Earth, the <hi>Humidity</hi> and <hi>Calidity</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> for that the Grain its ſelf was <hi>Extracted</hi> out of the Earth, &amp; formerly was nothing elſe but ſuch like <hi>vapour</hi> which afterwards became dead by <hi>Decoction,</hi> therefore, by this alone naturally to be Vivified, under the <hi>Conſervation</hi> of its <hi>Species.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I write this, becauſe ſo many and ſo Learned Men are ſo much Deceived with that Vulgar <hi>Mercury,</hi> for altho it is a <hi>Mineral Water,</hi> yet not of a like <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> or <hi>Eſſence</hi> with <hi>Gold.</hi> For who will not confeſs, that if a Grain of <hi>Wheat,</hi> be caſt into a Pool of Water, it will not Germinate nor Increaſe (yet <hi>Bull-Ruſhes</hi> are wont to <hi>Vegetate</hi> there) whence is this I Pray? Except that the <hi>Aquaous</hi> humour was not eſſential to it, neither of a like Nature with the <hi>Wheat;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth not Naturally Diſſolve it, but Deſtroys it: Not otherways Gold if it be mixed to be Decocted with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52222:64"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:52222:64"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:52222:65"/>
                        <hi>Quickſilver,</hi> or any other <hi>Mercury,</hi> Except alone of its own <hi>Humidity,</hi> it doth not receive a Diſſolution in them, to wit, becauſe theſe Waters being too Crude, Cold and unclean, are of a far unlike nature with <hi>Gold:</hi> wherefore in theſe it is not amended, neither retained, neither with theſe Matured into a fart more Noble <hi>Perfection,</hi> then its Nature. Therefore at Length our <hi>Mercury</hi> is not <hi>vulgar Mercury,</hi> for it is a pure Water, Clean, Clear, Bright and Reſplendent, and worthy of much Admiration: It is Crude, Cold and Immature, if Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Sol,</hi> but in Reſpect of Common <hi>Mercury</hi> Digeſted, warm and Mature, which has no qualitys like to this, except alone in whiteneſs of Colour, and of its form of <hi>Flux</hi> in which notwithſtanding there is a great Difference.</p>
                     <p>But laſtly that you may well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what our Water is, by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I tell thee (and that moved with Charity) that it is Living, Running, Clear, Shining, White like Snow, Hot and Moiſt, Airy, Vaporous and Digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:52222:65"/>in which <hi>Gold</hi> is melted like <hi>Ice</hi> in warm Water, in this is Contained the whole Regimen of Fire and Sulphur which Exiſt but Predominates not. This is indeed <hi>the keeper of our Gates the Bath of the King and his Queen,</hi> davly Warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and that Inceſſantly, and yet is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken elſewhere then from the Matter, and is diſtinguiſhed from the whiten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the Water, yet joyned and appearing, under the ſame form of <hi>Flux,</hi> and the ſame Colour. This is that heat of the Lamp, which if it be Temperate, every day will Circumact the Matter, (until by Calcination the Humidity being dryed a ſecond Fire of Aſhes is produced, in which the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel or Water is <hi>Hermetically</hi> ſhut and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, according to the Saying of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, take a Veſſel ſtrick it with a Sword, take its Life, this is the Cloſure.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this our Water is our Veſſel, and in that our <hi>Furnace</hi> dwells ſecretly, whoſe Fire ought to be moderate, leaſt the whole Work be deſtroyed, yet ſtrong enough leaſt the Life Diſpond for want
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:52222:66"/>of Heat. Therefore in this Water the whole Secret of our Veſſel confiſts, alſo the Structure of the hidden <hi>Furnace</hi> is founded in the Compoſition of this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the Knowledge whereof, all our Fires, all our Weights, all our Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens lye hid. This Water is the Clear Bright Fountain in which our <hi>King</hi> is to be waſhed, that he may overcome all his Enemies, of this Water and its Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration be Careful, becauſe ſurely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other help except the Appoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a perfect purged and Cleanſed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Nature will make from hence our moſt Secret <hi>Stone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And I ſay to thee in Truth, that this Water is <hi>Mineral,</hi> pure and Clean, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be Extracted elſewhere, but out of thoſe things alone in which it is by Nature. And the things out of which it is immediatly Drawn, are moſt ſecret above all others. Alſo the Means of Extracting it is moſt wonderful; alſo its Virtues Stupendious. For it doth Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve <hi>Sol</hi> without violence, and is made friendly to it, and it waſheth him from
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:52222:66"/>all his Foulneſs: It is White, Warm and Clear; therefore praiſed be the moſt High, who hath Created this <hi>Mercury</hi> and given it a Nature overcoming all others. For certainly the Work of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymy</hi> would be in vain and uſeleſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Water. But conſider thou what this Water is, and Learn from the Work as I have done. For having this <hi>Mercury</hi> thou haſt the Key of the whole <hi>Art,</hi> with which thou mayeſt unlock all the moſt ſecret things of <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> Therefore our Water is of alike Nature with <hi>Gold,</hi> of an unlike Subſtance, in the making of which there is a great Stink. Conſider therefore and deeply weigh the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Nature, and do not mix any <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous</hi> thing: For Nature is only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by its own Nature, and by no other. But if you do not yet underſtand do not blame me, for I have ſincerely (as far as it is Lawful for a Man to ſpeak) Expounded to you the whole Matter: That therefore you may underſtand the Concluſion of the Matter, be very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. Our Stone is made out of one thing,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:52222:67"/>and four <hi>Mercurial Subſtances</hi> (whereof one is Mature, the reſt Crude, but pure, of which two are drawn out of a <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> by the third, but wonderfully) joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Temperate, not Violent <hi>Fire,</hi> and ſo <hi>Cocted</hi> every day, until all be made one by a Natural Conjunction, moſt ſecret, not Manual.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards the <hi>Fire</hi> being changed, let it be Digeſted with a <hi>Fire</hi> daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, at firſt more Moderate, and ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day increaſed until theſe <hi>Volatiles</hi> are fixed by a <hi>Sulphur</hi> of their own kind, fixt and incombuſtible, until the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound poſſeſs the ſame Nature, Fixity and Colour. For then it ſecurely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the Fire, and this is the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power of Power, overcoming every ſubtil and penetrating every ſolid thing; the virtue of which being turned into Earth appears compleat.</p>
                     <p>But there are, that I may deſcribe the thing particularly, manifold Degrees of this our Proceſs, in Number Twelve, all which I will hrieſly run over, the firſt whereof is called <hi>Calcination.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:52222:67"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Calcination.</head>
                     <p>And <hi>Calcination</hi> is the firſt Purgation of the <hi>Stone,</hi> the <hi>Exſiccation</hi> of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity,</hi> by the virtue of the <hi>Natural Heat</hi> of our Water, ſtirred up by the Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Heat, from whence the Compoſition is turned into <hi>Calx</hi> or <hi>Powder</hi> of a black colour, yet unctuous, and retaining the <hi>Radical Humiaity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The final Cauſe of this <hi>Calcination</hi> is, that the <hi>Solution</hi> may be the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the <hi>Stone,</hi> which without this cannot be had: For <hi>Gold</hi> is a very fixt Body, neither can it be immediatly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by our Water, except only in part, that is, be made ſoft, <hi>Incrudated</hi> and <hi>Albificated:</hi> In which <hi>Albification</hi> two Natures appear, <hi>volatile</hi> and <hi>fixt:</hi> which we liken to two <hi>Dragons,</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.</hi> Wherefore that a full Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution may be made, there is need of Contrition, that the Body by Calcinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be made <hi>ſpongious</hi> and <hi>viſcous,</hi>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:52222:68"/>becauſe then at laſt it is fit for Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
                     <p>The Second final Cauſe is this, that we Reconcile contrary Qualities, for whilſt they fight, they are unprofitable unto us: For in the firſt Conjunction our Water diſtinguiſhes between <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury, volatile</hi> and <hi>fixt,</hi> and theſe are Enemies to one another, and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, but it is our part to bring them to a Union, but contrary qualities are not reconciled, but by a Medium; there are therfore in our firſt Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, four contrary qualities, Heat, Cold, Dryneſs, and Humidity, of which two, Hot and Dry, are Attributed to <hi>Sulphur,</hi> Cold and Humid to <hi>Mercury,</hi> therefore they are oppoſed Diametrically, the heat of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and the Cold of <hi>Mercury,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Humidity of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and Siccity of <hi>Sulphur:</hi> To reduce theſe Contraries to friendſhip cannot be done without a Medium, but the Medium muſt be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of both, alſo ſuited to both. Would we therefore reconcile Cold and Heat, the Medium will be by Siccity, which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:52222:68"/>may be joyned to both Heat and Cold; by turning therefore the Compoſition into Earth, heat and Cold agree in this third thing, that they may dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to wit the Degree being abated: But afterwards being diſſolved into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, alſo two other Enemies are Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled Siccity and Humidity, by the <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidity</hi> of Water, ſo that now one is made of two by the Conjunction, made after a Natural Separation.</p>
                     <p>But the Efficient of this Calcination is, the Operation of Heat upon Moiſture, turning every thing that reſiſts it into moſt ſubtile Powder, but the moving Inſtrument is the <hi>Fire</hi> contrary to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is hid in our diſſolving Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſtirring up heat in the body, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting the Humidity into a viſcous and unctuous Powder.</p>
                     <p>But that this Operation is prior to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution take theſe Reaſons; it is prior, becauſe a certain Solution is made (as I may ſo ſay) by our Divine Water, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the congealation of our Spirit, will be expected in the next place, becauſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:52222:69"/>are always congealed after the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Body: For they have the ſame Operation, ſuch therefore as the Solution is, ſuch the Congealation is to be expected after it.</p>
                     <p>Then the Order of <hi>Nature</hi> requires this, for a Woman Exerciſeth her Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion firſt, then it is neceſſary to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by her Husband, but the Woman retains her whole Domination in the Water; this therefore will be the firſt Work, of the Man Exerting his Power to overcome that, in which the Woman poſſeſſeth both her Qualities, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, he will eaſily Subject to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that, in which ſhe hath only one qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, Heat is not Conſequentially joined neceſſarily to any Quality, but Siccity will always be the end of Heat: from whence it appears, that the man ought firſt to exert his Power, therefore <hi>Calcination</hi> is rightly called the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Work.</p>
                     <p>Therefore <hi>Calcination</hi> is the head of the Work, for without this, will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:52222:69"/>be Commixtion or Union, this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is to be done in the firſt days of thy <hi>Stone,</hi> for in the firſt Dealbation, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is Reduced into its firſt Principles, <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> of which the firſt is fixt, the other volatile, therefore are compared to two <hi>Serpents,</hi> or <hi>Dragons,</hi> the one Winged, ſhewing its Volatile Nature, the other without Wings, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting fixity, both theſe coming from one Fountain, tends to one thing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is likened to a <hi>Serpent</hi> taking his Tail in his Mouth, to ſhew that <hi>Sulphur</hi> is nothing without the ſubſtance of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> nor <hi>Mercury</hi> without the ſubſtance of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> but that this <hi>Mercurial Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,</hi> and <hi>ſulphureous Mercury,</hi> perfect the whole Art. Therofore it is deſervedly called one Compoſition, that altho it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears twofold in the beginning of the Work, whence it is called <hi>Rebis,</hi> yet by Conjunction they may be made one and the ſame, and this is called one <hi>Elixir,</hi> which never would be poſſible unleſs they were quite of the ſame Nature. Therefore the Nature of <hi>ſulphur</hi> and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:52222:70"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="123" facs="tcp:52222:70"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="124" facs="tcp:52222:71"/>
                        <hi>Mercury</hi> is diligently to be Obſerved, and we muſt take care of Errours, for theſe two are not contrary things, but one and the ſame <hi>ſulphureal Mercury,</hi> Mature and digeſted, and <hi>Mercurial Sulphur,</hi> crude and Imature.</p>
                     <p>Therefore that Divine kind of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, will be neceſlary to be obſerved, to wit, how Nature has Operated in Procreating <hi>Metallick</hi> Bodies in the <hi>Mines</hi> under the Earth, becauſe we do all things in our Work in Imitation thereof, as near as can be, therefore we chuſe the ſame Matter which ſhe hath made uſe of, altho Art has found out a far more ſubtile way to the Abreviation of the Work, and the more then perfect Exaltation of the <hi>Stone.</hi> For in <hi>Metallick</hi> Veins, one thing alone is found, <hi>viz. Mercury,</hi> which is very crude and frigid, and in which the <hi>ſulphureal</hi> quality al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together is unactive, alſo no Digeſtive heat is found there, but by an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Motion after a long time, by little and little this <hi>Metallick</hi> Principle is changed, until at laſt it be converted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:52222:71"/>fixt <hi>ſulphur:</hi> for that whilſt it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Frigid and Humid, it was called <hi>Mercury,</hi> in this Eleration or Excitation, it is named <hi>ſulphur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the matter is otherways in this our Work: For beſides <hi>Mercury</hi> Crude and Cold we have another thing, to wit, Mature <hi>Gold,</hi> in which Act, more active qualities Exiſt, this therefore we joyn to our <hi>Mercury,</hi> in which paſſive qualities are found, that the one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the other, and that which Nature, helpt by no Heat hath digeſted in the <hi>Mines,</hi> we having a double <hi>Fire,</hi> Digeſt, whence it comes to paſs that we don't make ſimply <hi>Gold,</hi> but ſome other thing much more Noble and excellent then <hi>Gold.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You ſee therefore what <hi>Sulphur</hi> is, what <hi>Mercury;</hi> how alſo we have a double <hi>Snlphur</hi> and a double <hi>Mercury</hi> in our Art, which yet are not diſtinct in Eſſence, but in maturity and perfection; alſo you underſtand, as I think, after what manner they are worked, ſince the <hi>Perfect</hi> Body of <hi>Gold</hi> is Incrudated by
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:52222:72"/>our Divine water not wetting the hands, and it is reduced to its firſt Principles, to wit <hi>Mercury,</hi> which is not without Sulphur, participating of the Natures of the Luminaries, therefore in this Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the Woman Aſcends upon the Man, and predominates over him for a Time, which indeed is unnatural, till the man begins to exert his Power, and then firſt of all by his ſiccity-bringing heat, does Exſiccate the Humidity of the Woman, by converting all into a moſt ſubtile and viſcous Powder, from which Powder by ſolution, water is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards diſſolved, in which Water is the ſpirit of the Diſſolvent and diſſolved, the Man and the Woman are joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But the excited <hi>Heat</hi> doth not here find a Bound, but as yet Works every day by ſeparation, by diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing between the <hi>ſubtile</hi> and the <hi>groſs,</hi> that the firſt may ſwim at the lop, the latter may ſubſide ſo long till all are of the fame quality, and then at length in the hour of their Nativity, they are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:52222:72"/>Conjoined, and the <hi>Man</hi> aſcends upon the <hi>Woman,</hi> and Impregnates her: at length ſhe brings forth the Cloud which the hath <hi>Conceived,</hi> in which me <hi>Putriſies</hi> and is <hi>Corrupted,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards both of them <hi>aſcend</hi> or <hi>ariſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>Glorious;</hi> not now divided, but made one and the ſame by <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and are ſo <hi>Coagulated, Sublimed, Cibated</hi> and <hi>Exalted,</hi> into a moſt perfect nature and <hi>Multiplyed</hi> in weight and goodneſs of Quality, according to your Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whoſe excellent <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as well in <hi>Projection</hi> as in <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore theſe <hi>black</hi> and <hi>stinking Aſhes,</hi> are not to be deſpiſed, ſince in them the <hi>Diadem</hi> of our <hi>King</hi> is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I tell you in all truth, that <hi>whiteneſs</hi> will never be had unleſs you make it <hi>black,</hi> for unleſs the <hi>Body putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies</hi> it will remain without fruit, but if it be Corrupted then indeed thou ſhalt ſee them ariſing from thence, where it ſeemed they had loſt their <hi>Bodies</hi> which they had, and they will appear that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:52222:73"/>which they never were before. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you therefore the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of our <hi>King,</hi> for unleſs you do this, you ſhall never admire himcoming from the <hi>East.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore you muſt take Care that you don't Err in this firſt <hi>Entrance,</hi> for the Work is ſpoiled unleſs you be wary here. The common Errors in this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration are many and various; Firſtly, of them who know not what is to be Calcined, but ſeek the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making</hi> in Extraneous things. Some bring in for their <hi>Material Principle,</hi> thoſe things which are not of the ſame Impoſition with <hi>Metals,</hi> ſuch are <hi>Borax, Alloms, Attrement, Vitriol, Arſnick, Seeds of Plants, Wine, Vinegar, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, Hair, Blood, Gums,</hi> and the <hi>Roſins</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> ſome do endeavour, (ſuch is their <hi>Blockiſhneſs</hi>) to Generate <hi>Salts</hi> of every kind, out of the <hi>Flame,</hi> I paſs by theſe underſtanding nothing at all in this Art. Others, altho they work in <hi>Metals,</hi> yet deſire to perfect <hi>Calcination,</hi> either with Corroſive <hi>Waters, Spirit of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:52222:73"/>Salt, Sulphur</hi> or <hi>Fire,</hi> and do indeed <hi>Corrode</hi> the <hi>Bodies,</hi> not <hi>Calcine</hi> them. For this <hi>Calcination</hi> is not made by the Native <hi>Calidity,</hi> of the Body, helpt by a Friendly heat, but by a <hi>Corroſive</hi> Force of <hi>Waters,</hi> without any propenſity of the <hi>Metal</hi> to it; therefore <hi>Metals</hi> are <hi>fouled</hi> and <hi>Diſſipated,</hi> and ſo Eſtranged from a <hi>Metallick</hi> Nature, but not <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Calcined.</hi> Therefore every <hi>Calcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is made elſewhere then in the perfect <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> is vain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſeful to our work.</p>
                     <p>Alſo every <hi>Calcination</hi> of <hi>Sol,</hi> in which a <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> without <hi>laying on of Hands,</hi> does not follow, is falſe and vain.</p>
                     <p>Therefore this our <hi>Calcination,</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to be made by <hi>Mercury,</hi> which being joyned to <hi>Gold</hi> (a due <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi> both of Quantity and Quality being obſerved) ſoftens it and takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Solidity and <hi>Incrudates</hi> it; and by its internal Heat, joined with the outward <hi>Heat of Vulcan,</hi> ſtirrs up that Native heat of the <hi>Gold,</hi> which being ſtirred up, acts upon the <hi>Humidity</hi> and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:52222:74"/>
                        <hi>Exſiccates</hi> it into a ſubtile <hi>Powder, Viſcous</hi> and <hi>Black:</hi> And this is the true <hi>Key</hi> of the <hi>Work,</hi> to <hi>Incrudate</hi> the <hi>Mature,</hi> by the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of an <hi>Immature,</hi> being <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crudated,</hi> to <hi>Calcine</hi> it, being <hi>Calcined</hi> to <hi>Diſſolve</hi> it, <hi>Philoſophically</hi> not <hi>Vulgarly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſignes of this our <hi>Calcination</hi> are theſe, firſt, after the Body ſhall be <hi>ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> with <hi>Water,</hi> as ſoon as the <hi>Keeper of the Gates</hi> ſhall ſtir up the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Bath,</hi> the <hi>Water</hi> begins to be Obſcured, or that which was a <hi>ſplendid Compoſition</hi> before, then it viſibly grows <hi>Turgid,</hi> and ſwells, aſcending and deſcending continually, until the whole at laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>viſcous</hi> and <hi>fatt Powder;</hi> in which it appears that the <hi>Humidity</hi> is <hi>conſerved</hi> in this <hi>Operation,</hi> otherwiſe the Labour would be in vain. From thence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is eaſily reſolved into Mineral <hi>Water,</hi> which is the laſt and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Signe, that our <hi>Calcination</hi> has been true and <hi>Philoſophical.</hi> For as ſoon as the heat begins to Operate, the Frigid and <hi>Humid,</hi> being Impatient thereof, goes to the top, from thence it melts
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:52222:74"/>and deſcends, and ſo reduceth it, as much as may be, to its own <hi>Stmilitude:</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this daily untill at laſt the whole be reſolved into Fat, and as it were <hi>Gluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Water:</hi> For ſo our <hi>Operations</hi> are <hi>Concatinated,</hi> that one is the Cauſe and beginning of another, neither can one be had or underſtood without another. But we, that we may inſtruct the Sons of <hi>Art</hi> more fully, and drive away the unworthy, as far as may be from this <hi>Art,</hi> do handle, as it were, divers Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, when there is but one <hi>Recipe,</hi> one <hi>thing,</hi> one <hi>Regimen</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſive Diſpoſition to black, white</hi> and <hi>red,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are we to be underſtood otherwiſe. Wherefore every one that will truly be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> ſhould regard the <hi>Sence,</hi> not the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Writers</hi> in this <hi>Art.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But that we may come to our true <hi>Calcination,</hi> theſe things are to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidered that follow.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſtly,</hi> that thou ſhould get our <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> without which, nothing is done in this <hi>Art:</hi> See then that thou be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in that Common <hi>Mercury,</hi> which
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:52222:75"/>is altogether unuſeful to our <hi>Work,</hi> for if thou Work in it to thy <hi>Dying day,</hi> thou wilt find nothing in it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> thou muſt take Care, that the <hi>Fire</hi> of the <hi>Furnace</hi> be not too In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe, but let it be <hi>clibanically</hi> meaſured, which that thou maiſt fully underſtand, know, that the <hi>Sulphur</hi> which <hi>Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates</hi> not in the <hi>Mercury</hi> or <hi>Water</hi> digeſts the <hi>Matter,</hi> which together with <hi>Azoth</hi> is abundantly ſufficient for thee. Let not therefore, its Internal quality, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the external form, then be not <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous</hi> about the <hi>manner of making the Fire,</hi> only have a care that it be not too Gentle, for then thou wilt eaſily <hi>diſpond</hi> for want of Heat, nor yet let it be over Violent, but of a Moderate degree, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nature of the <hi>Bodies,</hi> and excluſive of Cold: Take theſe things on the other Hand, concerning the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Natural <hi>Fire,</hi> I call that <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> which increaſeth the Work in the End.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> be careful of the quantity, that thou doſt not put ſo much to be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:52222:75"/>
                        <hi>drunk</hi> by <hi>Laton,</hi> that he cannot after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Eate, for if thou ſhalt put on too much, there will be a Sea of trouble, if too little, it will be burnt into <hi>Smoak</hi> be not therefore <hi>Covetous</hi> or <hi>Prodigal,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Extreams,</hi> keep a <hi>Mean.</hi> Therefore, in joining the <hi>Male</hi> with his <hi>Female,</hi> remember that it behoves the Activity of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> to <hi>Exſiccate</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous <hi>Humidity</hi> of <hi>Mercury,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not drownd the active with too much <hi>Crude Sperm,</hi> the <hi>Woman</hi> will alſo deſire to Rule, therefore do not Choak the <hi>Humidity</hi> of thy Stone, with too much <hi>Earth,</hi> but with Diſcretion mix it ſweetly, and according to the <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Nature,</hi> leſt the <hi>Virtue</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> be <hi>diminiſhed;</hi> make therefore an <hi>Amalgama,</hi> not as the <hi>Goldſmith</hi> does, with four or five <hi>Parts</hi> of <hi>Water,</hi> but as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> do, with a double or treble to the laſt, but it is better, to take three to four, then one to two, ſince the ſolution will be better, becauſe the <hi>Cal ination,</hi> will be more <hi>Natural. Ripley</hi> Witneſſeth with me, <q>
                           <hi>That by ;how much the more Earth</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:52222:76"/>leſs Water thou take, ſo much the better ;Solution ſhalt thou make.</hi>
                        </q> In the firſt place therefore, beware that your Land be not overwhelmed with waters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Fire</hi> is hidden in the <hi>Earth,</hi> which will not Operate if there be too much <hi>Humid Superfluity:</hi> whence the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror will be <hi>Incorrigible,</hi> &amp; the work vain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Be careful of the <hi>cloſure</hi> of the <hi>Veſſel,</hi> leſt the <hi>Spirits</hi> ſhould fly out and the <hi>Work</hi> be deſtroyed. Keep there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Veſſel</hi> and its <hi>Ligature,</hi> nor look upon this to be of little moment. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider therefore Man, who as he is <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated</hi> by <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo alſo our <hi>Gold</hi> is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured by <hi>Art</hi> helped by <hi>Nature:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider with how great care. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has ſhut the <hi>VVomb</hi> of a <hi>pregnant woman,</hi> leſt any thing ſhould either get in, or paſs out; otherwiſe the <hi>Foetus</hi> would pariſh. with no leſs Induſtry be thou cautious in <hi>perfecting</hi> this <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical work,</hi> leſt thy Labour be in vain. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> therefore the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> ſaying, <q>
                           <hi>Take theſſel and Fire, ſtrike it with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>, take the Life, this is the Cloſure:</hi>
                        </q>
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:52222:76"/>Hermes alſo ſays, <q>
                           <hi>The Veſſel of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers is their water,and know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the veſſel of Nature is only fit for us in this Art,</hi>
                        </q> 
                        <hi>which diligently is to be ſhut.</hi> For in forming the <hi>Embrio,</hi> there are very great winds, which if they ſhould vaniſh, we are undone; for the error is <hi>Irreparable,</hi> whence the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is moſt certain.</p>
                     <p>The Work in the <hi>Fifth</hi> place is <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> that thou don't diſpond or ſtudy to make the <hi>ſolution</hi> too ſpeedy, but firmly believe, that too much baſt is the greateſt <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it: For the Body to be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> Impertinently <hi>Rubifies,</hi> ſtirring up a Feaver, that is, a <hi>Fire</hi> againſt <hi>Nature,</hi> whence being ſtruck as it were with the <hi>Hammer of Death,</hi> it becomes imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently paſſive from active, and inſtead of <hi>black,</hi> it appears <hi>citrine,</hi> like a wild <hi>Poppy.</hi> But our true <hi>Calcination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves</hi> the <hi>Radical Humidity</hi> in the <hi>Body</hi> to be <hi>diſsolved,</hi> and it is finiſhed in no other colour but <hi>black,</hi> and becomes a <hi>diſcontinuous Calx, unctuous, fatt,</hi> and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:52222:77"/>fit for <hi>fuſion.</hi> Be therefore <hi>Patient,</hi> that thou maiſt obtain thy Deſire, becauſe you will have very much cauſe of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair.</hi> When therefore we ſpeak of our <hi>Operations,</hi> do not think that we perfect them in one or two days, or ſee the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours</hi> or <hi>ſignes</hi> in the firſt hour, No ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; but we have expected much and long, till there was made an Agreement betwixt <hi>contrary qualities,</hi> wherefore <hi>Treveſan</hi> Teaches in his <hi>Practice,</hi> who was a Learned and good man in this <hi>Art,</hi> that <hi>be ſtaid in Priſon,</hi> that is, <hi>ſuſpence</hi> of mind and <hi>Doubt,</hi> fourty days, but that he returned afterwards, and ſaw <hi>Clouds</hi> and <hi>Miſts.</hi> Moreover if thou ſhould put Grain into Good Land, thou ſhalt not look into the <hi>Earth,</hi> by moving it every hour, that you may ſee, whether, and how much it begins to <hi>increaſe,</hi> if you ſhould do this, you could not expect a <hi>ſweet vegetation,</hi> much leſs <hi>Fruit</hi> from thence. So fooliſh and Inſipid are they who as ſoon as ever they have joined the <hi>Diſsolvent</hi> with the <hi>Diſsolvend</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeek ſome <hi>ſignes</hi> of the <hi>Operation,</hi> nor
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:52222:77"/>can ſatisfie themſelves, but they either move or open, or add, or detract ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or at leaſt increaſe the <hi>Fire</hi> to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerate</hi> the <hi>work,</hi> and ſo by this means hinder the <hi>work of Nature;</hi> and therefore do not attain the wiſhed for Ends. Therefore attend to my <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as ſoon as thou haſt prepared the <hi>Matter,</hi> that is, <hi>mature Sulphur yellow,</hi> with his <hi>Crude white Sulphur,</hi> and haſt duely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed them, ſhut them up in a veſſel and let them ſtand without trouble: if thou rightly proceed, within twenty four Hours, thou ſhalt ſee thy <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi> ſwelling, and perhaps ſending forth ſome <hi>Bubbles,</hi> by reaſon of the Heat of thy <hi>Sea water,</hi> ſtriving to excite the <hi>heat</hi> of the Included Matter; but in the firſt <hi>Entrance,</hi> thou ſhalt behold the <hi>variation</hi> of the <hi>colours</hi> ſlowly, (as at leaſt it will ſeem to thee) becauſe then the keeper of the <hi>Gate,</hi> neceſſarily ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many Labours, becauſe whatever is done, he alone then does it, becauſe the <hi>Bath</hi> is not yet prepared, that is, the <hi>Natural heat</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> is not yet
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:52222:78"/>ſtirred up. But when the <hi>Bath</hi> is made hot, our <hi>Houſe-keeper</hi> ſhall ſuſtain but few Labours, and the <hi>operations</hi> will be eaſily to be diſtinguiſhed. Therefore let the Sons of this <hi>Art know</hi> for certain, that the firſt colour that will appear, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>ſi ver colour</hi> of the <hi>Amalgama</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> will not be perfect black, for this colour does not come in a moment, but every day the more the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> is diminiſhed, the more blackneſs will ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervene, until at laſt it be <hi>compleated.</hi> For <hi>blackneſs</hi> is a ſigne of a diſſolved <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> which is not made in one hour, but by little and little, but Inceſſantly: for the <hi>Tincture</hi> proceeding from the <hi>Reins of Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna,</hi> ſhews it ſelf black to the Eyes, but is Extracted inſenſibly, and imperceptibly. Therefore, the coming of Blackneſs and the departure of the <hi>Tincture,</hi> out of the Bowels of the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvend Body,</hi> is the ſame meaſure and <hi>term of time,</hi> becauſe as ſoon as the Tincture is wholly gone out, ſo ſoon the <hi>blackneſs</hi> will be perfect and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. Concerning this, hear what <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:52222:78"/>Puerorum</hi> ſayes, <q>
                           <hi>Firſt, by how much the more thou Decocts, ſo much the more thou ſubtilizeth the Groſs, and blackens the Compound.</hi>
                        </q> And <hi>Bernard Treveſan</hi> ſaith, <q>
                           <hi>The Earth of the reſt beginning to predominate, the blackneſs of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment appears, but does not obtain his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion but by little and little.</hi>
                        </q> To finiſh in a word, there are only four Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple <hi>Colours,</hi> the firſt whereof is <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and that moſt ſlow in coming, and longeſt in duration, which if it were made <hi>perfect</hi> by a <hi>momentary Ingreſs,</hi> the work would be moſt <hi>expeditious,</hi> for it ſhould not periſh more ſlowly then it came, and remain in the top of <hi>blackneſs</hi> for an hour: For there is no <hi>Interſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> in theſe Operations, but it <hi>Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> to the height of one <hi>Degree,</hi> at which it no ſooner arrives, but <hi>Decreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> again, therefore it aſcends ſlowly to <hi>blackneſs,</hi> and deſcends ſlowly from it but there is not a <hi>Moment</hi> in which it doth not aſcend or deſcend, for nothing reſteth but in its End, but <hi>blackneſs</hi> is not the end of our <hi>Stone, ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="140" facs="tcp:52222:79"/>
How then ſhall <hi>blackneſs</hi> appear? to wit even as night comes, for firſt the <hi>Twilight,</hi> at laſt <hi>Dark Night,</hi> and that by <hi>inſenſible Degrees,</hi> every <hi>moment</hi> there being leſs Light in the <hi>Air</hi> then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until at laſt there be no Light at all, then it is <hi>deep Night,</hi> but all this is wont to be within an hour, yet the <hi>Motion</hi> is <hi>Inſenſible:</hi> But our work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it requires a longer time, the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> muſt needs be more <hi>Imperceptible.</hi> Thou therefore that ſeekeſt this, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Example</hi> produced, and thou ſhalt have thy Anſwer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Objection,</hi> But after the firſt <hi>Excitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Matter, the <hi>Tincture</hi> goes out every hour and moment, but the <hi>colour</hi> of the <hi>Tincture</hi> going out, is blackeſt <hi>blackneſs,</hi> therefore after the firſt ſtirring up of the <hi>Matter,</hi> blackeſt <hi>blackneſs</hi> will appear in an hour.</p>
                     <p>We Anſwer, the blackeſt <hi>blackneſs,</hi> is of the <hi>Tincture</hi> gone out, but not of the going out, or if ſo, yet it goes out <hi>Inſenſibly,</hi> but <hi>inſenſible blackneſs,</hi> altho moſt <hi>black,</hi> when it goes into much <hi>white,</hi>
                        <pb n="141" facs="tcp:52222:79"/>will not manifeſt the blackeſt <hi>blackneſs</hi> in the whole <hi>Compound,</hi> but a <hi>whitiſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> but if ſo be the <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> be not <hi>ſubtile</hi> and well <hi>depurated,</hi> even as this <hi>white</hi> is now, then its <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> in its firſt <hi>Egreſs,</hi> is not <hi>compleatly Black,</hi> but it obtains this by a <hi>Putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which is not a bare <hi>Egreſs</hi> of the <hi>Tincture,</hi> but a <hi>Repugnance</hi> and <hi>Reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> from it, which ariſeth between the outgoing <hi>Tincture,</hi> and the <hi>extracting Water,</hi> that is, between <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury.</hi> Concerning this thing hear the ſaying of <hi>Morienus,</hi> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>Our operation is nothing elſe, but an Extracting of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of its Earth, nor that only, but a returning of the Water upon the Earth, until the Earth putreſie.</hi>
                        </q> Therefore the <hi>Tincture</hi> is not altogether black of it ſelf, but moſt white, becauſe by how much the more the <hi>Tincture</hi> goes out, which is the Soul, by ſo much the more the Earth which is the <hi>Body,</hi> is <hi>diſpirited,</hi> and ſo it putrefies and Blackens.</p>
                     <p>How long time then, muſt we expect, before it be perfectly black? In this thing
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:52222:80"/>attend to what <hi>Flammel</hi> ſayes, <q>
                           <hi>The co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour which thou ought firſt to ſee is black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and that not every, but moſt black, and that within the ſpace of Fourty dayes.</hi>
                        </q> Alſo <hi>Ripley</hi> ſayes, <q>
                           <hi>ſuffer the Commixt, and Coequated Natures, to lye together ſix Weeks, which time expect with a ſlow Fire.</hi>
                        </q> VVhen the Colours dye they will ſhow it, for at that time they will Boyl like Liquid <hi>Pitch</hi> and will putrifie. And <hi>Bernard</hi> in his <hi>Parable</hi> ſays, <q>
                           <hi>The King pitting off his ſplendid Robes, gives the Silken ones to</hi> Saturn, <hi>being Cloathed in black, which be retains fourty dayes.</hi>
                        </q> All this underſtand of <hi>blackneſs</hi> in its height, which is plain from the above-repeated words of <hi>Flammel,</hi> but a more remiſs blackneſs, will appear ſooner; ſo the <hi>Scala Philoſophorum</hi> ſayes, <q>
                           <hi>within ſixteen dayes in the degree of Putrefaction, an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Fire being kept, the matter will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually Covered with blackneſs.</hi>
                        </q> And this either later or ſooner, according to the <hi>Ingenuity</hi> of the Operator, in <hi>Adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the Matters.</p>
                     <p>But whether will intermedial Colours
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:52222:80"/>appear, in a Progreſs from white to black, as in the Progreſs from black to white? It ſeems ſo, becauſe there is no <hi>tranſition</hi> from one extream to another, unleſs by Mediums: And we anſwer that they ſo appear, altho indeed confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, and ſome in ſome Works will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in a Progreſs to the height of black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which perhaps will not appear in another, becauſe they are only acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Colours:</hi> but not altogether the ſame, betwixt the firſt Whiteneſs and Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are between this, and ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Whiteneſs, becauſe there is not the ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Matter;</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer the thick <hi>Terreſtrial Matter</hi> was to be <hi>burned</hi> and <hi>purified,</hi> but in this work the <hi>Matter</hi> is more <hi>Spiritual</hi> and pure; therefore in a pure or <hi>Depurated Subject,</hi> in a <hi>Progreſs</hi> from the <hi>extremity</hi> of <hi>black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to the <hi>extremity</hi> of <hi>Whiteneſs,</hi> the Intermedial Colours will be much more clear and admirable, then thoſe which appeared in an Earthly Subject. But in both progreſſes they will appear, in the former <hi>tranſition,</hi> between the Extreams,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:52222:81"/>Obſcurer, fewer and fouler; in the Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more, more ſhining and splendid, witneſs the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>After the heighth of Blackneſs, before Whiteneſs, in the hour of Conjunction great Miracles will appear: For whatever Colours could be thought on in the whole World then will be conſpicuous.</hi>
                        </q> And <hi>Riply</hi> ſayes, <q>
                           <hi>In our work colours will appear, then which never more fair appeared.</hi>
                        </q> Alſo before perfect Blackneſs the intermedial Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours will ſhow themſelves, witneſs the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> who Painting the Colours of the Dragons, ſaith <q>
                           <hi>They are black, Yellow and Azure,</hi>
                        </q> and theſe intermedial Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours ſays he, denote that thy Confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not yet perfectly putrefied. In a Word, the various Colours in Dying, will appear more obſcure, but thin and few, and this before black Night <hi>obnubilate</hi> the whole <hi>Horizon.</hi> But in riſing again, very many and very Splendid ones will ariſe, becauſe the Body now begins to be glorified, and the Light to predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate over the Darkneſs and this in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purated, and ſpiritual Subject.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="145" facs="tcp:52222:81"/>
But in what order will theſe foreſaid Colours appear? This truly cannot be determined, becauſe they are varied ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways, but the better the juice of the Water of Life ſhall be, the better the Signs ſhall appear. The order of the four Principle Colours is deſcribed by all, but no one can determine the order of the accidental ones, let it ſuffice thee if within fourty dayes, thou haſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat blackneſs, don't mind other things much, but it is good to attend, for black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is firſt Eſpecially deſirable, and tho others appear, unleſs thou ſeeſt this without doubt thou haſt erred, But as I ſaid, other Colours are not to be Diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, except the Venerial, or imperfect Red, which if it appear before blackneſs, is to be ſuſpected, eſpecially when the ſiccity of the Compound, and Diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of the parts accompany it, I ſay this Precipitation is a fatal Index to the Operator of his loſt time.</p>
                     <p>This ſame thing the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſaying, <q>
                           <hi>A vehement Fire hinders Conjunction, and tinges white, with the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:52222:82"/>colour of the wild Poppy.</hi>
                        </q> And <hi>Flammel</hi> in his <hi>Hierogliphical</hi> Figures, ſayes, <hi>unleſs</hi> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>thou ſhalt behold, the blackeſt black of black whatever other colour thou ſeeſt, thou art in the way of Error: But eſpecially a reddiſh colour is to be ſuſpected, for if thou ſeeſt that, thou haſt burned, or art burning the lively virtue of the Stone.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>But I muſt ſtay no longer in theſe things, ſince one Water does all this, ſo that the Internal Compound, continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ruled, with External heat; neither is there any thing, in the whole Work more Wonderful, then this our Water. which I have fully Deſcribed above, to which place I ſend thee back.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Concerning Solution.</head>
                     <p>And the Diſſolution of our <hi>Stone,</hi> is the Reduction of it into its firſt matter, the Manifeſtation of the Humid, and the Extraction of Natures from their <hi>Profundity,</hi> which is finiſhed by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a Mineral Water.</p>
                     <p>This Operation is of no Light Work or Moment, for how hard it is, thoſe that have toiled in it can atteſt.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:82"/>
                  <p>THE FOUNTAIN OF Chymical Philoſophy</p>
                  <p>Written in Latine By EYRENAEUS PHILALETHES</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="3" type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:83"/>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:52222:83"/>
                  <head>TRACT The THIRD.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Fountain of Chymical Philoſophy.</head>
                  <p>I Will divide the whole of the <hi>Art</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe parts: The firſt ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain things ſubſtantially and eſſentially Conſtituting the Work: The ſecond the diſpoſition of them: The things Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially Coſtituting the <hi>Stone,</hi> are a <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> or Mature <hi>Sulphur,</hi> or <hi>red Braſs</hi> and Water, or Immature <hi>Mercury,</hi> or white <hi>Braſs,</hi> to which a Veſſel is added, a Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace and Triple Fire. The Diſpoſition of theſe things, Conſiders the Weight and the Regimen. The <hi>Pondus</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, the <hi>Regimen</hi> twofold: Thoſe things which perfect theſe Operations,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:52222:84"/>are <hi>Calcination, Diſſolution, Separation, Conjunction, Putrefaction, Diſtillation, Coagulation, Sublimation, Fixation,</hi> and <hi>Exaltation,</hi> of which the two firſt, are made eſpecially by a Temperate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comburent and altering <hi>Ignition</hi> of the Fire; heating the <hi>Kings bath</hi> and Changing him firſt into a ſubtile <hi>viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous</hi> Earth, Diſcontinued black and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, then into <hi>Mineral Water,</hi> diverſly coloured, and this is called a Fire againſt Nature. The three Operations which follow are made from the Combining of the firſt and third Fire, to wit, of the Natural and Contra-natural, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo joyned together, make an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fire, by Circulating the Matter eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and ſeparating the more ſubtile from the Thick, till all be of the ſame Temperament, and then Conjoyning the things ſeparated, impregnating them, and ſo putrefying them.</p>
                  <p>The five laſt Operations are made by the Fire of Nature, daily increaſing and Predominating, which firſt Circumacts the putrefied Matter daily and cleanſeth
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:52222:84"/>it from Filth, by an often aſcenſion, and deſcenſion, which therefore is called Diſtillation, Volatization, Ablution, Mundification, Cohobation Imbibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Cibation, Humectation of the Earth, and this is done ſo long by the heat, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Siccity begins to Coagulate, which is called Inſpiſſation, which by a longer Concoction, or Sublimation, brings a fixity, whoſe Bound is Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: This is not the change of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior place, for the Superior, but of the moſt vile thing, to make the moſt Noble.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are all our Opperations and ſucceſſive Diſpoſitions, which by ſome are called ſo many Regimens, which name if any one had rather impoſe, he may: however know there is only a double fire, Natural and againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which the Latter Acts firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the other is not brought to light, but by this, and Putrefaction muſt go before Regeneration; and when theſe two fight with one another, they make an Unnatural fire, and from this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:52222:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:52222:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:52222:86"/>riſes Putrefaction: and after this is a Glorious Regeneration in which the <hi>Sulphur</hi> and Water become one thing, and alſo receive a Congealation, from no fire but a Natural.</p>
                  <p>Therefore our Body which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Called <hi>Terra Lemnia,</hi> perfects the whole work: but it can in no wiſe be moiſtened but in its own Water, which Water is truely <hi>Pluvial,</hi> not ſuch as the common people knows to get, but ours, which none ever ſaw, but a true <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> believe me for I ſpeak the truth, Fools know how to Extract many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to wit wetting the hands, but our Water is the Life of all things, about which thou muſt take pains, then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sol,</hi> nor <hi>Luna</hi> will be wanting to ſupply thee with Riches.</p>
                  <p>But I will tell thee, and that faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what kind of Water this is, it is the Water of <hi>Salt Petre,</hi> which is known as <hi>Mercury,</hi> but in the heart a pure infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fire: but have a care thou be not deceived by <hi>Quickſilver,</hi> but underſtand that <hi>Mercury,</hi> which the returning Sun
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:52222:86"/>cefuſeth every where in the Month of <hi>March.</hi> Gather thou it in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> becauſe then ſurely it is found ripe, and the moſt precious Treaſure in the whole World.</p>
                  <p>But that I may deſcribe our <hi>Mercury</hi> to thee, our Rain Water ſo that thou maiſt find it, know that it is before the eyes of he whole World, that yet are Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant thereof, or at leaſt, does take the vulgar for it, and <hi>deturpates</hi> it with various Tortures, but neglects our true <hi>Mercury</hi> in its ſeaſon, therefore it never perfects our <hi>Magiſtery.</hi> For the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Alehymiſts</hi> does look upon it with a blew look; whence it comes to paſs, that they ſcorn it: but it aſtoniſheth the Sons of Learning with its Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and is greatly accounted of by them, therefore it is a vile thing, and yet the moſt precious, which no one ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned without a great judgement of God.</p>
                  <p>But thou when thou ſeeſt it don't deſpiſe it becauſe it will appear very durty, and if thou therefore diſpiſe it,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:52222:87"/>thou ſhalt be deprived of the <hi>Magiſtery,</hi> but if thou doſt greatly eſteem this contemptible thing, then indeed it ſhall ſeem Glorious, having changed its coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: For our <hi>Water</hi> is a moſt clean Virgin, and is loved by many, but ſhe meets all her Wooers, Cloathed in ſordid Garments, that by this means ſhe may diſtinguiſh <hi>Philoſophers</hi> from Fools, for whoſoever ſhall behold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but externally, will ſcorn him as unworthy of ſuch a Secret, ſince <hi>Whores</hi> ſhew themſelves to their <hi>Woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> dreſt in ſplendid Garments; but this chaſt and moſt precious <hi>Maid,</hi> ſeems outwardly foul, but is inwardly fair, which indeed cheats many Fools. But whatſoever Mental man, can ſee the Spirit which lyes hid, under the patent <hi>body</hi> will not eſteem her little, alſo our Virgin will look upon him as a Friend, and putting off her filthineſs, will ſhine moſt amiable, whom then none but a fool but muſt admire and love, for ſhe will beſtow upon him infinite Riches, and perfect health. Therefore honour ye
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:52222:87"/>this Female, the <hi>Siſter</hi> and <hi>Wife</hi> of our <hi>King,</hi> to whom if you be aſſiſtant in putting off her dreggs, ſhe will get moſt ſplendid Garments for her ſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow infinite Riches upon thee. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this our <hi>Queen</hi> is clean above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whom if you ſhall behold, you will think you look upon a certain Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Body, for the is indeed the Heaven or the fifth Eſſence of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> whoſe brightneſs you cannot imagine, unleſs you ſee it: believe me for I have ſeen her Snowy Splendor with my Eyes, touched with my hands, then which nothing can be thought fairer. Our Water is then truly <hi>Pontick, Serene, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaline,</hi> pure and clean, which is not ſo in its Nature as we make it by our Art; and its our Sea, our hidden Fountain, out of which our <hi>Gold</hi> naturally is Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, when yet it prefers its ſelf to <hi>Gold,</hi> and conquers it, and in the hour of its Nativity, Gold is joyned with it, and is waſhed in it, and both increaſeth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into a Stout <hi>Hero,</hi> which neither <hi>Coeſar</hi> nor the <hi>Pope</hi> can buy with Money.
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:52222:88"/>Therefore with all thy ſtrength get this Water, of which an Ounce is worth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Thouſand Pound, becauſe by this alone, without any other Labour, except the Addition of a perfect clean, pure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, thou maiſt perfect our moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Stone,</hi> to which no Treaſure in the World can be equaled.</p>
                  <p>But there is need of profound Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation before thou canſt conceive our <hi>Sea,</hi> to wit its <hi>Flux</hi> and <hi>Reflux:</hi> But if thou be diligent, by the help of God, thou ſhah obtain thy defire; I for my part, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I knew the Field in general, where this our Secret Fountain did Purl, yet I did not learn to get it out, till after a year and a half, giving my ſelf, to dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtudy and profound Contemplations, becauſe the Fiery Furnace of the wiſe men lay hid from me long: but after I knew this, and how it was fitted to its proper Verel, after a few dayes I beheld the admirable Brightneſs of our Water, which being ſeen I could not but be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, for as in the Practice, ſo it is in the Theory, and on the contrary: for
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:52222:88"/>he that exactly knows the Magiſtery of this Water, no Words or Secrets of the <hi>Philoſophers;</hi> Sayings, Writings or Enig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, will be concealed from him; ſo whoſoever hath once made up our Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nothing remains to be done, but to caſt in a clean Body in a juſt quantity, ſhut the Veſſel and ſo let it ſtand, till the Complement of the Work. But we have another twofold <hi>Fire,</hi> which thou ſhalt eaſily know, as ſoon as thou haſt Learned this firſt: but that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Water, in which believe me, the whole ſecret Conſiſts, which Water altho it be one, yet is not ſimple but Compound, to wit of the Veſſel and <hi>Fire</hi> of Philoſophers to which a third is added, namely the Bond. When therefore we ſpeak of our Veſſel, underſtand our Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when of the <hi>Fire,</hi> in like manner underſtand Water and when we Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the <hi>Furnace</hi> we would have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Diverſe, or divided from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Therefore the Veſſel is one, the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace one, the Fire one, and all theſe are one to wit Water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:52222:89"/>
Therefore the fire Digeſteth, the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel Whiteneth, and Penetrates, and the <hi>Furnace</hi> or <hi>Bond</hi> Encompaſſeth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all, and the <hi>Fire</hi> is <hi>Mercury,</hi> the Veſſel alſo <hi>Mercury,</hi> laſtly the ſame <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi> is <hi>Mercury,</hi> and Note well, there is no fire in the whole work but <hi>Mercury,</hi> when notwithſtanding, the fire is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, and the water manifold: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well fire as water is diverſified by their virtue, in the work; as in Number, ſo they agree in one and the ſame Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to wit <hi>Mercury,</hi> therefore our <hi>Fire</hi> is Living, our <hi>Water</hi> Living, our <hi>Veſſel</hi> Living, our <hi>Furnace</hi> Living, and all theſe are one.</p>
                  <p>Know alſo deareſt! that there is only one thing in the whole world, in the which this our <hi>Mercury</hi> is to be found, it is of a like Eſſence with <hi>Gold,</hi> unlike in Subſtance, by converting the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereof, thou ſhalt find what thou ſeekeſt. Joyn the Heaven with the Earth, upon a Fire of friendſhip, and in the midſt of the Firmament, thou ſhalt ſee <hi>Hermes</hi> his <hi>bird.</hi> Do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:52222:89"/>the Natures, but divide them and joyn them again, and thou ſhalt Reign in <hi>Honour</hi> all thy Life; hear therefore this great <hi>Secret,</hi> in the <hi>Southern Coaſt</hi> is found a very high <hi>Mountain,</hi> very near to the <hi>Sun,</hi> which is one of the <hi>ſeven,</hi> and higheſt but one: This Mountain of which we now ſpeak is of a very hot temperature, becauſe it is not far from the <hi>Sun,</hi> and in this Mountain a <hi>Vapour</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> is ſhut up, which is highly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our Work; but it does not aſcend unleſs it be enlivened, neither is enlivened unleſs the <hi>Earth</hi> be digged Knee deep in the top of the Mountain, but if this be done, the Spirit or thin <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation aſcends,</hi> which being <hi>congealed</hi> by the <hi>Air,</hi> drop by drop, runs into moſt clear <hi>Water,</hi> warm like a <hi>Bath,</hi> which is preſently gathered, for it is the true <hi>Caduce of Mercury,</hi> with which he works Wonders; this is our <hi>Water,</hi> our <hi>Fire,</hi> our <hi>Furnate</hi> and it is our <hi>Mercury,</hi> and not the <hi>Vulgars;</hi> but the hot and humid Liquor of the moſt pure Salt,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:52222:90"/>which we name <hi>Mercury;</hi> becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with the <hi>Sun,</hi> it's immature and Frigid. Verily I ſay unto thee, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Almighty</hi> had Created this <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> the <hi>Tranſmutation of Metals</hi> were impoſſible, becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> does not <hi>tinge</hi> unleſs it be <hi>tinged.</hi> But he is not <hi>tinged</hi> but by this our <hi>Water</hi> alone. O this bleſſed <hi>Humidity!</hi> which is the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical</hi> Heaven, whence wiſe men have drawn their Ineſtimable <hi>Dainties!</hi> O per manent <hi>Water! Diſſolving</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <hi>Sol,</hi> our <hi>Nitre</hi> and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Salt Petre!</hi> whoſe price is Ineſtimable yet it is little eſteemed. Therefore the thing is <hi>vile</hi> and yet very <hi>Precious,</hi> whom our <hi>Sol</hi> Loves as his only <hi>Bride,</hi> whoſe <hi>virtue</hi> if the vulgar knew, they would not ſell a <hi>drahm</hi> for a Thouſand <hi>Ounces</hi> of <hi>Silver;</hi> for it is moſt precious <hi>Gold</hi> Lively and <hi>penetrating,</hi> therefore it turns the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> into a meer <hi>Spirit,</hi> and is joined in <hi>Marriage,</hi> as the <hi>Woman</hi> to the <hi>Husband,</hi> whoſe fairneſs <hi>Sol</hi> admires, and rejoices in her, and for Love kills
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:52222:90"/>his own <hi>Wife,</hi> and ſhe moved with Love makes him alive, and is <hi>impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated</hi> by him, Conceives and grows big, alſo brings forth a Son a moſt <hi>ſerene King.</hi> O happy they who can go to this Fountain of our <hi>Water!</hi> for if they ſhall Drink of it, and ſhall Eat afterwards a little piece of fat Fleſh, they ſhall reign as Princes all their Life on the Earth. Therefore the whole <hi>ſecret</hi> of our <hi>Work</hi> conſiſts in knowing this our Sea, which who ever is Ignorant of, he hath long ago Deſtined his Money to perdition, if he does ſpend any about this Work. For our <hi>Ocean</hi> draws its Original, from one Mountain and that a very high one, as I have ſaid above. But if aſcending to the Top thou digg Knee Deep, a Certain <hi>Exhalation</hi> or <hi>white fume</hi> will aſcend, which will perfect the whole <hi>Magiſtery,</hi> but there remains another Secret, which thou art obliged not to be ignorant of, that thou maiſt obtain thy deſire, to wit, how thou muſt <hi>digg</hi> in the <hi>Mountain,</hi> ſince that the Earth in the Superfice of the <hi>Mountain,</hi> is to be cut with no Blow, for
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:52222:91"/>is his Dryneſs, that it is <hi>Concreted</hi> by the means of <hi>Heat,</hi> into a Subſtance harder then <hi>Flint.</hi> Attend therefore to this Secret, in <hi>Saturnine</hi> places is found a certain <hi>Herb</hi> called <hi>Satarnia,</hi> whoſe branches appear dry, but Juice abounds in the Root, gather this Herb together with the Root and carry it with thee, until thou come to the foot of the <hi>Mountain,</hi> under which by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> thou ſhalt digg and Bury the Herb, which preſently goes through the pores of the Mountain, by looſing the Earth thereof, then at length, Clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Top, thou ſhalt eaſily Bore Knee deep, and ſhalt pour ſo much Fat and dry Water, that deſcending to the Bottom of the Mountain it may wet the Herb there laid, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently being made moiſt, together with the Water, aſcends like ſmoak, and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with it the Spirit of the Mountain, carrying it up with it, which Spirit is a fiery Virtue, mingling it ſelf with the water, and inhabiting therein, and it
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:52222:91"/>is the Water into which thou haſt caſt thy Bond, or the <hi>Veſſel</hi> or <hi>Furnace;</hi> the <hi>ſpirit of Saturnia</hi> is a whitening <hi>fume,</hi> and the vapour of the Mountain is fire, and all theſe are fire, ſo thou haſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnia</hi> a <hi>Vegetable, Royal</hi> and <hi>Mineral Herb,</hi> of which with fat Fleſh is made ſuch a <hi>Broth,</hi> to which no Dainties in the World may be Compared. Now thou haſt the whole <hi>ſecret</hi> of our <hi>Water,</hi> deſcribed under an <hi>enigmatical Diſcourſe,</hi> yet not ſo <hi>abſcurely</hi> but thou maiſt Eaſily if thou be diligent and Learned, by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations</hi> and <hi>Experiments</hi> perfect the <hi>Work.</hi> For all theſe are the true Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial <hi>Principles</hi> of our <hi>Stone,</hi> beſides which, nothing can or ought to enter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Work:</hi> to wit, the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which is the <hi>Bath</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> &amp; know that our <hi>Water</hi> is a <hi>Veſſel,</hi> as our <hi>King</hi> is Contained in it; and a Furnace as our <hi>Fire</hi> is included in it; and our <hi>Fire,</hi> as the <hi>Virtue</hi> or Spirit of the <hi>Mountain</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits in it; and the <hi>Female,</hi> as it contains the <hi>Vapour</hi> of <hi>Vegetable Saturnia,</hi> which
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:52222:92"/>is very friendly to <hi>Sol;</hi> and <hi>Penetrates, Whitens</hi> and <hi>Molifies</hi> him and makes him to caſt out <hi>Sperm;</hi> then the <hi>Fiery Virtue</hi> which is ſhut up in the <hi>Water</hi> begins to work upon our <hi>Body</hi> ſo <hi>reduced,</hi> by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting it and Mortifying, by burning and Putrefying, or rather exciting to theſe things until the innate heat of <hi>Sol,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from power into Act, which <hi>deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, Coagulates, Fixeth</hi> and <hi>Tingeth:</hi> and therefore our <hi>Stone</hi> is called the <hi>world</hi> becauſe it contains both the <hi>Agent</hi> and <hi>Patient</hi> in it. It is the moving and the moved, Active and Paſſive, Fixt and Volatile, Mature and Crude, one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>ſuccours</hi> the other, and the one is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the other, becauſe both is <hi>Homegeneous</hi> in its ſelf. For <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> are the ſame in <hi>Water</hi> and in a <hi>Body,</hi> in <hi>Identity</hi> of the <hi>Genus,</hi> and only are diverſifyed by <hi>Decoction.</hi> Keep this <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi> Therefore we do not to that end, order <hi>Crude</hi> and <hi>Volatile Mercury,</hi> to be mingled with <hi>Mature</hi> and <hi>fixt Sulphur,</hi> that we might affirm that <hi>Sulphur</hi> is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:52222:92"/>in one and the other, and the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> different alſo; For where would then the <hi>Homogeneity,</hi> of <hi>Metals</hi> be, which we affirm in our <hi>Stone,</hi> but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we mix theſe two Species's, that we by our <hi>Art,</hi> might Perfect <hi>Gold,</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Degrees more, in a far ſhorter ſpace, than <hi>Nature</hi> has formed <hi>ſimple Gold</hi> in the <hi>Mines.</hi> For <hi>Nature</hi> from only <hi>Crude, Humid,</hi> and <hi>Frigid Mercury,</hi> without any Addition, Generates <hi>Gold</hi> by a long <hi>Decoction,</hi> under the Earth: But Art to contract the work, throws in <hi>Mature</hi> and <hi>fixed Sulphur</hi> to <hi>Mercury</hi> made moſt pure by <hi>Art.</hi> and ſo <hi>Extracts</hi> the moſt <hi>digeſted</hi> virtue of <hi>Sulphur by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> which <hi>Sulphureal Virtue,</hi> ſtrongly Changes and perfects <hi>Mercury</hi> into a Compleat <hi>Elixir.</hi> Obſerve therefore, the <hi>Work</hi> and the <hi>Proceſs</hi> thereof, whence thou ſhalt underſtand the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the wonderful Abreviation of the <hi>Work, Gold</hi> is a <hi>Body</hi> hot and dry, <hi>Luna Gold</hi> &amp; <hi>moist, Mercury</hi> the Medium of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying</hi> the <hi>Tinctures:</hi> The <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Sol</hi> is
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:52222:93"/>moſt digeſted, of <hi>Luna imperfect</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature; Mercury</hi> the Bond, by which theſe two Contraries are United. Join <hi>Luna</hi> to <hi>Mercury,</hi> with a due and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>Ignition,</hi> and mingle them ſo, that <hi>Luna</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> may become one <hi>Mercury,</hi> retaining the <hi>fire</hi> in it ſelf, and all the <hi>feces</hi> and <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> will fall from <hi>Mercury,</hi> and he ſhall become clear, as the <hi>tear</hi> of the <hi>Eye,</hi> altho not <hi>Diaphonous,</hi> then laſtly mingle this <hi>Mercury</hi> with <hi>Gold,</hi> in which is <hi>Luna</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> and then the hot and Dry will love the <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt,</hi> and will lye down together in one bed, that is in the <hi>Fire of friendſhip,</hi> and the <hi>Man</hi> will be diſſolved upon the <hi>Woman,</hi> and the <hi>woman</hi> will be <hi>Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated</hi> upon the <hi>Man,</hi> and then the Spirit and the Body will be one by Commixti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Go on afterwards with that foot thou haſt begun, and ſo often Reiterate the <hi>Heaven</hi> upon its <hi>Eearth,</hi> until the <hi>Spirit</hi> put on the <hi>Body,</hi> and both be fixt together. For then our <hi>Stone</hi> is perfect, and indued with Regal <hi>Virtue,</hi> the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:52222:93"/>which no price can Buy. For <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> is the water of all <hi>Metals,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>decocted</hi> in it: And even as ſimple wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which in its own <hi>Nature</hi> is cold and moiſt, which notwithſtanding if it be mixt in <hi>decoction</hi> with any <hi>Vegetable,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives and puts on other Qualities of the thing mixt with it, whoſe force and ſpirit or life, which reſides in the water, goes out by <hi>Decoction</hi> into the <hi>water,</hi> and the <hi>water Convertibly,</hi> receives its <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> Yet the thick and <hi>Corporeal Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> part of the <hi>ſubſtance decocted,</hi> is not that <hi>ſpirit</hi> that Changes the quality of the <hi>water,</hi> but is ſeparable from the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> after <hi>decoction.</hi> In like manner we muſt underſtand of <hi>Argent Vive,</hi> with its <hi>Species's</hi> yet differently, for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Metal</hi> or <hi>Mineral</hi> ſhall be ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with <hi>Mercury,</hi> as to be mixt <hi>per mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima,</hi> and <hi>decocted with it,</hi> that <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> according to the <hi>Species</hi> of the <hi>Metal</hi> ſo joined, puts on other Qualities, and will caſt off his own Dreggs. Therefore <hi>Metallick and Mineral ſpecies's</hi> are <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately,</hi>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:52222:94"/>and <hi>ſubalternately</hi> to be <hi>deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> in it, and it is their <hi>water,</hi> into which <hi>Mineral ſpirits</hi> are emitted, by <hi>Decoction,</hi> and do alter it no other ways then <hi>Vegetables decocted</hi> in their ſimple water. Yet a <hi>double difference</hi> is to be noted, between the foreſaid <hi>Decoctions,</hi> firſt that <hi>water</hi> is not fixt with the <hi>Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables,</hi> as <hi>Mercury</hi> with <hi>Metals,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe are of a ſtronger Compoſition than thoſe. The Second, that in the <hi>Decoction of Vegetables</hi> or <hi>Animals,</hi> the <hi>water</hi> being a <hi>Diaphanous</hi> Humor, not only receives new Virtue and <hi>Qualities,</hi> but alſo a different Colour to what it had. But it is not ſo in <hi>Mercury</hi> for its Nature is altered, but not its Colour nor form of <hi>Flux:</hi> but the colour of a diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Metal</hi> lyes under the form of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Argent vive,</hi> and by its virtue does not appear. Therefore <hi>Mercury</hi> firſt acteth up a <hi>Metal</hi> by diſſolving it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the <hi>Metal</hi> Acts upon <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> by <hi>Coagulating</hi> it, and as in Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the form and colour of the <hi>Metal</hi>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:52222:94"/>lay under the form and colour of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſo alſo in <hi>Coagulation</hi> the form and Colour of <hi>Mercury</hi> is hid under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and form of the <hi>Metal,</hi> ſo neither the Qualities of the <hi>Metal</hi> in diſſolution hinders the <hi>Flux</hi> of <hi>Mercury,</hi> nor the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Coagulation,</hi> hinder the <hi>fixity</hi> of the <hi>Metal.</hi> Doſt thou not ſee here a certain wonderful Agreement: betwixt <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Metals,</hi> for they Love like <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Son, Siſter</hi> and <hi>Brother, Male</hi> and <hi>Female,</hi> therefore their <hi>Bodies</hi> are made better by <hi>Water</hi> for the Generation of all things is by <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and they take in it, and by it, a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>ſubtilty,</hi> that is a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>volatile Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Water</hi> in like manner is amended by the Bodies, and is retained &amp; puts on a Corporeal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; ſo the whole compound is <hi>matured</hi> together, when the <hi>Agents</hi> become <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi> and on the contrary. But the reaſon that the Colour of <hi>Mercury</hi> is not changed in <hi>Decoction</hi> by the Body Diſſolved, is this, that the <hi>Earth</hi> and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:52222:95"/>
                     <hi>Water</hi> are <hi>Homogeneous</hi> in <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ſo temperate that neither can be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the other, and they are ſo ſtrongly Commixt, that in ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a <hi>tenuity</hi> of <hi>matter,</hi> there is ſuch great <hi>denſity</hi> of <hi>Substance,</hi> as to hide the Colours, whence if any proportion of <hi>Mercury</hi> be ſpoiled, either <hi>deſtructively</hi> by <hi>deturpating</hi> things or <hi>Generatively</hi> with a <hi>Body</hi> Appropriated to its ſelf, it will manifeſt the <hi>colour</hi> that is thrown into the <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> But there are <hi>Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of <hi>Mercury</hi> in reſpect both of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> in reſpect of the ſecond it flows and is <hi>Liquid,</hi> in reſpect of the firſt it <hi>wets nothing</hi> that it touches, but that which is of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of its <hi>Nature.</hi> From what hath been ſaid, all <hi>Errors</hi> of <hi>Operators</hi> in <hi>Mercury</hi> are detected. For ſome Obſtruct or Divide its <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneity,</hi> by drying it with various <hi>ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> others Spoiling and Diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionating the <hi>Earth,</hi> to bring in a <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parency.</hi> As many as do this, do nothing but a <hi>Sophiſtical work.</hi> For <hi>Mercury</hi> is
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:52222:95"/>
                     <hi>Sperm</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> which <hi>Nature</hi> with much <hi>ſagacity</hi> hath formed in the <hi>Veins</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> for <hi>Metal;</hi> Neither is any thing wanting to it but <hi>pure Digeſtion,</hi> but it is not Digeſted unleſs by <hi>pare me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallick incomburent ſulphur,</hi> which indeed it hath in its <hi>Center,</hi> by which Nature would form <hi>Gold</hi> in a long time; but it is altogether unknown to man how he ſhould make this by his <hi>Art.</hi> For altho <hi>Gold</hi> might be made of <hi>Mercury</hi> alone without any addition, yet it would not be perfected but by long time and great coſt, which would be fooliſh to undergo in making <hi>ſimple Gold.</hi> Therefore <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> is the only thing in the world which <hi>Nature</hi> has perfected, that is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to <hi>Mercury.</hi> This therefore is mixt <hi>Radically</hi> with it, and by this <hi>Mercury</hi> is <hi>decocted,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Repugnance</hi> of <hi>Qualities</hi> putrefies it, and ſo by <hi>Regeneration</hi> it riſes again, not <hi>Gold</hi> ſuch as is had in <hi>Mines,</hi> but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Penetrative</hi> and <hi>tinging,</hi> in ſo much that it eaſily enters all Imperfect
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:52222:96"/>
                     <hi>Metals,</hi> when caſt upon them, which in a very ſhort time, it Digeſteth to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natical</hi> proportion of <hi>Gold,</hi> and the dregs being caſt off Reſtores them to perfect Health. Thou ſeeſt therefore that <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> is by no means to be <hi>Diſproportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> from its own <hi>Nature,</hi> but to be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured</hi> and that not by it ſelt without any addition, and yet without any outward addition, but a <hi>Radical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of a clean <hi>Body</hi> with it <hi>per minima,</hi> which is done by our ſecret Conjunction. Yet ſee you be not deceived, for this <hi>Conjunction</hi> is not made by <hi>manual operation,</hi> but only by a Natural, man not only not help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but alſo not well underſtanding its Cauſe, therefore this is called a Divine Work. Fools can confound the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> with <hi>Mercury,</hi> and then they call it <hi>animated Gold,</hi> but they find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it. For altho theſe two ſhould remain together a Thouſand Years, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs they would afterwards recede one from the other in their own proper <hi>Nature.</hi> Therefore the Conjunction was not <hi>alterative</hi> but only a <hi>Confuſion</hi> of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:52222:96"/>two between themſelves. But in out Operation, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Sol</hi> Infuſeth its ſelf into the <hi>ſpirit of Mercury,</hi> ſo that they never depart the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afterwards, even as <hi>water</hi> doth not, being mixt with <hi>water.</hi> Therefore in this <hi>Operation</hi> the greateſt nay the whole ſecret of the <hi>Art</hi> lyes hid. Attend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou <hi>Son of Learning</hi> and ſee wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that thou doſt not err here. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Body of <hi>Sol</hi> will never be join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Mercury</hi> inwardly, unleſs <hi>Luna</hi> mediating, or an imperfect Body and <hi>Fire;</hi> and this <hi>Luna</hi> is the <hi>Juice</hi> of the <hi>water of Life,</hi> which lyes hid in <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which is ſharpened by the fire, and is a <hi>ſpirit</hi> entring a <hi>Body,</hi> and altring it and Compelling it to retain its Soul. Now therefore thou ſeeſt of what <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> we have hitherto ſpoken, not <hi>vulgar</hi> but <hi>pluvial;</hi> which properly is not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mercury,</hi> but <hi>Mercurial water;</hi> for the <hi>Mercury</hi> of the <hi>vulgar</hi> is <hi>water,</hi> but a <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>fiery virtue</hi> is wanting to it, ſupply if thou canſt that which is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all thy <hi>Art,</hi> then it will no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:52222:97"/>be <hi>Mercury</hi> of the <hi>vulgar,</hi> but like to ours. But if thou canſt not do this let that <hi>Mercury</hi> alone, for thou canſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but loſs from it. Behold now God is my witneſs, I have told the whole <hi>matter,</hi> which if thou art wiſe thou canſt not be ignorant of. For vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar <hi>Mercury</hi> has ſeduced more, then any thing elſe, for the Workers herein have found nothing, becauſe they did not know our <hi>Mercury.</hi> But to return to Conjunction, which believe me is the whole Secret of the <hi>Art,</hi> for the <hi>Earth</hi> is not united inſeparably with the <hi>water,</hi> but <hi>water</hi> adheres ſtrongly to <hi>water,</hi> hence it follows, that this <hi>laudable Conjunction</hi> is not <hi>celebrated</hi> till after <hi>Diſſolution;</hi> attend thou therefore to <hi>ſolution,</hi> &amp; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will joyn together, and this <hi>Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> is made in <hi>Mercury</hi> by the help of included <hi>Luna,</hi> and <hi>Fire.</hi> For <hi>Luna</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrates and <hi>Albifies,</hi> and the fire morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and Triturates, but the Water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes both theſe Virtues, according to the ſaying of the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>The Fire which I will ſhew thee is water.</hi> And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:52222:97"/>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs Bodies be ſubtilized by Fire and water, nothing is done in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</hi>
                     </q> O Bleſſed <hi>Mercury</hi> of ours, which frees us from thoſe many La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours which <hi>Sophiſters</hi> endure! for they make many Operations with their hands, and profit nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not the true Courſe of <hi>Nature.</hi> But we do nothing, but leave all things to be done by our <hi>Mercury,</hi> which proceeds in a better <hi>Method,</hi> according to its Natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, then any man could invent: for he is conſtrained by the neceſſity of his End, wherefore he never miſſes the right way if he be not hindred.</p>
                  <p>But there are ſome <hi>Sophiſtical</hi> Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, who take <hi>Gold</hi> and put it to <hi>Mercury,</hi> then ſhut them in a Glaſs and ſet them over the <hi>Fire,</hi> expecting ſome notable thing from thence: But ſince they caſt fat and good <hi>Seed</hi> into barren <hi>Land,</hi> they are deceived, for they find not the <hi>Harveſt they expected,</hi> becauſe, as is aboveſaid, and ſhall
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:52222:98"/>be further ſaid more plainly, <hi>Gold</hi> is not the matter of our <hi>Stone</hi> in its whole Eſſence, nor yet <hi>Mercury,</hi> wherefore the bare mixture of theſe cannot <hi>Generate our Stone,</hi> for <hi>Gold,</hi> in the Work, is a <hi>Male</hi> to the Work of <hi>Generation,</hi> in whoſe moſt ſecret <hi>Reins</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> lies hid, which if it once ſend forth, being received in a due <hi>Matrix</hi> and conjoined with the paſſive <hi>female Seed,</hi> 'tis Cheriſhed with a due Heat, and <hi>Cibated</hi> with a proper Aliment, then truely we ſhall have from <hi>Gold</hi> abundantly to perform our Work. So neither a man, as he is man, can neither be called the Father, nor the matter of the <hi>Embrio:</hi> but he has in him ſuch a matter, from which by the Conjunction of a <hi>Diſſimilar ſperma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick matter,</hi> in the ſame kind, by an apt Diſpoſition the <hi>Infant</hi> is formed: In like manner we muſt underſtand of <hi>Gold.</hi> For <hi>Gold</hi> is the moſt perfect of all <hi>Metals,</hi> and the Father of our <hi>Stone,</hi> yet it is not the <hi>matter</hi> thereof
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:52222:98"/>for the <hi>Sperm</hi> which <hi>Gold</hi> ſends forth if it be handled by Art, will be the <hi>maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine matter</hi> of our <hi>Stone,</hi> and is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe then a moſt digeſted <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> which is Extracted from it by <hi>ſagacious Art,</hi> and then is called our <hi>Living Gold,</hi> and not <hi>vulgar,</hi> which is dead: So alſo in the Procreation of man, a man may be ſaid to be Dead, (Reſpect being had to to the <hi>Act of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi>) until he pours out the due matter which he hath in himſelf into a fit Place, juſt ſo tis in our Art; therefore our <hi>Gold</hi> is not <hi>vulgar Gold,</hi> for they differ as a Father differs from his <hi>Sperm</hi> which he hath, the firſt is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to our Work, and Living, the other dead and unprofitable, that is, ſends forth its <hi>Seed,</hi> which is the Active Virtue of our <hi>Stone.</hi> So therefore go ye on with a great deal of <hi>Caution,</hi> take this <hi>Body</hi> which I have Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, and ſweetly Extract the Seed from it, then (and not till then) this <hi>Gold</hi> (which before was Dead, Idle
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:52222:99"/>and uſeleſs) being made Living, active and fit for our Work, will ſupply thee with the firſt matter of our <hi>Stone,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>maſculine,</hi> and ſo is no longer called <hi>Gold</hi> by us, but <hi>Braſs, Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Lead, Dung,</hi> nor can it indeed properly be called <hi>Gold,</hi> for <hi>Gold</hi> is a <hi>Body</hi> but this a <hi>Chaos,</hi> that is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> nor will Return by any Art to its <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Species</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> becauſe the Body is turned into <hi>Spirit,</hi> from hence ſaith <hi>Menabdes,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>I order Poſterity to make Bodies incorporate. Hermes</hi> alſo ſays, <hi>O Son Extract the Shadow from the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dins,</hi>
                     </q> that is, Extract from the <hi>Gold</hi> which is called the Radius, its Seed which is called the Shaddow, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lies hidden and as it were in a Shade, and alſo becauſe it comes out under an obſcure Shade of <hi>Blackneſs. Ariſtotle</hi> alſo ſaith, <q>
                        <hi>The firſt thing that ye ought to do is to ſublime the Mercury, then caſt clean bodies into a clean Mercury.</hi>
                     </q> But I would have the Reader Admoniſht what ſort of <hi>ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> is here intended, for there are
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:52222:99"/>infinite falſe Erroneous and <hi>Sophiſtical Operations,</hi> one true and Natural, which notwithſtanding is done by Art, I omitting all theſe Vulgar <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> follow the Intention of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and mean that <hi>Sublimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which they call the Preparation of the Thin Matter, by which the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe</hi> of the <hi>Earthy Interpoſition</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Luna,</hi> that ſhe may receive Light from <hi>Sol,</hi> which comes to paſs when the <hi>Dark Sphere of Saturn</hi> which <hi>obnubilates</hi> the whole <hi>Horizon</hi> is van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed then <hi>Jupiter</hi> obtaining the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire aſcends into the Air with a <hi>ſplendid Cloud,</hi> whence ſincere, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and Lovely <hi>Dew</hi> drops upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> which mollifies it, and raiſeth great Winds in its Belly or boſom, which brings our <hi>Stone</hi> upward whence tis endued with Heavenly Virtue, which falling down again to the Earth which is its Nurſe, puts on a <hi>Terrene</hi> and Corporeal Nature, ſo it receives the Force of Inferiours
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:52222:100"/>and Superiours. We conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that neither <hi>Gold</hi> nor <hi>Mercury,</hi> can afford us the firſt <hi>matter</hi> of our <hi>Stone,</hi> until the Tincture be <hi>Extracted</hi> from <hi>Gold,</hi> the Diſſolvend, by <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Diſſolvent, which Tincture is a Living active virtue, not Dead as <hi>Gold</hi> was before its Diſſolution. This is the matter of the old <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> which we ought to take, which as the Author of the new Light ſayes, <q>is, but does not appear until the Artiſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, in knowing which all the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction conſiſts.</q> Wherefore I order you who ever would be ſearchers out of this Secret, that you would take that which is vile, and manifeſt to the whole world, out of which, by a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful manner, ye ſhall Extract that which is moſt hidden therein, that is our <hi>Menſtruum;</hi> and the <hi>Weſtern Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> is our <hi>Philoſophical Field,</hi> in which your <hi>Sol</hi> ſhall ariſe and aſcend; Join this with his Delectable <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> and let them lye in the <hi>bed of Love</hi>
                     <pb n="181" facs="tcp:52222:100"/>without ſtirring, until from this hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Nature (which is <hi>Mercury</hi> regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> there proceed a Living Virtue which may raiſe the Dead, then comes a Royal Off-ſpring, of which <hi>Sol</hi> is the Father, and <hi>Luna</hi> the Mother; and ſo you have a moſt true Explication of the new Light, you muſt take (ſaith the <hi>Author</hi>) <q>that which is, but is not ſeen till the <hi>Artiſt</hi> pleaſe, and you muſt uſe this, for the true matter of the old <hi>Philoſophers,</hi>
                     </q> and ſo we have ſpoken fully and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our <hi>body,</hi> and of our <hi>water;</hi> and of our <hi>Red Sulphur,</hi> and white <hi>Braſs.</hi> We have ſaid there ought to be added to theſe a <hi>Furnace, Veſſel</hi> and triple Fire: Note well what, and about what, I ſpeak here, for the Furnace is of Lute, or Brick, the Veſſel Glaſs, and the Fire Elementary, of which we will ſpeak lower in the laſt place of this little Treatiſe, concerning our Diſpoſition, but here we ſpeak of things Eſſentially and Subſtantially Conducing to the work. For the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:52222:101"/>
                     <hi>Furnace</hi> of Brick, is not wont to be called by us our <hi>Furnace,</hi> nor Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary <hi>fire</hi> ours, nor the Glaſs veſſel ours: for theſe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are common to us and <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> and they will excel us often in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity of theſe Externals. But we call thoſe things ours which they Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have nor can have, verily I ſay that our <hi>Fire,</hi> our <hi>Furnace,</hi> our <hi>Veſſel</hi> are ſecret, nor obvious but to <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> for they enter into the very Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our Work, hence a certain <hi>Philoſopher</hi> writing of this fire, ſayes, <q>
                        <hi>Behold the fire which I will ſhow thee is Water,</hi>
                     </q> alſo another witneſſeth thus of the Veſſel, <q>
                        <hi>The veſſel of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers is their water,</hi>
                     </q> another alſo writes, <q>
                        <hi>The Intention of all the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers is this, that all operations ſhould be made in their humid fire, in a ſecret furnace and veſſel,</hi>
                     </q> which Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies plainly enough declare another Fire, Veſſel and Furnace then are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known. Moreover my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let it not be a cauſe of ſcruple to thee, that I have before numbred,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:52222:101"/>our <hi>furnace, fire,</hi> and <hi>veſſel</hi> amongſt the things eſſentially Conſtituting our Stone, for in this I follow the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all <hi>Philoſophers</hi> writing in this Art. Concerning this Veſſel <hi>Sendivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> Writing, names it the Veſſel of Nature, alſo the Fire of Nature. <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, Artefius, Lully,</hi> and all the reſt have kept the ſame Method; it is plain therefore that they would have ſomething hidden from the eyes of the Vulgar. But I in good truth ſay, that theſe three are but one, for Nature is but one, the <hi>Adept</hi> Sons of <hi>Art</hi> do know, and will Witneſs this. For the Fire is, to the Excruciating of Bodies, more then fire, therefore it is called burning Wine and a moſt ſtrong fire, hence the <hi>Philoſopher, 'Burn our Braſs in moſt ſtrong fire;</hi> which whilſt <hi>Sophiſters</hi> hear, they are deceived, thinking it to be a fire of Coals or flame, which is contrary to our fire. concerning this <hi>John Mechungus</hi> ſpeak, <hi>"No artificial fire can infuſe ſo great a heat as that which comes from Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="addition">
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:52222:102"/>
                  <head>The Firſt Gate.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Concerning Philoſophical Calcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Not Printed in the Dutch Edition.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAlcination</hi> Purgeth our <hi>Stone,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores Natural Heat, deſtroys no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Radical <hi>Humidity,</hi> &amp; brings a due Solution to the <hi>Stone:</hi> The Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that it may be done <hi>Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> not vulgarly with <hi>Salts</hi> or <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> variouſly prepared, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver therefore truly deſires to Calcine, ſhould deſiſt from this Work till they underſtand our Caleination better, for that every Calcination deſtroys Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, deſtroying the Humidity of the <hi>Stone;</hi> we alſo do Reprobate all dry Calxes, for that we Increaſe the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical <hi>Humidity</hi> by <hi>Calcining,</hi> but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh none. In <hi>Calcination,</hi> we joyn
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:52222:102"/>Nature to its Nature, for that like loves like, if any one denies this he will not be worthy of the Name of a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> nor ever will get any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit from our Writings, for he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands them not. Therefore apply thou Nature to Nature, as Reaſon requires, ſeing all things have this from nature, that Like begets its Like, Man is begot by a Man, a Lion by a Lion, ſo let every thing be Calcined firſt in its proper nature. Learn this and never doubt to be benefited by it. Therefore we make Calxes unctuous both white and Red, which are not perfected but by three Degrees, they are fluid like Wax, other ways to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, nor are perfected, but in a year, to <hi>Tinge</hi> without a <hi>Fucus.</hi> But thou muſt take care in the firſt place Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Weight, for it is poſſible for thee to doubt in this: Leſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou ſhouldeſt looſe thy Labour, let the body be <hi>Calcined</hi> with <hi>Mercury,</hi> made ſo ſubtile, in which there is one
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:52222:103"/>part of the <hi>Solar</hi> quality, two of the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar,</hi> until the whole flow together like a Liquid Wax.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards Increaſe the <hi>Solar</hi> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in <hi>Mercury,</hi> that there may be four parts of him, two <hi>Lunar,</hi> ſo that thou ſhalt begin the work at the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the <hi>Trinity.</hi> Three parts of body, three of ſpirit, and to Compleat the Unity, let there be one part more of the ſpiritual, then the corporeal ſubſtance. This is proved by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Raymond, If any one ſeek the Proportion there, the Doctor hath demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to me the ſame. But</hi> Bacon <hi>hath taken three parts of the ſpirit to one of the body,</hi> I did not ſleep of many nights. But chooſe which way thou wilt.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:52222:103"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
